<TEI><body><text>
<!--*** THE WITCH OF HEBRON-->

<!--+++ H689g-->

<note resp="MJS" type="source">Mitchell Library, Harpur MS A87-2, p. 429.</note>

<pb n="1" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689g/30"/>
<note resp="Harpur">(From the Colonial Monthly Magazine)</note>
<note resp="Anonymous">mail us reply to letter sent Nov 14</note>

<head type="title">The Witch of Hebron</head>
<head type="subtitle"><author>By Charles Harpur</author></head>
<head type="subtitle"><hi rend="dul">Part I.</hi></head>

<lg><l>From noon until the setting of the sun,</l>
<l>The Rabbi Joseph on his knees had prayed,</l>
<l>When, from the Synagogue, a messenger</l>
<l>Came as directed, with an <hi rend="dul">I</hi>ndian page,</l>
<l>Who there had sought his presence, and who now</l>
<l>Before him bowing low, besought that he</l>
<l>Would hasten whither he was sent to lead him—</l>
<l>Even to the mansion of a <hi rend="dul">L</hi>ady, once</l>
<l>Of princely rank, and who now lying sink</l>
<l>Nigh unto death and griviously tormented,</l>
<l>Implored the comfort of his holy prayers.</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">The <hi rend="dul">R</hi>abbi, ever to the calls of sorrow</l>
<l>Open as day, arose; and girding straight</l>
<l>His robe about him, with the page went forth;</l>
<l>Who swiftly led him deep into the woods</l>
<l>That hung, heap over heap, like broken clouds,</l>
<l>Along the southern terraces of <hi rend="dul">H</hi>ebron:</l>
<l>When through a broad glade suddenly beheld,</l>
<l>A wonderous <del><hi rend="dul">P</hi>alace</del> structure, like a <hi rend="dul">P</hi>alace, showed</l>
<l>Its gleaming front and many-pillared porch,</l>
<l>Fretted with sculptured vinage, flowers and fruit,</l>
<l>Or rough with figures exquisitely wrought,</l>
<l>As by some <hi rend="dul">P</hi>hidian hand.</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">But interposed</l>
<l>A certain space in front, and belting all</l>
<l>The splendid structure with its beauty, smiled</l>
<pb n="2" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689g/31"/>
<l>A low-walled <hi rend="dul">G</hi>arden, cut with paven paths</l>
<l>Into divisions of a hundred shapes,</l>
<l>Yet all related, as concurring all</l>
<l>To form one perfect whole;—that glowed throughout</l>
<l>With rarest aromatic shrubs, and flowers</l>
<l>Effusing odors such as seemed to bring</l>
<l>Tidings from <hi rend="dul">P</hi>aradise, so rich their fame!</l>
<l>While intermixed judiciously with these</l>
<l>At happiest intervals, were pleasant growths</l>
<l>Of higher verdure gemm'd with golden fruit,</l>
<l>Or bright with silver blooms, and which below</l>
<l>Were glassed in fountains gleaming lambent lights,</l>
<l>Each like a shield of pearl.</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">But if thus rich</l>
<l>Was all without,—within, when he had entered,</l>
<l>More wondrous yet was what the <hi rend="dul">R</hi>abbi saw.</l>
<l>Halls worthy of <hi rend="dul">H</hi>erod the magnificent!</l>
<l>With pictured walls, and columns gleaming white</l>
<l>As <hi rend="dul">C</hi>armel's snow, or blue-veined as with life,</l>
<l>And from whose capitals suspended, hung</l>
<l>Sidonian tissues all with threaded gold</l>
<l>Embroidered, or all colored through with dyes</l>
<l>Of puce and purple—rich as sunset clouds.</l>
<l>And letting off from these were chambers, filled</l>
<l>With on pillowy couches of carved citron wood,</l>
<l>And tables in mosaic, upon which</l>
<l>Were lucent vases of <hi rend="dul">A</hi>rmenian art,</l>
<l>In crystal, and in alabaster, mixed</l>
<l>With ewers whose luminous transparency</l>
<l>Were stained with inward splendors,—caskets clamped</l>
<l>With ivory corners, and all sprigged with pearls,</l>
<l>And myrrhine cups, and lamps with golden globles</l>
<l>And feathery branches bearing pine-like cones,</l>
<l>From which long radianc<add>i</add>es, like spears of fire,</l>
<pb n="3" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689g/32"/>
<l>Protending, touched as into dazzling life</l>
<l>Clasps, viols, mirrors, of unspeakable cost:</l>
<l>A pomp of orient wealth, till thus beheld,</l>
<l>Merely incredible! While in every hall,</l>
<l>And in each chamber, passing or engaged,</l>
<l>Were trains of servitors of every clime,</l>
<l>Greeks, <hi rend="dul">P</hi>ersians, <hi rend="dul">I</hi>ndians, <hi rend="dul">E</hi>thiopians,—all</l>
<l>In richest though in various raiment clad.</l></lg>

<lg><l>Short time for wonder had the <hi rend="dul">R</hi>abbi, ere</l>
<l>The <hi rend="dul">P</hi>age returned and led him to a still</l>
<l>And distant chamber, where the sick one lay.</l>
<l>Which entering soon, such brilliance met his gaze</l>
<l>As shrunk the costliness of all that he</l>
<l>Had erewhile seen, though wondrous. Small indeed</l>
<l>This chamber was as with the rest compared,</l>
<l>Yet obviously contrived to fit a nice</l>
<l>And personal privacy. But all within</l>
<l>Its limits showed a sumptuousness extreme,</l>
<l>And spoke of lavish habits,—glowing all</l>
<l>With purple and gold, or interblazing quick</l>
<l>With royal jewels of a sumless worth,</l>
<add><metamark>V</metamark> <l>Wherewith all things of personal use and wont—</l>
<l>The mirrors, instruments, coronets and clasps,</l>
<l>Were studded as with stars effulging flames!</l></add>
<l>And in the midst of all this orient pomp,</l>
<l>On profuse pillows of the swan's new down,</l>
<l>Encased in the soft silk of <hi rend="dul">S</hi>hiraz,—lo,</l>
<l>A queen-like <hi rend="dul">W</hi>oman lay;—so beautiful,</l>
<l>That though upon her moon-bright visage, pain</l>
<l>And languor, like eclipsing shadows, gloomed,</l>
<l>The ancient <hi rend="dul">R</hi>abbi's pious heart was thrilled</l>
<l>With singular tremours as he looked upon her.</l>
<l>Young was she—but alas! from time to time,</l>
<l>O'er her fair face a hetic flush would break,</l>
<l>To leave that utter pallor which portends</l>
<l>The nearness of the tomb.</l>
</lg>
<fw>From</fw>
<pb n="4" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689g/33"/>
<lg><l part="F">From youth to age</l>
<l>Much had the <hi rend="dul">R</hi>abbi <hi rend="dul">J</hi>oseph sought in herbs</l>
<l>And minerals, the virtues they possess,</l>
<l>Soothing or pungent; and, by mixing these,</l>
<l>And so completing them as powers, to work</l>
<l>In their effects to a salubrious end,</l>
<l>With absolute integrity of art,</l>
<l>Had for <add>all</add> ailimemts fit medicaments.</l>
<l>Of these he offered her what to him seemed</l>
<l>Then needful. But the dying <hi rend="dul">W</hi>oman said:</l>
<l>Alas! I want not these, nor did I send</l>
<l>To implore thy presence, thinking thou couldst cure</l>
<l>A malady like mine,—so fell and fatal—</l>
<l>Yea, fatal as the funeral march of <hi rend="dul">T</hi>ime!</l>
<l>But simply that I might discharge my mind</l>
<l>Of a dread secret, that hath been to me</l>
<l>An ever-haunting and most ghostly fear,</l>
<l>Hanging and darkening, like an ominous cloud,</l>
<l>O'er all the ways and prospects of my life,</l>
<l>And which must end it ere the morning come.</l>
</lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">The Rabbi answered: If indeed it stand</l>
<l>Within my power to serve thee, pour at once</l>
<l>Thy sorrow all before me. But, if not,</l>
<l>And if thy woe hath any mortal taint,</l>
<l>Forbear, <hi rend="dul">O</hi> <hi rend="dul">W</hi>oman to acquaint my soul</l>
<l>With aught that, if advised, it would not seek,</l>
<l>Though covetous of knowledge; Or with aught</l>
<l>That only thenceforth could for horror chase</l>
<l>The memory of a man of <hi rend="dul">I</hi>srael.</l>
</lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">I am, said she, the daughter of thy friend</l>
<l>Rabbi <hi rend="dul">B</hi>en <hi rend="dul">B</hi>achai—be his memory blessed!</l>
<l>But now the widow of a Prince;—a man</l>
<l>Whose state was mainly pedigree, being one</l>
<fw>Of</fw>
<pb n="5" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689g/34"/>
<l>Of Ishmael's race.—Behold you this abode!</l>
<l>Did ever yet the tent-born Arab build</l>
<l>Thus for his pride or pleasure? See you all</l>
<l>These riches! Tell me, when were such amassed</l>
<l>By the grey <hi rend="dul">D</hi>esert's wild and wandering son?</l>
<l>Riches he could not even hoard in dreams,</l>
<l>As not by him conceivable. Ah, no!</l>
<l>Deadly and desperate was the game that won them!</l>
<l>And with a burning bitterness at best</l>
<l>Have I enjoyed them ever. And at last</l>
<l>How vainly now would I forego them all</l>
<l>To mend with a repentant hand my peace</l>
<l>In abject poverty. Their very taste,</l>
<l>Though to my sense but as a thing foregone,</l>
<l>How vainly now do I abhor—too late!</l>
</lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">Thus having spoken, calmly for awhile</l>
<l>In her pale loveliness she lay, with looks</l>
<l>Dreamily self-involved,—as if her mind</l>
<l>Were vaguely roaming in the fatal <hi rend="dul">P</hi>ast:</l>
<l>Then suddenly her beauteous countenance grew</l>
<l>Bedimm'd and dreary, like the eclipsëd moon;</l>
<l>Then darkened more, and writhed with horrid pangs,</l>
<l>Frightful to see! while evermore in this</l>
<l>Her burning agony she tossed about</l>
<l>Madly convulsed, and from her foaming lips</l>
<l>Words of so weird a meaning smite the ear</l>
<l>Of <hi rend="dul">R</hi>abbi <hi rend="dul">J</hi>oseph, that he bowed his head</l>
<l>And cast his eyes in holy horror down.</l>
</lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">And thus a space, bowed rigidly, he stood</l>
<l>As one transfixed—though pitying, and with prayer</l>
<l>Strengthening his soul. And when again his looks</l>
<l>He lifted to the <hi rend="dul">W</hi>oman—lo, that face</l>
<pb n="6" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689g/35"/>
<l>Which erewhile showed so ghastly-wild and weird,</l>
<l>Was cloudless as a summer heaven! The late</l>
<l>Dark brow was bright; the late pale cheek suffused</l>
<l>As with inevitable roseate bloom;</l>
<l>And wondrous more than all, her eyes that seemed</l>
<l>Before so sunken and so weary, now</l>
<l>Were big with splendors that about her shot</l>
<l>Electric influence! while her lips that erst</l>
<l>Were thin and faded as autumnal leaves,</l>
<l>Now full and crimson, curled with stormy pride,</l>
<l>Or quivered with a fierce voluptuousness!</l>
</lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">Well might the <hi rend="dul">R</hi>abbi stand in disbelief</l>
<l>Of all that now he saw. Could this be she</l>
<l>By whom, as dying, he so late had knelt?</l>
<l>This bold and beauteous being that now looked</l>
<l>So lovely-fierce—yea, terrible, in all</l>
<l>The bright audacity of passionate power?</l>
<l>But seeing his amazement, thus she spake.</l>
</lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">These are the common changes of the fell</l>
<l>And fatal ailment, that with torments <del>sta</del><add>strange</add></l>
<l>And varied, as thou seest, is tearing up</l>
<l>The dark foundations of my mortal state,</l>
<l>And sinking all its structures, hour by hour,</l>
<l>Into the dust of <hi rend="dul">D</hi>eath. But nothing now</l>
<l>Is left me, but to meet my nearing doom</l>
<l>As best I may, and suffer.</l>
</lg>

<lg><l part="F">Hearing which,</l>
<l>The <hi rend="dul">R</hi>abbi in his wisdom knew that she</l>
<l>Was troubled thus by the indwelling power</l>
<l>Of some strong <hi rend="dul">S</hi>pirit of <hi rend="dul">E</hi>vil, and on this</l>
<l>Sent straightway for an unction, wherewith erst</l>
<pb n="7" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689g/36"/>
<l>The famous ansestor whose name he bore,—</l>
<l>Herod the <hi rend="dul">G</hi>reat's chief hakim,—had expelled</l>
<l>The demon haunter of the dying <hi rend="dul">K</hi>ing.</l>
<l>'Twas brought him, and therewith did he at once</l>
<l>Annoint her forehead, and her eyes, and touch</l>
<l>The tips of all her fingers. Next he made</l>
<l>Within a consecrated crucible</l>
<l>A fire of citron-wood and cinnamon;</l>
<l>Then splashed the flames with insense,—every rite</l>
<l>Inspiriting with the influence of prayer.</l>
<l>And, as the smoke arose, he bowed her head</l>
<l>Into its coils, that so she might inhale</l>
<l>The salutary odour—till the <hi rend="dul">F</hi>iend</l>
<l>That dwelt within her should be thence expelled.</l>
</lg>
<fw>Again</fw>
<pb n="8" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689g/37"/>
<lg><l rend="indent1">Again a change came over her. Her face</l>
<l>Once more grew pale with pain; once more she writhed</l>
<l>In burning torment, uttering many words</l>
<l>Of most unhallowed meaning! Yet her eyes</l>
<l>Were fixed the while, and motionless her lips!</l>
<l>Whereby the <hi rend="dul">R</hi>abbi certainly perceived</l>
<l>'Twas not the <hi rend="dul">W</hi>oman of herself that spake—</l>
<l>But the dread <hi rend="dul">S</hi>pirit that possessed her soul.</l>
<l>And thus it cried aloud:</l></lg>
<divider type="double"/>
<note resp="Harpur">(To be continued.)</note>
<note resp="MJS">The folds in the paper and the annotations on the first page suggest that this first Part was sent to the <hi>Colonial Monthly</hi> but later returned to Harpur. The poem was never published except in the 1883 <hi>Poems</hi>. If Harpur made a fair copy of the other Parts, these have not survived. The Finding List includes the other draft fragments of the poem found in this manuscript as part of the one version. The underlining of capitals (presumably to assist the compositor) has been ignored in the transcription.</note>
</text></body></TEI>
