<TEI><body><text>
<!--*** THE WITCH OF HEBRON-->

<note resp="MJS" type="source">Mitchell Library, Harpur MS A87-2, pp.699-700,745-746</note>
<note resp="DS">Created 7/1/15. Reordered fragments to correspond to that in h689i.</note> 

<!--h689i, ll.1432ff.-->
<pb n="746" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689l/336"/>
<l part="F">An to this end</l>
<l>I now <del>enrobe</del><add>arrayed</add> my self in <app><rdg><del>whites that</del></rdg>
<rdg><del>ample</del> robes that seemed</rdg><rdg>robes that seemed</rdg></app></l>
<l><del>Th</del><add>Aereal</add> ultimates of perfect whiteness</l>
<l>While scarfs of purple such as only Queen</l>
<l>May purchase from the Indus caravans</l>
<l><del>Tinted</del><add>Barred</add> them with rainbow <del>splendors</del><add>tints</add>; a burnished band</l>
<l>Or purest gold, whose midst throughout was raised</l>
<l>With a full row of pearls—all perfect ovals—</l>
<l>Held in the <sic>wavevelets</sic> of my sunny hair:</l>
<l>A gem that seemed indeed a frozen mass</l>
<l>Of white fire, flashed upon my silk soft brow.</l>
<l>Then, in my loveliness, even thus arrayed,</l>
<l>I swam into his presence (though indeed</l>
<l>My hid feet rowed) graceful as a swan!</l>

<lg><l rend="indent1">"The Harem Girls applauded: <del>while within</del><add>while there seemed</add></l>
<l>Even in <sic>is</sic> own dull eyes almost a flash <del>and now a glow</del></l>
<l>As of extorted <del>pleasure</del><add>joy</add> but which <del>at once</del> became</l>
<l>At the next moment a malignant scoul,</l>
<l>Much had its <del>source</del><add>dark source</add> in a thought like this</l>
<l>As <del>I</del> learned after from a Nubian girl</l>
<l>Who always waited on his baser needs</l>
<l>"What did a soft and ignorant <sic>mix</sic> like me</l>
<l>Think to entrap </l>
<l>Who was the sharpest fellow, past a dout,</l>
<l>In the whole Orient. "Did a minx like me</l>
<l>Think to outwit a piece of such intelligence</l>
<l>By floating in before him, like a swan</l>
<l>A little better feathered than at first.</l></lg>

<lg><l>Even while the musing had been mustering up</l>
<l>The Harem ladies had been all dismissed</l>
<l>The Newbian Girl<del>s</del> alone remaining; then</l>
<l>A conclave of those singular Gnome-like things</l>
<l>Who housed no one knew where, <unclear>were</unclear> summoned in </l>
<l>Nor was the council long I was that night</l>
<l>Was to be poisoned—and with a pomegranate.</l>
<l>On given signals forth, were summoned in</l>
<l>One of a number to be <sic>plukct</sic> &amp; brought</l>
<l>For every lady of his Harem, forth</l>
<l>At Supper time out of his Summer Garden </l></lg>

<!--h689i, ll.1437ff-->
<pb n="700" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689l/289"/>
<note resp="DS"><ref target="http://setis.library.usyd.edu.au/ozedits/harpur/A90/00000157">A verbatim fragment of A90</ref>: a precursor? Overwritten with a cross and the word "Elsewhere".</note>
<note resp="MJS">The texts in A90 and A97 have been consulted in deciphering this difficult, if not at times impossible, hand. These draft lines below are also on p. 746 and may have preceded the version here. The first five lines are crossed out and "Elsewhere" written over them. The next two lines follow on more or less from these. The last two lines occur a little further on in Part VI (in other versions) and were presumably on pages of this version that are now lost.</note>
<l part="F"><metamark>X</metamark> A burnished brand</l>
<l>Of purest gold, whose midst throughout was raised</l>
<l>With a full row of pearls—all perfect ovals,</l>
<l>Held in the wavelets of my sunny hair.</l>
<l>A gem, that seemed indeed a frozen mass</l>
<l>Of white fire, flashed upon my silk-soft brow!</l>
<divider type="single"/>

<!--h689i, ll. 1481ff.-->
<pb n="745" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689l/335"/>
<note resp="DS"><ref target="http://setis.library.usyd.edu.au/ozedits/harpur/A97/00000222">
An approximate fragment of A90.</ref></note>
<l>And one too for himself, <del>though much he liked them not</del><add>though he disliked them</add></l>

<lg><l rend="indent1">"The Nubian had <sic>slipping</sic> away, and told me</l>
<l>All she had heard: <app><rdg><del>I of</del></rdg>
<rdg><del>Not much it</del> moved me</rdg>
<rdg>Yet <del>it</del> moved me not <del>much her news</del></rdg>
<rdg>Yet her news moved me not</rdg></app></l>
<l>So sure I felt that such was not my doom.</l>
<l>Or <sic>movered</sic> one most to this—the packing up</l>
<l><del>Much</del><add>Of</add> property, and things that <unclear/> ladies doat on.</l>
<l>But time abides not, we were sumond <del>into</del><add>forth</add></l>
<l>To supper. <del>In</del><add>On</add> the center-<unclear/> boar<expan>d</expan> a basket stood</l>
<l>Of silver <unclear>tint</unclear> <del>loaded</del><add>piled</add> high with crimson goards</l>
<l>These soon the King dispensed about the board</l>
<l>To every <unclear>lady one</unclear>—till two at last</l>
<l>Alone remained—one of these <del>was</del><add>being</add> marked</l>
<l>This came to me—of could I could but take it.</l>
<l>But on the instant fell as in a faint</l>
<l>That flurried all the ladies till they thronged</l>
<l>About me—flurried even the king himself.</l>
<l>With infinite dexterity again I came to life</l>
<l>Amid this bustled and exchanged the gourds</l>
<l>Took his, and <sic>lift</sic> him mine. This I ate.</l>
<l>And praised as being the very soul of fruit.</l>
<l>He also, with a rollac in his eye</l>
<l>Ate that which had been poisoned, and avowed</l>
<l>He never knew before what fruit it was</l>
<l>Nay, that it held with its crimson rind</l>
<l>The juice of Paradise.</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F"><del>While this went on</del><add>While this went on,</add></l>
<l>I slipped away <del>to where my girls were pack</del><add>wholly unseen to where <del>my</del></add></l>
<l>My goods were packed—and to prepare for flight</l>
<l>Nor had I long withdrawn, ere to my chamber</l>
<l>The Nubian girl came running; telling me</l>
<l>That soon the King had with a mighty start</l>
<l>Fall prostrate; while the Ladies all away</l>
<l>Had scattered like gossamer clouds</l>
<l>Before a storm-blast in a summer sky!</l>
<l>And that the chamber now was thronged instead</l>
<l>To suffocation, with a musty mass</l>
<l>Of bare-poled hakims and gre<expan>y</expan>haired Physicians,</l>
<l>Who all concurred at least in this—the dark</l>
<l>Affair in hand was quite unlooked for quite!</l></lg>

<!--h689i ll.1530ff-->
<pb n="699" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689l/288"/>
<del><l part="F">That all around</l></del>
<l><app><rdg><del>There were strong</del> symtoms of a</rdg>
<rdg><del>Having symtoms of a</del></rdg>
<rdg>And had strong symtoms of a</rdg></app> poison-case"</l>
<l>And as she told her news the Nubian laught</l>
<l>With infinite delight—so loved are kings.</l>
<add><metamark>x</metamark> <l>And I laughed also, feeling that I had</l>
<l>A natural and a perfect right to do so.</l></add>
<l>But no time might be wasted—and we fled</l>
<l>Together, loaded both with costly spoils.</l>
<l>Still as we passed beneath the <app><rdg><del>chamber</del></rdg>
<rdg><del>wonders of the court</del></rdg>
<rdg><del>airy</del> latticed Court</rdg></app></l>
<l>Wherein the Monarch suffered, all in vain</l>
<l>I strove to dash <del>the w</del><add>my womanly desire</add></l>
<l>To have a last look at him. So aloft</l>
<l>I mounted, on the slave's bent back—and looked.</l>
<l>The king was sprawling on the <del>walled</del><add>pillowy</add> florr,</l>
<l>With quite a herd of anxious quaks about him.</l>

<!-- h689i, ll.1544ff-->
<pb n="700" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689l/289"/>
<lg><l>Jews &amp; Armenians, infidels &amp; slaves,</l>
<l>All ranks, all races; and as still he took</l>
<l>Their nostrums, with grimaces horrible</l>
<l>He still kept threatening them, that if they failed</l>
<l>To cure him ere that dreadful night was passed</l>
<l>The dawn should see them headless—every man!</l>
<l><app><rdg>Then would he curs<del>t</del></rdg>
<rdg>Then would he curse the <del>though</del> that made him chose</rdg>
<rdg>Then would he curse the whim that made him chose</rdg>
<rdg>Then would wonder why <hi rend="ul">he</hi> <unclear/></rdg></app></l>
<l>Pomegranites <del>for</del><add>at</add> his supper. <del>But the most</del><add>Then in rage</add></l>
<l>He cursed his blunder, and the palpable trick</l>
<l>By which a silly woman had <app><rdg><del>entrapped</del></rdg><rdg><del><unclear/></del></rdg><rdg><add>o'erreached</add></rdg></app> him!</l>
<l>Then would he sprawl, and bellow like a beast.</l>
<l>And so I left him sprawling, while the sound</l>
<l><add>Of </add>his brute <app><rdg><del>bellowings</del></rdg><rdg><del><unclear/></del></rdg><rdg>ragings</rdg></app>, followed <del>me</del><add>us</add> beyond</l>
<l>The garden walls as through the dark we fled!</l>
<l><add>—We </add>heard long after, that he died ere he</l>
<l>Had time <add>to </add>cut off <emph rend="ul">all</emph> the <del>hakim's</del><add>doctors'</add> heads.</l></lg>

<!--h689i, ll. 1583ff-->
<pb n="700" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689l/289"/>
<note resp="DS"><ref target="http://setis.library.usyd.edu.au/ozedits/harpur/A90/00000162">An approximate fragment of A90.</ref></note>
<add><l>with <unclear>shin-bowed shanks</unclear> and bore</l></add>
<l>A brother-likeness to a huge baboon</l>
<note resp="MJS">The other non-contiguous fragments from Part VI in this manuscript are treated as a <ref target="h689m">separate version</ref>.</note>

<divider type="single"/>

</text></body></TEI>
