<TEI><body><text>
<!-- *** THE WITCH OF HEBRON [p. 150]-->

<!--+++ H689d-->

<note resp="MJS" type="source"><p>Mitchell Library, Harpur MS A90, pp. 150-160.</p></note>
<note resp="DS">Revised 8/1/15</note> 

<pb n="150" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689d/153"/>

<head type="parthead">Part VI</head>

<lg><l>Within a rustic chamber, dark and low,</l>
<l>And with wild-looking men &amp; women thronged,</l>
<l>I seemed to wake—but knew not <del><unclear/></del> what I was.</l>
<l>Nor how I had been thither brought: nor why?</l>
<l>I was not large, my consciousness ere long</l>
<l>Had measured that fact. Inwardly I felt</l>
<l>No buskness of existence, but a sense</l>
<l>Of languor rather, or revival slow.</l>
<l>And ever more the men &amp; women same</l>
<l>And looked at me with wonder, and with shouts</l>
<l>Significant of conformed astonishment</l>
<l>Then would the whirl about the room in dance</l>
<l>Abandoned to their barbarous delights!</l>
</lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">As thus I <add>surely</add> strengthened into life</l>
<l>I looked about the chamber, half in hope</l>
<l>And half in fear, of seeing it might be</l>
<l>The mighty Angel who now ruled my life</l>
<l>My gestures were mistaken for a wish</l>
<l>To breathe the open air; <del>and forth at once<lb/>The bore me</del><add>and I was borne</add></l>
<l>Towards a wide-casement. Like a picture large</l>
<l>The world without, and instantly confirmed</l>
<l>My hitherto vague impression that a new</l>
<l>Life-change had passed upon me. On all hands</l>
<l>Nothing but mountains feathered to their tips</l>
<l>With a dense fell of pines, and valleys filled</l>
<l>With a cold darkness that was <del>filled</del><add>lit</add> alone</l>
<l>By the broad flashes of the furious torrent</l>
<l>That leaped in thunder down from marble gaps</l>
<l>Was seen in prospect. Over all a low</l>
<l>Dull vapour, like a canopy of smoke,</l>
<l>And so obscured the sun, that I had <del><unclear/></del> thought</l>
<l>The scene that now I saw was not of Earth</l>
<l>But <del>that</del><add>for</add> a golden flush that now and then</l>

<pb n="151" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689d/154"/>

<l>Would touch the highest ranges. <del>And at this</del> What I had</l>
<l>Indeed become I knew not, but I still</l>
<l>Retained impressions of my former roots</l>
<l>And often made vain efforts to expand</l>
<l>The <unclear/> I had no longer, and sail off</l>
<l>And though those sullen vapours—up, and up</l>
<l>Into the mighty silence of the blue.</l>
</lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">The day was fading, and a blare of horns</l>
<l>With <unclear/> voice and much trampling noise</l>
<l>Heard from without around me. And ere long</l>
<l>The women that been before around me</l>
<l>Again rushed in—each bearing some such robe</l>
<l>Or <add>some</add> gay bauble, wherewithal they soon</l>
<l>Arrayed me to their task, and holding then</l>
<l>Armour up before, I perceived</l>
<l>My soul had this time passed into the form</l>
<l>A young female. The whole truth was this</l>
<l><del>The being whom I</del><add>The being whom I</add> now reanimated</l>
<l>Was the sole child of a Circassian Chief</l>
<l>A maiden of most memoral beauty</l>
<l>Who had been long regarded by her house</l>
<l>As its chief treasured, and as such reserved</l>
<l><del>To</del><add>For</add> him alone no matter whence, he came</l>
<l>Whose lust could dip into the longest purse</l>
<l>But Envy lurks in the Circussian hills</l>
<l><del>As</del> As <del>she lurks</del> elsewhere, and a dose of opium,</l>
<l>Administered by one who had been long</l>
<del><l>The rival beauty of a neighboring tribe</l>
<l>Had squashed</l></del>
<l>The rival beauty of a neighboring tribe</l>
<l>Had served to quash a quite complete</l>
<l>Save in the final payment of the gold</l>
<l>Which had been even offered and told down</l>
<l>And only <hi rend="ul">not</hi> excepted by some old</l>
<l>Delaying ceremony of the tribe;</l>
<l>And in which luckless circumstance, 'twas plain</l>
<l>That both my admirable parents saw</l>
<l>The unkindest cut of all.</l>
</lg>

<pb n="152" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689d/155"/>

<lg><l rend="indent1">On all hands forth</l>
<l>Had scouts been sent, to summon all the tribe</l>
<l>To attend my obsequies, and then forthwith</l>
<l>To exterminate our ancient enemies!</l>
<l>But while these things were pending, lo, the light</l>
<l>Had broken like a morning from the eyes</l>
<l>Of the dead beauty; on her cheeks had dawned</l>
<l>A roseate color; from her moistening lips</l>
<l>Low murmers too had broken: whereupon</l>
<l>My parents, in the exultant hope of still</l>
<l>Consummating their bargain, had transformed</l>
<l>The fancial to a general tribal feast</l>
<l>And loaded me with all the family gauds</l>
<l>And ornaments they held. The Persian too</l>
<l>Had been inverted to renew his purchase</l>
<l>And carry me at once beyond the chance</l>
<l>Of future opium doses</l>
</lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">With the rest</l>
<l>Back had he galloped, and was now without,</l>
<l>Eager once more to bear me to the arms</l>
<l>Of his long-bearden Lord. Within he came</l>
<l>In wonder, but full ready to make good</l>
<l>His former bargain and pay down the <del>gold</del><add>price</add></l>
<l>My worthy parents tenderly embraced me,</l>

<pb n="153" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689d/156"/>

<l>With many tears, protesting that I was</l>
<l>The life light of their eyes—their rose of Joy!</l>
<l>Then stretched their palms out for the Persian gold,</l>
<l>And hurried off to tell it oer in secret:</l>
<l>The dear recovered treasure they so late</l>
<l>Had mourned, as lost for ever. On that night</l>
<l>I was packed carefully on a camel's back</l>
<l>Beside a case of porcelain pipes and gini-cracks</l>
<l>And carried Persia-ward, by stages long</l>
<l>From the Circussian mountains.</l>
</lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">At the court</l>
<l>I soon became the favorite of the king;</l>
<l>Lived sumptuously, but in perpetual fear.</l>
<l>My food was served to me on plates of gold</l>
<l>I slept on beds the furniture of which</l>
<l>Were fringed with countless pearls; and yet no less</l>
<l>I envied the poor slave who swept the floors</l>
<l>My Persian Lord for one whole month had been</l>
<l>Devoted to me—for a month and more:</l>
<l>And then I heard my place was to be filled</l>
<l>By a new favorite. And strange to say,</l>
<l>Albeit I loathed him as we loathe a snake,</l>
<l>I could not bear that he should thus supply</l>
<l>My presence with another. I would make</l>

<pb n="154" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689d/157"/>

<l>An effort to regain his faded favor:</l>
<l>For I was beautiful—and therefore vain</l>
<l>As beauty needs must be. And to that end</l>
<l>I now arrayed myself in robes that seemed</l>
<l>Aeriel ultimates of perfect whiteness,</l>
<l>While scarfs of purple such as only queen's</l>
<l>May purchase from the Indus Caravans,</l>
<l>Barred them with rainbow tints; a burnished band</l>
<l>Of purest gold, whose midst throughout was raised</l>
<l>With a full row of pearls—all perfect ovals—</l>
<l>Held in the wavelets of my sunny hair:</l>
<l>A gem that seemed indeed a frozen mass</l>
<l>Of white fire, flashed upon my silk-soft brow.</l>
<l><del>And</del><add>Then</add> in my loveliness, even thus arrayed,</l>
<l>I swam into his presence (though indeed</l>
<l>My hid feet rowed me) graceful as a swan!</l>
</lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">The Harem girls applauded, while thus seemed</l>
<l>Even in his own dull eyes almost a flash</l>
<l>As of exhorted joy: but which became</l>
<l>At the next moment a malignant scowl,</l>
<l>Which had its dark source in such thoughts as these:</l>
<l>(As <del>from a Nubean girl <unclear/> I after learned</del><add>I learned after from a Nubean girl</add></l>
<l>Who always waited in his baser needs)</l>

<pb n="155" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689d/158"/>

<l>"What! did a soft and ignorant minx like me</l>
<l>Think to entrap again a man like <hi rend="ul">him</hi>,</l>
<l>Who was the sharpest fellow, past all doubt,</l>
<l>In all the orient? Did a minx so raw</l>
<l><del>Think</del><add>Ween</add> to outwit a piece of such intelligence,</l>
<l>By floating in before him, like a swan,</l>
<l>A little better feathered than at first?"</l>
</lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">Even while this mischief had been mustering up,</l>
<l>The Harem ladies had been all been dismissed,</l>
<l>The Nubean girl alone remaining; then</l>
<l>A conclave of those singular gnome-like <del>things</del><add>dwarfs</add></l>
<metamark>x</metamark> <app><rdg><l>Who <del>housed</del> no one knew <del>where</del>, were summoned in:</l></rdg>
<rdg><l><del>Who came no one knew whence, were summoned in</del></l></rdg>
<rdg><l>Who from their secret dens and holes would come</l>
<l>At given signals forth, were summoned in</l></rdg></app>
<l>Nor was the council long: I on that night</l>
<l>Was to be poisoned—and with a pomegranate,</l>
<l>One of a number to be pluckt and brought</l>
<l>For every lady of his Harem, forth</l>
<l>At supper, from his <add>favorite</add> Summer Garden <del>trees</del>,</l>
<l>And one too for himself, though he disliked them.</l>
</lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">The Nubean had slipped away and told me</l>
<l>All she had learned: yet her news moved me not,</l>
<l>So sure I felt that such was not my doom;</l>
<l>Or moved me but to this—the packing up</l>

<pb n="156" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689d/159"/>

<l>Of such gay properties as ladies doat on</l>
<l>But time slid on, and we were summoned forth</l>
<l>To supper. On the centre board <del>of a crate</del> there stood</l>
<l>Of silver <del>lined</del> crate piled high with crimson goards</l>
<l>And these the king despersed amongst us soon,</l>
<l>To every lady one; till two at last</l>
<l>Alone remained, one of them being marked.</l>
<l>This came to me, nor could I but accept it,</l>
<add><l>But mindful of the part I had to play,</l></add>
<del><l>But on the instant</l></del>
<l>Even as I took it I fell fainting down</l>
<l>And flurried all the ladies, till they thronged</l>
<l>About me—flurried even the king himself.</l>
<l>With infinite dexterity I then</l>
<l>Revived as suddenly, and contrived the while</l>
<l>Amid the bustle to exchange the goards—</l>
<l>Took his, and left him mine. His soon I ate</l>
<l>And praised as being the very soul of fruit.</l>
<l>He also with a rollic in his eye</l>
<l>Ate that which had been poisoned, and avowed</l>
<l>He never knew before what fruit it was,</l>
<l>Nay, that it held within its crimson rind</l>
<l>The juice of Paradise.</l>
</lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">While this went on</l>
<l>I had slipped away wholly unseen to where</l>
<l>My goods were packed, and to prepare for flight.</l>

<pb n="157" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689d/160"/>

<l>Nor had I long withdrawn, ere to my chamber</l>
<l>The Nubean girl came running; telling me</l>
<l>That soon the king had with a monstrous snort</l>
<l>Fall'n prostrate; while the ladies all away</l>
<l>Had scattered like a flock of gossamer clouds</l>
<add><l>Before a storm wind in a summer sky</l></add>
<l>And that the chamber now was thronged instead,</l>
<l>To suffocation, with <del>musty</del><add>fusty</add> mass</l>
<l>Of <del>b</del><add>bare-poled</add> hakims and grey-haired Physicians,</l>
<l>Who all concurred at least in this—the dark</l>
<l>Affair in hand was quite unlooked for—quite,</l>
<l>And had strong symptoms of a "poison-case"</l>
<l>And as she told her news the Nubean laughed</l>
<l>With infinite delight—so loved are kings!</l>
<l>And I laughed also, feeling that I had</l>
<l>A natural and a perfect night to do so.</l>
<l>But no time might be wasted—and we fled</l>
<l>Together, loaded both with costly spoils.</l>
<l>Still as we passed beneath the latticed Court</l>
<l>Wherein the Monarch suffered, all in vain</l>
<l>I strove to dash my womanly desire</l>
<l>To have a last look at him. So aloft</l>
<l>I mounted, on the slave's bent back—and looked.</l>
<l>The king was sprawling on the pillowy floor,</l>
<l>With quite a herd of anxious quacks about him;</l>

<pb n="158" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689d/161"/>

<l>Jews &amp; Armenians, infidels and slaves,</l>
<l>All ranks, all races; and as still he took</l>
<l>Their nostrums, with grimaces horrible,</l>
<l>He still kept threatening them, that if they failed</l>
<l>To cure him ere that dreadful night were past,</l>
<l>The dawn should see them headless—every man!</l>
<l>Then would he <del>curse the whim that made him choose</del><add>wonder, why he ever chose</add></l>
<l>Pomegranates for his supper. Then in rage</l>
<l>He cursed his blunder, and the palpable trick</l>
<l>By which a silly woman had o'er reached him!</l>
<l>Then would he sprawl, and bellow like a beast!</l>
<l>And so I left him sprawling, while the sound</l>
<l>Of his brute ragings followed us beyond</l>
<l>The Garden bounds as through the dark we fled!</l>
<l>—We heard long after, that he died ere he</l>
<l>Had time to cut off <hi rend="ul">all</hi> the doctor's heads.</l>
</lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">With a strong spirit of mischied in my head,</l>
<l>I was not bad at heart; for <del>those</del><add>they</add> who knew</l>
<l>Me closely, and the closlier they knew me</l>
<l>Though they saw thus,—and not the less perhaps,</l>
<l>If of the women sort, because 'twas plain</l>
<l>My conduct most was from its balance thrown</l>
<l>By wherein, and by human almost mad <del>,</del>—</l>
<l>These always, and the closlier they knew me,</l>

<pb n="159" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689d/162"/>

<l>Loved me—nay, served as the Nubian did.</l>
<l>And now as no one else might sell me—lo,</l>
<l>I sold myself, and thought that I had made</l>
<l>A capital bargain, till I found myself</l>
<l>Throned as the wife of a rude Afric Chief,</l>
<l>Black as a log of ebony, and who</l>
<l>As still at stated times, in motley state,</l>
<l>On bow-bent shanks and <del>huge</del><add>big</add> pot-bellied bulk,</l>
<l>He strode before us, bore I must confess</l>
<l>Much brother likeness to a huge baboon</l>
<l>But luckily the monster soon preferred</l>
<l>The Nubian to myself—a consummation</l>
<l>That filled me with much thankfulness of heart</l>
</lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">'Twere long to tell whay haps befell me next:</l>
<l>I was the capture of a Bedoine <del>sh</del><add>shiek</add></l>
<l>And fed his camels, while I served his lusts;</l>
<l>Was sold in the slave mart of Astrachan</l>
<l>And carried thence beyond the Ganges, where</l>
<l>A Rajahpoot received me as his queen.</l>
<l>A Turcoman horse stealer owned me next,</l>
<l>At once his water-carrier and his wife.</l>
<l>At <del>Constantinople</del><add>Alexandria</add> I became the slave</l>
<l>Of a harsh Roman matron, who was wont</l>

<pb n="160" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689d/163"/>

<l>To flog and famish me to make me good;</l>
<l>And when I owned myself converted, then</l>
<l>She flogged and famished <add>one</add> the more to make</l>
<l>My goodness lasting. But this much of change</l>
<l>In the contexture of my fatal past</l>
<l>But troubles and distracts me. The extreme</l>
<l>Is what I best remember: I was now</l>
<l>A queen; and now a drudge: and finally</l>
<l>Fell stabbed in Cairo—slaughtered by a slave.</l>
</lg>

</text></body></TEI>
