<TEI><body><text>

<!--*** THE WITCH OF HEBRON-->

<!--+++ H689h-->

<note resp="MJS" type="source">Mitchell Library, Harpur MS A94, p. 97.</note>
<note resp="MJS">These lines are the end of Part VI and lines 8- of Part VII and have been lined through with a thick nib. This fragment does not match up with any of the others. There is a ?signature in the bottom right-hand corner, "I.L./ ci." The meaning of "Cse." at the top of the page is unclear.</note>
<note resp="DS">Revised 8/1/15</note> 

<pb n="97" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689h/103"/>

<div type="poempart">

<lg><l>That filled me with much thankfulness of heart.</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">'Twere long to tell what haps befell me next.</l>
<l>I was the captive of a Bedoine shiek,</l>
<l>And fed his camels while I served his lusts;</l>
<l>Was sold in the slave mart of Astrachan</l>
<l>And carried thence to India, to be crowned</l>
<l>A Rajahpoot's sultana; from which state</l>
<l>Flying at length, I <del>fled</del><add>fell</add> into a worse</l>
<l>Being pounced on by a Turcoman horse-stealer</l>
<l><add>Who made me, with much liberal self-applause,</add></l>
<l>At once his mistress and his water-carrier.</l>
<l>At Adrianople I became the slave</l>—
<l>Of a harsh Roman matron, who was wont</l>
<l>To flog and famish me to make me good,</l>
<l>And when I owned myself converted, then</l>
<l>She flogged and famished me the more, to make</l>
<l>My goodness lasting. But this mush of change</l>
<l>In the contexture of my fatal life</l>
<l>But troubles and distracts me. The extremes</l>
<l>Is what I best remember: I was now</l>
<l>A queen, and now a drudge: and finally</l>
<l>Fell stabbed in Cairo—slaughtered by a slave.</l></lg>
</div>
<divider type="diamond"/>

<div type="poempart">

<lg><l>Again I had some deep-down hold <del>of</del><add>on</add> being,</l>
<l>Dim as an oister's in its ocean bed;</l>
<l>An aboriginal inception, <del>like</del><add>yea</add></l>
<l><del>Quick inter-knitting</del><add>A self-producing</add> knot<del>s</del> of living roots</l>
<l>Which terminated all in one smooth surface:</l>
<l><add><metamark>^</metamark> With as it were tentacula that search</add></l>
<l>The confines of my circumscribed <del>sedate</del> abode</l>
<l>Then came a sence of free space, light, and air,</l>
<l><del>Then</del><add>And then</add> of hunger, and along with this</l>
<l>Strong suctatorial powers. I could detect</l>
<l>Sweet food from sour—warm presences from cold;</l></lg>
</div>


</text></body></TEI>
