<TEI><body><text>
<!--*** THE WITCH OF HEBRON-->

<!--+++ H689i-->

<note resp="MJS" type="source">Mitchell Library, Harpur MS A97, pp. 179-234.</note>
<note resp="MJS">The poem constitutes Manuscript no. 14 on blue lined paper. On the title-page, "An Australian Composed 1868" has been added by Mrs Harpur. A distinction has been made in the coding between corrections made (concurrently?) in ink and those made (subsequently?) in pencil.</note>
<note resp="DS">Revised 8/1/15</note> 

<pb n="179" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/180"/>

<div type="titlepage">

<head type="title">The Witch of Hebron:/ A Rabbinical Legend:/ By/ Charles Harpur./ <add>An Australian  Composed <date>1868</date></add></head></div>

<pb n="181" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/182"/>

<div type="poempart">
<head type="parthead">Part I.</head>

<lg><l>From morn until the setting of the sun</l>
<l>The Rabbi Joseph on his knees had prayed,</l>
<l>When, from the Synagogue, a Messenger</l>
<l>Came, as directed, with an Indian page</l>
<l>Who there had sought his presence, and who now</l>
<l>Before him bowing low, besought that he</l>
<l>Would hasten whither he was sent to lead <del><hi rend="del-pencil">him</hi></del>—</l>
<l>Even to the mansion of a Lady, once</l>
<l>Of princely rank, and who, now lying sick</l>
<l>Nigh unto death and grievously <del><hi rend="del-pencil">tormented</hi></del><add><hi  rend="pencil">dismayed</hi></add>,</l>
<l>Implored the comfort of his holy prayers.</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">The Rabbij, ever to the call of sorrow</l>
<l>Open as day, arose; and girding straight</l>
<l>His robe about him, with the Page went forth;</l>
<l>Who swiftly led him deep into the woods</l>
<l>That hung, heap over heap, like broken clouds,</l>
<l>Along the southern terraces of Hebron:</l>
<l>When, through a broad glade suddenly beheld,</l>
<l>A wondrous structure, like a Palace, showed</l>
<l>Its gleaming front and many-pillared porch,</l>
<l>Fretted with sculptured vinage, flowers and fruit,</l>
<l>Or rough with figures exquisitely wrought,</l>
<l>As by some Phidian hand.</l></lg>

<pb n="182" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/183"/>

<lg><l part="F">But interposed</l>
<l>A certain space in front, and belting all</l>
<l>The splendid Structure with its beauty, smiled</l>
<l>A low-walled Garden cut with paven paths</l>
<l>Into divisions of a hundred shapes,</l>
<l>Yet all related, as concurring all</l>
<l>To form one perfect whole;—that glowed throughout</l>
<l>With rarest aromatic shrubs, and flowers,</l>
<l>Effusing odors such as seemed to bring</l>
<l>Tidings from Paradise, so rich their fume!</l>
<l>While intermixed judi<expan>ci</expan>ously with these</l>
<l>At happiest intervals, were pleasant growths</l>
<l>Of higher verdure gemm'd with golden fruit,</l>
<l>Or bright with silver blooms, and which below</l>
<l>Were glassed in fountains gleaming lambent lights,</l>
<l>Each like a shield of pearl.</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">But if thus rich</l>
<l>Was all without—within, when he had entered,</l>
<l>More wondrous yet was what the Rabbi saw.</l>
<l>Halls worthy of Herod the magnificent!</l>
<l>With pictured walls, and columns gleaming white</l>
<l>As Carmel's snow, or blue-veined as with life,</l>
<l>And from whose capitals suspended, hung</l>
<l>Sidonian tissues all with threaded gold</l>
<l>Embroidered, or all colored through with dyes</l>
<l>Of puce and purple—rich as sunset clouds.</l>
<l>And letting off from these, were chambers, filled</l>
<l>With pillowy couches of carved citron wood,</l>
<l>And tables in mosaic, upon which</l>
<l>Were lucent vases of Armenian art,</l>
<l>In crystal, and in alabaster, mixed</l>
<l>With ewers whose luminous transparency</l>
<l>Were stained with inward splendors,—caskets, clamped</l>

<pb n="183" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/184"/>

<l>With ivory corners, and all sprigged with pearls,</l>
<l>And myrrhine cups, and lamps with <del>globes of gold</del><add>golden globes</add></l>
<l>And feathery branches bearing pine-like cones,</l>
<l>From which long radiancies, like spears of fire,</l>
<l>Protending, touched as into dazzling life</l>
<l>Clasps, viols, mirrors of unspeakable cost—</l>
<l>A pomp of orient wealth, till thus beheld,</l>
<l>Merely incredible. While in every hall,</l>
<l>And in <del>every</del><add>each</add> chamber, passing or ingaged,</l>
<l>Were trains of servitors of every clime,</l>
<l>Greeks, Persians, Indians, Ethiopeans,—all</l>
<l>In richest though in various raiment clad.</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">Short time for wonder had the Rabbi, ere</l>
<l>The Page returned and led him to a still</l>
<l>And distant chamber where the sick One lay:</l>
<l>Which entering soon, such brilliance met his view</l>
<l>As shrunk the costliness of all he had</l>
<l>Seen erewhile, though so wondrous. Small indeed</l>
<l>This chamber was as with the rest compared</l>
<l><add><hi rend="pencil">Being obviously contrived</hi></add> to fit a nice</l>
<l>And personal privacy: but all within</l>
<l>Its limits showed a sumptuousness extreme</l>
<l>And spoke of lavish habits,—glowing all</l>
<l>With purple and gold, or interblazing quick</l>
<l>With royal jewels of a sumless worth,</l>
<l>Wherewith all things of personal use and wont—</l>
<l>The mirrors, instruments, coronets and clasps,</l>
<l>Were studded as with stars effulging flames!</l>
<l>And in the midst of all this orient pomp,</l>
<l>On profuse pillows of the swan's new down,</l>
<l>Encased in the soft silk of Shiraz,—lo,</l>
<l>A queen-like Woman lay;—so beautiful,</l>
<l>That though upon her moon-bright visage, pain</l>

<pb n="184" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/185"/>

<l>And languor, like eclipsing shadows, gloomed,</l>
<l>The ancient Rabbi's pious heart was thrilled</l>
<l>With singular tremours as he looked upon her.</l>
<l>Young was she—but alas! from time to time,</l>
<l>O'er her fair face a hectic flush would break,</l>
<l>To leave that utter pallor which portends</l>
<l>The nearness of the tomb.</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">From youth to age</l>
<l>Much had the Rabbi Joseph sought in herbs,</l>
<l>And minerals, the virtues they possess,</l>
<l>Soothing or pungent; and, by mixing these</l>
<l>With much-informed integrity of art,</l>
<l>And so completing them as powers, that work</l>
<l>In their effects to a salubrious end,</l>
<l>Had for all ailments fit medicaments.</l>
<l>Of these he offered her what to him seemed</l>
<l>Then needful. But the dying Woman said:</l>
<l>Alas! I want not these, nor did I send</l>
<l>To entreat thy presence, thinking thou couldst cure</l>
<l>A malady like mine—so fell and fatal—</l>
<l>Yea, fatal as the funeral march of Time!</l>
<l>But simply that I might discharge my mind</l>
<l>Of a dread secret that has been to me</l>
<l><sic>And</sic> ever-haunting and most ghostly fear,</l>
<l>Hanging and darkening, like an ominous cloud,</l>
<l>O'er all the ways and prospects of my life,</l>
<l>And which must end it ere the morning come.</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">The Rabbi answered: If indeed it stand</l>
<l>Within my power to serve thee, pour at once</l>
<l>Thy sorrows all before me. But if not,</l>
<l>And if thy sin hath any mortal taint,</l>
<l>Forbear, O Woman, to acquaint my soul</l>

<pb n="185" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/186"/>

<l>With aught that, if advised, it would not seek,</l>
<l>Though covetous of knowledge; or with aught</l>
<l>That only thenceforth could for horror chase</l>
<l>The memory of a man of Israel.</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">I am, she said, the daughter of thy friend</l>
<l>Rabbi Ben Bachai—be his memory blest!</l>
<l>But thou has long forgotten one, who once</l>
<l>Played at thy side, a laughing child,—and who</l>
<l>Is now the widow of a Prince,—a man</l>
<l>Whose state was mainly pedigree, being one</l>
<l>Of Ishmael's race. Behold you this abode!</l>
<l>Did ever yet the tent-born Arab build</l>
<l>Thus for his pride or pleasure? See you all</l>
<l>These riches! Tell me; when were such amassed</l>
<l>By the grey Desert's wild and wandering son?</l>
<l>Riches he could not even hoard in dreams,</l>
<l>As not by him concievable. Ah, no!</l>
<l>Deadly and desperate was the game that won them!</l>
<l>And with a burning bitterness at best</l>
<l>Have I enjoyed them! And how vainly now</l>
<l>Would I at last forego them all, to mend</l>
<l>My broken peace with a repentent heed</l>
<l>In abject poverty! Their very taste,</l>
<l>So doubly deadly, as a thing foregone,</l>
<l>How vainly now do I abhor—too late!</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">Thus having spoken, calmly for awhile</l>
<l>In her pale loveliness she lay, with looks</l>
<l>Dreamily self-involved,—as if her mind</l>
<l>Were vaguely roaming in the fatal Past:</l>
<l>Then suddenly her beauteous countenounce grew</l>
<l>Bedimm'd and dreary, like the eclipséd moon</l>
<l>When o'er it passes the predicted wraith;</l>

<pb n="186" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/187"/>

<l>Then darkened <del>more</del><add>worse</add>, and writhed with horrid pangs,</l>
<l>Till more and more in this her burning woe</l>
<l>She tossed about, as one through all her frame,</l>
<l>Madly convulsed! while from her foaming lips</l>
<l>Words of so weird a meaning smote the ear</l>
<l>Of Rabbi Joseph, that he bowed his head</l>
<l>And cast his eyes in holy horror down.</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">And thus a space, bowed rigidly, he stood</l>
<l>As one transfixed—though pitying, and with prayers</l>
<l>Strengthening his soul. And when again his looks</l>
<l>He lifted to the Woman—lo, that face</l>
<l>Which erewhile showed so ghastly-wild and weird,</l>
<l>Was cloudless as a summer heaven! The late</l>
<l>Dark brow was bright; the late pale cheek<del><unclear/></del> suffused</l>
<l>As with inevitable roseate bloom;</l>
<l>And wondrous more than all, her eyes that seemed</l>
<l>Before so sunken and so weary, now</l>
<l>Were big with splendors that about her shot</l>
<l>Electric influence! while her lips that erst</l>
<l>Were thin and faded as autumnal leaves,</l>
<l>Now full and crimson, curled with stormy pride,</l>
<l>Or quivered with a fierce voluptuousness!</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">Well might the Rabbi stand in disbelief</l>
<l>Of all that now he saw. Could this be she</l>
<l>By whom, as dying, he so late had knelt?</l>
<l>This bold and beauteous Being that now looked</l>
<l>So lovely-fierce—yea, terrible, in all</l>
<l>The bright audacity of passionate power?</l>
<l>But seeing his amazement, thus she spake.</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">These are the common changes of the fell</l>
<l>And fatal ailment, that with torments strange</l>

<pb n="187" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/188"/>

<l>And varied, as thou seest, is tearing up</l>
<l>The dark foundations of my mortal state,</l>
<l>And sinking all its structures, hour by hour,</l>
<l>Into the dust of Death. But nothing now</l>
<l>Is left me, but to meet my <del>com</del><add>nearing</add> doom</l>
<l>As best I may, and suffer.</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">Hearing which</l>
<l>The Rabbi in his wisdom knew that she</l>
<l>Was troubled thus by the indwelling power</l>
<l>Of some strong Spirit of Evil,—and on this</l>
<l>Sent straightway for an unction, wherewith erst</l>
<l>The famous ancestor whose name he bore—</l>
<l>Herod the Great's chief hakim—had expelled</l>
<l>The demon Haunter of the dying King.</l>
<l>'Twas brought him, and therewith did he at once</l>
<l>An<del><hi rend="del-pencil"></hi></del>oint her forehead, and her eyes, and touch</l>
<l>The tips of all her fingers. Next he made</l>
<l>Within a consecrated crucible,</l>
<l>A fire of citron wood and cinnamon;</l>
<l>Then splashed the flames with incense,—every rite</l>
<l>Inspiriting with the influence of prayer.</l>
<l>Then, as the smoke arose, he bowed her head</l>
<l>Into its coils, that so she might inhale</l>
<l>Its salutary odour—till the Fiend</l>
<l>That dwelt within her should be thence expelled.</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">Again a change came over her. Her face</l>
<l>Once more grew pale with pain; once more she writhed</l>
<l>In burning torment, uttering many words</l>
<l>Of most unhallowed meaning! Yet her eyes</l>
<l>Were fixed the while, and motionless her lips!</l>
<l>Whereby the Rabbi certainly percieved</l>
<l>'Twas not the Woman of herself that spake,</l>

<pb n="188" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/189"/>

<l>But the dread Spirit that possessed her soul.</l>
<l>And thus it cried aloud:</l></lg></div>

<div type="poempart">
<head type="parthead">Part II.</head>

<lg><l>"Why am I here, in this my last resort,</l>
<l>Purturbed with incense and an<del><hi rend="del-pencil">n</hi></del>ointings? Why</l>
<l>Compelled to listen to the sound of prayers</l>
<l>That smite me through as with the fire of God!</l>
<l>O pain, pain, pain! What if this chamber be</l>
<l>So full of us—for Legion is our name—</l>
<l>Yet look around! Is it not also full</l>
<l>Of our immi<del>t</del>t<del>a</del><add>i</add>gable punishers?</l>
<l>Full of avenging Angels, holding each</l>
<l>A scourge of thunder in his potent hand,</l>
<l>Ready to lighten forth! and who, thus armed,</l>
<l>For ever chase and wound us as we fly!</l>
<l>Nor end with this—but in each wound they make</l>
<l>Pour venom sweltered from that tree Asgard,</l>
<l>Whose deadly shadow in its blackness falls</l>
<l>Over the lake of everlasting doom!</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">"Five hundred years ago, I who thus speak,</l>
<l>Was an Egyptian living at the Court</l>
<l>Of Ptolemy Philadelphus. To the top</l>
<l>Of mountainous power, though roughened with unrest</l>
<l>And girt with dangers as with thunder clouds,</l>

<pb n="189" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/190"/>

<l>Had I resolved, by all resorts, to climb,</l>
<l>By truth and falshood, right and wrong alike:</l>
<l>And I succeeded. Thus high built in power,</l>
<l>Second alone to my imperial Lord's,</l>
<l>I crowned with its impunity my lust</l>
<l>Of Beauty,—sowing, broadcast as it were,</l>
<l>Such sensual baits wide round me, as should lure</l>
<l>Through pleasure, or through interest entrap</l>
<l>The fairest daughters of the Land—and lo,</l>
<l>Their lustrous eyes surcharged with passionate light</l>
<l>The chambers of my Harem! But at length</l>
<l>Wearying of these, though sweet,—I set my heart</l>
<l>On riches, heaped to such a fabulous sum</l>
<l>As never <emph rend="ul">one</emph> man's hoard, before or then,</l>
<l>Might match; and to acquire them, steeped my life</l>
<l>In every public, every private wrong,</l>
<l>In lies, frauds, secret murders: till at last</l>
<l>A favored minion I had trusted most,</l>
<l>And highest raised, unveiled before the King</l>
<l>The so abysmal badness of my life</l>
<l>But dearly he abode it; nor till now</l>
<l>Guessed I how deadly grateful was revenge!</l>
<l>I stole into his chamber as he slept,</l>
<l>And with a sword whose double edge for hours</l>
<l>I had w<add><hi rend="pencil">h</hi></add>etted, to well fit it for the deed,</l>
<l>There staked him through the midriff to his bed,</l>
<l>Where he lay writhing till the morning came</l>
<l>And showed the murder: meanwhile I had fled.</l>
<l>But first I sent, as oft I had used before,</l>
<l>A present to the mistress of the man</l>
<l>Who had in secret prompted my betrayer,</l>
<l>Of scented wine, and those Damascus cakes</l>
<l>So prized by luxury. Ha, ha! On these</l>
<l>Both feasted, and both fell together down,</l>

<pb n="190" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/191"/>

<l>Rolling and panting in their dying pangs,</l>
<l>Like poisoned desert dogs!</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">"But I had <del>fled</del> fled.</l>
<l>A swift ship bore me, which my forecast long</l>
<l>Had kept still ready against some such need</l>
<l>As even now involved me. O'er the waves</l>
<l>Proudly she rode—But on the third day, lo,</l>
<l>A mighty storm strode o'er us, trampling all</l>
<l>Her masted bravery flat, and driving still</l>
<l>The wave-swept ruin tow'rds a reefy shore!</l>
<l>Meanwhile amongst the terror-stricken crew</l>
<l>An ominous murmur went from mouth to mouth</l>
<l>And ran them into councils, which, ere long,</l>
<l>Grew loud and furious with surmises wild,</l>
<l>And maniac menaces—all aimed at <emph rend="ul">me</emph>!</l>
<l>'My fugitive head it was at which so loud</l>
<l>The thunder bellowed! The wild-shrieking winds</l>
<l>And roaring <del>waves</del> waters held in vengeful chase</l>
<l>Me only!—<emph rend="ul">me</emph>, whose signal crimes <del>had brought</del> alone</l>
<l>Had brought on all this anger of the Gods!'</l>
<l>And thus reproaching me, with glaring eyes,</l>
<l>They would have siezed and slain me: but I sprang</l>
<l>Back from amongst them, and outstr<add><hi rend="pencil">i</hi></add>king stabbed</l>
<l>With sudden blow their leader to the heart;</l>
<l>Then with my poinard scaring off the rest,</l>
<l>I leaped the deck, and swimming, reached the shore:</l>
<l>From which, in savage triumph, I beheld</l>
<l>The battered ship, with all her howling crew,</l>
<l>Heel, and go down <del>into</del> <add>amid</add> the whelming waves.</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">"Inland my course had lain, for many days,</l>
<l>O'er barren hills and glens, whose herbless scopes</l>
<l>Never grew luminous with a watery gleam,</l>

<pb n="191" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/192"/>

<l>Or heard the pleasant bubble of a brook,</l>
<l>And round me <del>now</del> the Great Afric Desert <add>now</add></l>
<l>Stretched vast and objectless. Still inland, on</l>
<l>Starving and sunscorched, and afire with thirst<del>,</del></l>
<l>Intolerable, I wandered—till I came</l>
<l>To where amid the dun and level waste,</l>
<l>In frightful loneliness, a mouldered group</l>
<l>Of ancient tombs stood ghostly. Here at last</l>
<l>Utterly spent, in my despair, I lay</l>
<l>Down on the burning sand—to gasp and die!</l>
<l>When from amongst the tombs, a withered Man</l>
<l>Who looked as old as the grey desolation</l>
<l>Of which he seemed the one sole habitant,</l>
<l>Came and stood o'er me,—saying, 'Get thee up;</l>
<l>Not much have I to give, but these at least</l>
<l>I offer to thy need—water and bread.'</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">"His offer strengthened me, and I arose</l>
<l>And straightway followed him to where he dwelt</l>
<l>Amid the tombs;—dwelt in a dusty Cell</l>
<l>That seemed <app><rdg><del>s</del>o</rdg><rdg>to have been, erewhile<del>, itself</del></rdg><rdg> to have been, erewhile</rdg></app> a tomb,</l>
<l>So lightless was it, and so foul with damp;</l>
<l>While at its entrance there were skulls and bones</l>
<l>Arranged in figures, with an aim, it seemed,</l>
<l>At <add>somewhat</add> ornamental. But of this</l>
<l>Small heed I took—so long and deep I drank,</l>
<l>And munched so greedily the Hermit's bread.</l>
<l>But with the strength which thence my frame derived,</l>
<l>The fierce dissatisfaction of my soul,</l>
<l>Returning, <del><hi rend="del-pencil"></hi></del><add><hi rend="pencil">g</hi></add>nawed me, and I cursed my fate!</l>
<l>Whereat the withered <add>Creature</add> laughed in scorn,</l>
<l>And mocked me with the malice of his eyes;</l>
<l>That sometimes, like a snake's, shrank small, and then</l>
<l>Enlarging, blazed as with infernal fire!</l>

<pb n="192" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/193"/>

<l>Then, on a sudden, with an oath that seemed</l>
<l>To wake <del>an</del> a stir in the surrounding tombs,</l>
<l>As if their silence shuddered, he averred</l>
<l>That he could lift me once more to the height</l>
<l>Of all my wishes—nay, even higher; but</l>
<l>On one condition only: Dared I swear</l>
<l>By the dread Angel of the Second Death,</l>
<l>I would be wholly his, both body and soul,</l>
<l>After a hundred years?</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">"Why should I not?</l>
<l>I answered, quivering with a stormy haste—</l>
<l>A rampant unreluctance! For so great</l>
<l>Was still my fury against all mankind,</l>
<l>And my desire of pomp and riches yet</l>
<l>So monstrous, that I felt I could have drunk</l>
<l>Blood, fire, or worse, to wear again the power</l>
<l>That Fortune, working through my enemies' hands,</l>
<l>Had stript away from me, and thereby left</l>
<l>My life so naked. Wherefore, word by word,</l>
<l>I swore the oath as he repeated it.</l>
<l>Nor much it moved me, in my eagerness,</l>
<l>To feel a damp and earthy odor break,</l>
<l>At ever<expan>y</expan> word, out of each several tomb,</l>
<l>In all of which again too, there awoke</l>
<l>A darkling stir and hissing, as of snakes:</l>
<l>Yet, though the fell of hair upon my scalp</l>
<l>Rose bristling under a cold creeping thrill,</l>
<l>I failed not, but swore all the dread oath through!</l>
<l>No sooner had he ended, and once more</l>
<l>The tombs become all silent as their dead,</l>
<l>Than straightway a new feeling as of youth</l>
<l>And sensual vigor, in bold riot, coursed</l>
<l>Through all my <del>heart</del> veins and summered in my heart!</l>

<pb n="193" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/194"/>

<l>Till there before him in my pride I stood</l>
<l>In stately strength, and agile aptitude</l>
<l>For instant action, as the wind e<add>x</add>press—</l>
<l>Stood there before him in my stormy pride</l>
<l>Magnificent as a desert-nurtured steed</l>
<l>Of princeliest pedigree, with nostrils wide</l>
<l>Dilated, and with eyes effusing flame!</l>
<l>''Tis well!' he said; 'and now begone, prepared</l>
<l>To live thy hundred years (no trifling lease)</l>
<l>Of pomp, of power, of pleasure, and'—His voice</l>
<l>Sighed off into the distance. He was gone:</l>
<l>Only a single raven, far aloft,</l>
<l>Was beating outward with its sable wings!</l>
<l>And when I looked around the tombs as well</l>
<l>Had vanished: only in the utmost view</l>
<l>The level Desert, objectless and grey,</l>
<l>Merged its whole circle with the bending sky.</l></lg></div>

<div type="poempart">
<head type="parthead"><hi rend="dul">Part III.</hi></head>
<note resp="MJS">An alternative reading for the first line has been written above the line in pencil: "Out of these <del>w</del><add>W</add>ilds to Egypt I returned:". This reading was adopted in <ref target="H689j"><hi rend="it">Poems</hi></ref>.</note>

<lg><l>"Out of the Desert—I returned to Egypt:</l>
<l>Where it was now supposed that I had gone</l>
<l>Down with the ship, and perished; and where none—</l>
<l>Not even the dwarf Eunuck who of old</l>
<l>Had worshipped me, and with a wizard heed</l>
<l>Divined my every wish ere I myself</l>
<l>Might fully feel it,—no, not even he</l>

<pb n="194" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/195"/>

<l>Now recognised me: for indeed my face</l>
<l>And form were wholly changed,—from passing fair</l>
<l>To fairer yet; from manly, to a pile</l>
<l>So nobly built, that in all eyes I looked</l>
<l>More beautiful than beseemed a mortal man—</l>
<l>Yea, beautiful as Thammuz! Nor was changed</l>
<l>My person only, but my heart and head.</l>
<l>Ambition wilder than a leopard's thirst</l>
<l>For blood of roe, or flying hart, possessed</l>
<l>My spirit, like the madness of a God!</l>
<l>But which I yet, even in its fiercest strain,</l>
<l>Could curb and guide with sovereign strength of will.</l>
<l>And thus accomplished, on my new career</l>
<l>I started.</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">"Working by all possible means,</l>
<l>All passions, interests, with a weight of brain</l>
<l>And ultimate sagacity, that shrank</l>
<l>The men about me into speaking mice—</l>
<l>Nay, into insects,—rapidly I rose:</l>
<l>Stepping, as up a stair, from rival head</l>
<l>To rival head,—from high to higher still,</l>
<l>And so to the loftiest post that might be held</l>
<l>Under the Ptolomies. And firm fixed in this,</l>
<l>Some liesure now was <del>lef</del><add>mine</add> for paying off</l>
<l>Each old unsettled score; and so betimes</l>
<l>I set myself to ruin all who erst</l>
<l>Had worked against me,—sweeping them and theirs</l>
<l>Out of all posts, all places: for though Time</l>
<l>And Change had much dispersed them through the land,</l>
<l>Not the less surely did, in briefest space,</l>
<l>The sleuth-hounds of my vengeance find them out!</l>
<l>Which things not being in a corner done,</l>
<l>What wonder was it, that all Egypt now,</l>

<pb n="195" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/196"/>

<l>From end to end, even like a shaken hive,</l>
<l>Buzzed, as disturbed with my portentous fame?</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">"And what if I had secret enemies?</l>
<l>Had I not also spies, who knew right well</l>
<l>How to pin down a whisper in the dark,</l>
<l>And keep it there for good; or how to dash</l>
<l>A covert frown, though by the same prompt means</l>
<l>An<del>d</del> open charge had challenged? Hence at length</l>
<l>My very name became a sound that struck,</l>
<l>Wherever uttered, through the popular heart</l>
<l>Ineffable dismay! And yet, behold,</l>
<l>The more I trampled on mankind, the more</l>
<l>Did fawning flatterers throng me as I swept</l>
<l>On set days of processional display,</l>
<l>Like a malignant meteor through the Land!</l>
<l>The more I hurled the mighty from their seats,</l>
<l>And triumphed o'er them, prostrate in the dust,</l>
<l>The human hounds that licked my master hand</l>
<l>But multiplied the more! And still I strode</l>
<l>From bad to worse, corrupting as I went</l>
<l>The lowly, making them more abject yet;</l>
<l>Awing as with a thunder-bearing hand</l>
<l>The high and affluent; while I bound the strong</l>
<l>To basest service, though with chains of gold.</l>
<l>All hated me; all cursed me in their hearts;</l>
<l>But what of that?—all feared me! For in vain</l>
<l>Daggers were levelled at my brazen heart—</l>
<l>They glanced, and slew some minion at my side!</l>
<l>Poison was harmless as <add>a</add> heifer's milk</l>
<l>When I had sipped it with my lips of scorn!</l>
<l>All private hate, all popular abhorrence;</l>
<l>All that paraded pomp and smiling power</l>
<l>Could draw against me from the envious hearts</l>

<pb n="196" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/197"/>

<l>Of men as would be wicked as myself,</l>
<l>I challenged, I encountered,—like a God</l>
<l>To triumph o'er them all!</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">"Thus many years</l>
<l>Wore o'er me,—till exhaustion now at last</l>
<l>Was showing seer through all my tree of life.</l>
<l>My spirits flagged—my <del>sp</del> senses more and more</l>
<l>Grew blunted, and incapable of joy!</l>
<l>The splendors of my rank availed me not:</l>
<l>A poverty as naked as a slave's</l>
<l>Seemed lurking under them, and peering thence</l>
<l>As with a mocking eye. The pride of power</l>
<l>That once had such a plenitude of glow,</l>
<l>As it ruled in me, throned on perfect health,</l>
<l>Was now like something dying at my heart!</l>
<l>To cheat or stimulate my jaded taste,</l>
<l>Feasts, choice or sumptuous, were devised in vain;</l>
<l>There was disflavor, there was fraud within them,</l>
<l>Like that which filled the fair-appearing rind</l>
<l>Of those delusive apples that of old</l>
<l>Grew on the Dead Sea shore! The magical charm</l>
<l>Of Beauty, once so sovereign in its power,</l>
<l>Might only now solicit my desires,</l>
<l>To irk and disappoint them.</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">"Yet, though thus</l>
<l>All that gave pleasure to my younger life,</l>
<l>Was withering from my paths <del>of</del> like summer grass,</l>
<l>I still had one intense relief, and which</l>
<l>Grew ever keener as my years encreased:</l>
<l>A hatred of mankind; to pamper which</l>
<l>I gloated, with a burning in my soul,</l>
<l>Over their degradation: and like one</l>

<pb n="197" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/198"/>

<l>Merry with wine, I revelled day by day</l>
<l><expan>In</expan> scattering baits that should corrupt them more!</l>
<l>The covetous I sharpened into thieves;</l>
<l>Urged the vindictive; hardened the malign;</l>
<l>Sanctioned the violent with a self-belief</l>
<l>That read all interests into ruffian whets;</l>
<l>And flung them then like burning brands abroad!</l>
<l>Much was I helped, too, in my present bent,</l>
<l>By the decadence of the state in which</l>
<l>My fortunes had recast me. In the Court,</l>
<l>Even like a common drunkard, brute Excess</l>
<l>Reeled shameless, to and fro; or staggering thence,</l>
<l>Was met and even rivalled by the wild</l>
<l>And furious looseness of the popular herd,</l>
<l>For public there was none! Down to its death</l>
<l>The old Greek dynasty was sinking fast,</l>
<l>And with it all dominion—body and soul!</l>
<l>Waste, and thence want,—extortion, meanness, fraud—</l>
<l>These, welling outward from the throne itself,</l>
<l>Had reproduced themselves through all the realm:</l>
<l>Wherefore, I say, all things worked with me well,</l>
<l>Clothed as I was with rank and power that made</l>
<l>Even Ptolomy a cipher; in himself</l>
<l>Nothing, though mighty when summ'd up with <emph rend="ul">me</emph>.</l>
<l>And still I lured him into wilder waste,</l>
<l>And baser need,—though to succeed in this</l>
<l>Little I had to do, but did that little.</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">"A new ambition siezed upon my soul,</l>
<l>The aim of which was ultimately this:</l>
<l>To hurl the feeble Ptolomy from his throne,</l>
<l>And mount it in his stead. And to this end</l>
<l>I daily wove around him cunning snares</l>
<l>That reached and trammelled all the Court as well.</l>

<pb n="198" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/199"/>

<l>My schemes all prospered, and drew hourly now</l>
<l>Nigh to their consummation. But alas!</l>
<l>In the wild frensy of my expectation</l>
<note resp="MJS">A "z" has been written above "frensy" in line 3 in pencil, indicating the alternative spelling "frenzy". This line is not in <ref target="H689j"><hi rend="it">Poems</hi></ref>.</note>
<l>I had forgotten <emph rend="ul">one</emph> thing—that my time</l>
<l>Was measured.</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">"At a banquet, which was held</l>
<l>In the King's chamber,—lo, a Guest appeared</l>
<l>Whose strangely withered face methought was one</l>
<l>That I had somewhere seen—I knew not where—</l>
<l>Out in the distant Past. He was the Chief</l>
<l>Of one of the rude Bactrian tribes, and now</l>
<l>Was come with compensation for such loss</l>
<l>As his wild horsemen had, from time to time,</l>
<l>Inflicted on the Egyptian caravans</l>
<l>Bound from the Indus, bearing silk and gold.</l>
<l>A man of fabulous age, the cramps of which</l>
<l>Had shrunk his body till it scarce was human.</l>
<l>But his repute for wondrous craft, had reached</l>
<l>Before all memory into many lands,</l>
<l>And still the seekers of forbidden lore—</l>
<l>The Magi—the Soothsayers—those who held</l>
<l>Dark consultations with the unblest dead—</l>
<l>Acknowledged all, that in their several lines</l>
<l>They were excelled by this decrepit wretch.</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">"The first glance, as I said, of his weird eye</l>
<l>Had kindled in the darkness of my soul</l>
<l>A sudden flash of <del>sud</del> fearful recognition!</l>
<l>But at the dry croak of his raven voice</l>
<l>No doubt was left me! I again beheld</l>
<l>The Old Man of the Tombs—and fell at once</l>
<l>Into the outer darkness of despair!</l>
<l>The day that was to close my dread account</l>

<pb n="199" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/200"/>

<l><expan>Had</expan> surely come. The long triumphant feast</l>
<l>Of life had ended in a funeral treat.</l>
<l>I was to die—to suffer with the damned</l>
<l>The hideous torments of the Second Death!</l>
<l>The days, weeks, months of a whole hundred years</l>
<l>Seemed crushed into a thought, as summ'd in mind,</l>
<l>And in their ultimate<add>s</add> all burning out</l>
<l>In that brief period which remained me now.</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">"Out from the royal chamber rushing,—urged</l>
<l>By terror and by horror, shame and hate,</l>
<l>I siezed my sword, and was about to plunge</l>
<l>Its ready point into my maddened heart:</l>
<l>When some one held my arm! I turned—and lo,</l>
<l>The withered visage of the Bactrian met</l>
<l>My loathing eyes! I struggled to get free</l>
<l>From the shrunk wretch in vain! his spidery hands</l>
<l>Were strong as fetters of Ephesian brass!</l>
<l>And all my strength, though now with madness strung,</l>
<l>Was as a child's to his. He  smiled and said:</l>
<l>Forbear, thou fool! am I not Sammael?</l>
<l>Whom to resist is vain, and from whom, yet</l>
<l>Never flowed mercy, never came remission!</l>
<l>For what to me are feelings which in men—</l>
<l>Even in men—are found the most in fools!</l>
<l>But lo, a Prince of Lies, wide round I reign.</l>
<l>'Tis I that gout the Bactrian sands with blood!</l>
<l>'Tis I that fill the Persian pallaces</l>
<l>With lust and profligacy, till they flow</l>
<l>Even like the darkling heads of city sewers</l>
<l>With a <sic>curruption</sic> that, in fretting thence,</l>
<l>Taints the whole region! And I now am come</l>
<l>To fling the firebrands of a civil war</l>
<l>Through all this people—this most ill-mixed mob—</l>

<pb n="200" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/201"/>

<l>This gatherum of effeminate Asiatics,</l>
<l>And barbarous Africans, and treacherous Greeks!</l>
<l>Doubtless 'twas coming of itself, by steps</l>
<l>Measuredly fatal; but I must not let</l>
<l>The wickedness of men transcend my own</l>
<l>Or work so far without it, as might make</l>
<l>My influence doubted in the Courts of <del>Hell</del><add>Hell</add>!</l>
<l>This Land throughout shall be a deluge soon</l>
<l>Of blood and fire, till Ruin stalk alone,</l>
<l>A grisly Spectre, in its grass-grown marts!</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">"As thus he spake, his withered visage grew</l>
<l>Like a live coal, as all instinct with fire,</l>
<l>And his strange voice, erewhile so thin and dry,</l>
<l>Came as if bellowed from the vaults of doom!</l>
<l>Down fell I, powerless or to move or speak.</l>
<l>And now he was about to plunge me down</l>
<l>Ten thousand times ten thousand fathoms deep,</l>
<l>Through the Earth's crust, and through the slimy beds</l>
<l>Of nether oceans—down! still down, below</l>
<l>The darkling roots of all this upper world,</l>
<l>Into the regions of eternal fire</l>
<l>And penal retribution!</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">"Thus to stamp</l>
<l>Me downward, to the convict dead, his heel</l>
<l>Already had he lifted—but it hung</l>
<l>As if arrested, and I heard him heave</l>
<l>A sudden groan of superhuman pain,</l>
<l>So deep 'twas drawn! and as he groaned I saw</l>
<l>A mighty downburst of miraculous light</l>
<l>Enlap and cover him from head to foot,</l>
<l>As with a robe, within whose venemous folds</l>
<l>He writhed in horrible torment!</l></lg>

<pb n="201" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/202"/>

<lg><l part="F">"So a space</l>
<l>He stood thus writhing: when a shining Shape</l>
<l>Unspeakably magnificent, appeared</l>
<l>Standing above him! One of the high Sons</l>
<l>Of Paradise, who still keep watch and ward</l>
<l>O'er Israel's progeny, where'er dispersed.</l>
<l>And now they fought for me with arms that filled</l>
<l>The air wide round with intervolving gleams,</l>
<l>And flashes, as of lightning. But ere long</l>
<l>The Evil One fell conquered. From the ground</l>
<l>Then sprang he, cursing,—up into a cloud</l>
<l>That moved aloft, low thundering as it went.</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">"When thus the fight had ended, and clear off</l>
<l>The Evil One—even Sammael, had passed</l>
<l>The shining Son of Paradise came and stood</l>
<l>Over me, where I lay, and with a face</l>
<l>Severe with wrath, yet beautiful as severe—</l>
<l>Gloriously beautiful, because divine,</l>
<l>And bright with holiest excellence, he said:</l>
<l>'O Child of Guilt! should vengeance not be wrought</l>
<l>On thee as well? Why should the Evil One</l>
<l>Be punished, and not thou, his willing slave?'</l>
<l>I clasped his radiant knees—I wept—I groaned—</l>
<l>I beat my bosom in my wild distress!</l>
<l>At last the <del>ho</del><add>sacred</add> Presence, who had held</l>
<l>The blow suspended still, spake thus: 'Thou'rt spared;</l>
<l>From no weak pity, but because thou art</l>
<l>Descended from an Israelitish mother:</l>
<l>For that cause spared;—yet must thou at my hands</l>
<l>Find some meet punishment.' And as he spake,</l>
<l>He laid his hand with a life-crushing weight</l>
<l>Upon my forehead—and I fell, as dead!</l></lg></div>

<pb n="202" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/203"/>

<div type="poempart">
<head type="parthead"><hi rend="dul">Part IV.</hi></head>

<lg><l>"Awaking as from sleep, I bounded up,</l>
<l>Strung with a feeling of enormous strength,</l>
<l>Though yet half wild with horror. Onward then</l>
<l>Ramping I went,—out through the palace gates—</l>
<l>Down through the streets, <del>an</del><add>and</add> into the highways,</l>
<l>Astonished at my own miraculous speed!</l>
<l>And now afar, in long-drawn line appeared</l>
<l>A Caravan upon its outward way</l>
<l>Over the desert of Pentapolis.</l>
<l>And strange the instinct seemed that urged me then</l>
<l>To rush amongst them—and devour: for I</l>
<l>Was fierce with hunger and inflamed with thirst.</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">"Still bounding on, I suddenly sprang amidst</l>
<l>A laggard company that yet beside</l>
<l>A clear spring rested, as for the last time;—</l>
<l>One of those clear springs that, like giant pearls</l>
<l>Inlay the burning borders of the grey</l>
<l>Enormous Desert. All at once they rose</l>
<l>At sight of me, and made a startling outcry!</l>
<l>Some fled—some threw themselves amongst the brakes—</l>
<l>Some siezed their <del>saw </del><add> swords and lances</add>, and so stood</l>
<l>As if on their defence; all which to see</l>
<l>Filled me at once with unaccountable rage,</l>
<l>And savage joy! The sternness of their looks—</l>
<l>The very gleam of their protending spears</l>

<pb n="203" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/204"/>

<l>Seemed to insult me, and I rushed amongst them!</l>
<l>But, as I did so, sudden spasms of pain</l>
<l>Searched deep my side—a lance was quivering in it!</l>
<l>I roared a roar that startled even myself,</l>
<l>So loud and hoarse and terrible was its tone!</l>
<l>Then bounding, irresistible it seemed</l>
<l>As some huge fragment from a crag dislodged,</l>
<l>Against the puny wretch that had assailed me,</l>
<l>Instantly tore him, as he were a kid,</l>
<l>All into gory shreds! The rest all fled</l>
<l>At sight of this, nor cared I then to chase them:</l>
<l>So parched was I with thirst, so faint with heat,</l>
<l>And wear<add><hi rend="pencil">i</hi></add>ed by my rampant flight that day</l>
<l>Under the burning sun. Besides, the well</l>
<l>Was gleaming in its coolness there before me.</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">"At <add>once</add> forgetful of <add>all</add> else, behold,</l>
<l>I rushed to it—I stooped to drink. Ha, see!</l>
<l>Stooping reversed within the lucid lymph</l>
<l>The semblance of a monstrous Lion stood!</l>
<l>I saw his shaggy mane—I saw his red</l>
<l>And glaring eyeballs, rolling in amaze!</l>
<l>His rough and grinning lips! his long sharp fangs,</l>
<l>That like discolored rows of ivory spikes,</l>
<l>Were foul with gore, and hung with dripping strings—</l>
<l>The muscular integuments of the slain!</l>
<l>I shrank away in horrible purturbation.</l>
<note resp="MJS">"dismay" has been added in pencil (not in Harpur's hand) as an alternative reading for "purturbation". This reading was adopted in <ref target="H689j"><hi rend="it">Poems</hi></ref>.</note></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">"But as my thirst each moment fiercer grew,</l>
<l>I soon returned, to stoop <del>an</del> at once and slake</l>
<l>Its insupportable heat!—Alas! alas!</l>
<l>Again was that tremendous Presence there</l>
<l>Standing reversed, as erewhile, in the clear</l>
<l>And gleaming mirror of the smiling well!</l>

<pb n="204" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/205"/>

<l>The horrid truth smote like a rush of fire</l>
<l>Upon my brain! The terrible Thing I saw</l>
<l>Was my own Shadow! I was a Wild Beast!</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">"'They did not fable then, who held that oft</l>
<l>The guilty dead are punished in the shapes</l>
<l>Of beasts, if brutal were their lives as men;</l>
<l>Each in the form of that particular beast</l>
<l><del>The</del> <add>His</add> nature most was kin to!' Through my mind</l>
<l>Thus flashed that doctrine. At the fatal well</l>
<l>A final glance now swept all shadow of doubt</l>
<l>From the dread Verity—I was a Wild Beast!</l>
<l>A Presence terrible in face and form</l>
<l>As that grim Semblance! Down I stooped and drank.</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">"Long lapped I the cool lymph, while still my tongue</l>
<l>Made drip for drip with that so monstrous one</l>
<l>Which, as in ugly mockery, from below</l>
<l>Seemed to lap up against it. But though thirst</l>
<l>Was quenched at length, what might appease the fierce</l>
<l>Dissatisfaction of my <del>fatal</del> fated soul?</l>
<l>The thought that I no more was Human, ran</l>
<l>Like scorpian venom through my mighty frame!</l>
<l>And off I bounded, tearing up the sands,</l>
<l>That like a drab mist coursed me as I went</l>
<l>Out on my homeless track. I made my fangs</l>
<l>Meet in my own pierced flesh, that so I might</l>
<l>In the sharp violence of bodily pain,</l>
<l>Find respite from the anguish of regret!</l>
<l>From morn to <del>morn</del> <add>night</add>, from night to morn, I fled</l>
<l>Along the limitless wastes, that so I might</l>
<l>In the exhaustion of my giant strength,</l>
<l>Find haply some remmission from the keen</l>
<l>And searching memory of my lost estate!</l>

<pb n="205" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/206"/>

<l>Worn out and bleeding, in the burning sands</l>
<l>I lay down, as to die! In vain!—in vain!</l>
<l>The savage vigor of my Lion life</l>
<l>Might yield alone to the long tract of time.</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">"From hill to valley rushing after prey</l>
<l>With whirlwind speed, was now my daily wont.</l>
<l>For all things fled before me—all things shrunk</l>
<l>In mortal terror at my shaggy front</l>
<l>And ponderous <del>front</del> ramp. Or sometimes, I would seek</l>
<l>The perlieus of those close-fenced villages,</l>
<l>Wherein the desert dwellers hide their swart</l>
<l>And naked bodies from the scorching heats,</l>
<l>Hoping that I might perish by their shafts.</l>
<l>And often was I wounded—often bore</l>
<l>Their poisoned arrows in my burning flesh.</l>
<l>But still I lived.</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">"The tenor of my life</l>
<l>Was always this—the solitary state</l>
<l>Of a Wild Beast of Prey, who hunted down</l>
<l>The antelope, the boar, the goat, and gorged</l>
<l>Their quivering flesh, and lapped their steaming blood:</l>
<l>Then slept, till hunger, or the hunter's cry,</l>
<l>Roused him again to battle or to slay,</l>
<l>To flight, pursuit, blood, strategem and wounds!</l>
<l>And to make this rude life more hideous yet,</l>
<l>I still retained a consciousness of all</l>
<l>The nobler habits of my <del>early</del><add>earlier</add> life,</l>
<l>And had a keen sense of what most had moved</l>
<l>My nature as a Man: and knew besides</l>
<l>That this my punishment was fixed by One</l>
<l>Too mighty to be questioned—and too just</l>
<l>One tittle of its measure of remit.</l></lg>

<pb n="206" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/207"/>

<lg><l rend="indent1">"How long this haggard course of life went on</l>
<l>I might not even guess: for I had lost</l>
<l>The human faculty that measures time.</l>
<l>But still from night to night, I found myself</l>
<l>Roaming the desert, howling at the moon,</l>
<l>Whose cold light always, as she poured it down,</l>
<l>Awoke a drear distemper in my brain!</l>
<l>But much I shunned the sunblaze, which at once</l>
<l>Inflamed me, and revealed my dread approach.</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">"Homelessly roaming thus for evermore,</l>
<l>The tempests beat on my unsheltered bulk,</l>
<l>In those bleak seasons, when the drenching rains</l>
<l>Drove into covert all those gentler beasts</l>
<l>That were my natural prey. I swinkt beneath</l>
<l>The furnace heats of the midsummer sun,</l>
<l>When even the palm of the oasis stood</l>
<l>All withered, like a weed: and for how long</l>
<l>Yet knew not.</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">"Thus the sun and moon arose</l>
<l>Through an interminable tract of time,</l>
<l>And yet in that dim remnant that remained</l>
<l>Within me, of my former understanding,</l>
<l>I strove in vain even to guess the term</l>
<l>Of their prolonged <sic>sucessions</sic>. But though thus</l>
<l>So dim in this regard, the view of all</l>
<l>My human life was ever at my beck—</l>
<l>Nay, opened out before me of itself!</l>
<l>Plain as the pictures in a Wizard's glass</l>
<l>I saw again the trains that round my car</l>
<l>Streamed countless, as I rolled in state through Egypt!</l>
<l>I saw the wondrous beauty of my form</l>
<l>As it strode smiling through the courts of Ptolomy!</l>

<pb n="207" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/208"/>

<l>With them who there adored it,—saw their fair</l>
<l>And passionate faces, such as dreams alone</l>
<l>Might limn as extant elsewhere;—saw again</l>
<l>The pomps and pageants that around me beamed</l>
<l>Unparagoned brightness! And, in seeing, felt</l>
<l>Again the temper and the taste of all</l>
<l>The godlike loftiness of such a life—</l>
<l>Its passions, pleasures,—even its noble pangs!</l>
<l>Then in the rage of my thus-goaded heart</l>
<l>Would I roll howling, in the burning sand!</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">"At length this life of horror seemed to near</l>
<l>Its fated bourn. The slow but sure approach</l>
<l>Of old decay was felt in every limb</l>
<l>And every function of my Lion frame.</l>
<l>My massive strength seemed spent; my muscular springs</l>
<l>That once were as express as are the bolts</l>
<l>Of heaven, were ponderous still, but quick no more.</l>
<l>The antelope escaped me! In disgust</l>
<l>I sought a mountain cavern, shut from day</l>
<l>By savage draperies of tangled briers,</l>
<l>And only dragged my tardy bulk abroad</l>
<l>When pressed by hunger.</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">"On a day, thus urged<del><hi rend="del-pencil">,</hi></del></l>
<l>Abroad by the dull cravings of my maw,</l>
<l>Behold, I sprang upon a buffalo <del>hea</del><add>herd</add></l>
<l>That passed across the Desert, tearing soon</l>
<l>Its leader down, loud bellowing as he fell.</l>
<l>When lo, the Chief of those that drove them came</l>
<l>Against me, and I turned my rage on him!</l>
<l>But though the long lapse of so many years</l>
<l>Of ever-grinding wrechedness, had dulled</l>
<l>My memory, yet, I felt that I had seen</l>

<pb n="208" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/209"/>

<l>His withered visage <emph rend="ul">twice</emph> before: and straight</l>
<l>A shuddering awe subdued me, and I cowered</l>
<l>Beneath him in the dust. My appetite</l>
<l>For carnage; my unpitying delight</l>
<l>In mortal anguish—these had died within me!</l>
<l>And could I then have uttered as I lay,</l>
<l>In human speech, the wild desire that now</l>
<l>Inspired me, I had prayed him, once for all,</l>
<l>To crush me out of being, and consign</l>
<l>My misery to the pit of final death!</l>
<l>But when, thus wishing, I again looked up,</l>
<l>The tawny presence of the Afric Chief</l>
<l>Was gone! and I beheld the shining Son</l>
<l>Of Paradise <del>once more</del><add>instead</add>,—arrayed with power</l>
<l>And majesty immense, but from whose brow</l>
<l>There flashed as well the lightnings of a wrath</l>
<l>Inexorably just, because divine!</l>
<l>Yea, 'twas the Angel that with Sammael</l>
<l>Had fought for me in Egypt; and once more</l>
<l>He laid his crushing hand upon my front,</l>
<l>And earth and sky, with all that in them is,</l>
<l>Became to me a Darkness, swimming blank</l>
<l>In the Eternal, round that point where now</l>
<l>Stretched out in body, I again lay—<emph rend="ul">dead</emph>.</l></lg></div>

<div type="poempart">
<head type="parthead">Part V.</head>

<lg><l>"Again I lived—again I felt. But now</l>
<l>The winds of heaven seemed under me, and I</l>
<l>Was sweeping,—like the Spirit of a storm</l>
<l>That bellowed round me,—in its murky glooms,</l>
<l>All heaving with a wide and manifold motion</l>
<l>That seemed yet mightier than the darkling swells</l>
<l>Of ocean, wrestling with a midnight gale!</l>
<l>The wild winds tossed me; I was drenched throughout</l>
<l>With heavy moisture, and at intervals,</l>
<l>Amid the ragged gaps of moving cloud,</l>
<l>Methought I caught dim glimpses of the sun</l>
<l>Hanging aloft, as if in drear eclipse.</l>
<l>But gradually my senses cleared, and I</l>
<l>Grew conscious that some new change was upon me.</l>
<l>Then glancing at my limbs, I saw that they</l>
<l>Were clothed with plumage; at the same time, too,</l>
<l>I felt the sharpness of long-taloned claws,</l>
<l>As they worked closing with a fierce desire</l>
<l>And sudden hungriness for blood and prey!</l>
<l>An impulse to pursue and to destroy</l>
<l>Both on the earth and in the air, ran quick</l>
<l>Out from my heart and shivered in my wings:</l>
<l>And as a thing more central yet, I felt</l>
<l>Regnant within me, throned o'er all, a lone</l>
<l>And sullen, yet majestic, glow of pride.</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">"'Twas plain that I who had aforetime been</l>
<l>Crushed out of human being into that</l>
<l>Of a Wild Beast, had thence again been crushed</l>

<pb n="210" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/211"/>

<l>Into the nature of some mighty Thing</l>
<l>That now swept sailing on wide van-like wings,</l>
<l>Amid the whirls of an aerial gloom,</l>
<l>That, out extending, in one mighty cope</l>
<l>Hung heaving, like a black tent roof,<metamark><hi rend="ss">x</hi></metamark><note resp="Harpur">The larger Arab tents are often flat-roofed; and the "tents of<lb/> Kedah," we know were <emph rend="ul">black</emph>, even in the days of Job.</note> o'er all</l>
<l>The floor of Africa.</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">"Still on I swept,</l>
<l>And still as far as my keen vision went,</l>
<l>That now was gifted with a power that seemed</l>
<l>To pierce all space, I saw the vapours roll</l>
<l>In dreadful continuities of black</l>
<l>And shapeless masses, by the winds convulsed;</l>
<l>But soon in the remotest distance they</l>
<l><del>Were</del><add>Showed</add> different, as touched with sunny splendors;</l>
<l>And nearing still to these, I saw them dash,</l>
<l>Like the wild surges of an uproused sea</l>
<l>Of molten gold, against the marble sides</l>
<l>Of heaven-high mountains which, though far below</l>
<l>My flight, yet pierced up through them all, and stood</l>
<l>With splintered cones and monster-snouted crags,</l>
<l>Immovable as Fate. Beneath me, lo,</l>
<l>The grandeur<del>s</del> of the Kingdom of the Air</l>
<l>Was circling in its magnitude immense!</l>
<l>A dread magnificence of which before</l>
<l>I might not even dream. I saw its quick</l>
<l>And subtle interchange of forms and hues</l>
<l>That more and more astonished; saw its black</l>
<l>And solid-seeming reservoirs of rain—</l>
<l>Its laboring forges of the awful thunder.</l></lg>

<pb n="211" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/212"/>

<lg><l rend="indent1">"At last, as onward still I swept, above</l>
<l>A milky mass of vapour, that spread flat</l>
<l>Like a vast floor of purest alabaster,</l>
<l>Behold, reflected in its quiet gleam,</l>
<l>I saw a Shadow that swept on with me,</l>
<l>Reversed as was the Lion's in the well:</l>
<l>With van-like wings; with eyebals seething fire;</l>
<l>With taloned claws, and cruel down-bent beak:</l>
<l>The shadow of a monstrous Eagle—such</l>
<l>As seemed indeed, the mightiest that had sailed</l>
<l>The seas of space since Adam named the first.</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">"No doubt was left me as to what I was:</l>
<l>My fated soul had passed into the form</l>
<l>Of that huge Eagle which swept shadowed there!</l>
<l>My first impression from the thing I saw</l>
<l>Was a cold horror! I was once again</l>
<l>Imprisoned in the being of a Brute,</l>
<l>Albeit a noble one; and had again</l>
<l>To live for ages—centuries it might be—</l>
<l>In the base being of a nature, yet</l>
<l>Inferior, by what infinite descent!</l>
<l>Even to that remnant of intelligent mind</l>
<l><del>That</del><add>Which</add> still kept with me,—like a put-back soul</l>
<l>Burningly conscious of its foregone powers,—</l>
<l>Its inborn sovereignty of kind,—and yet</l>
<l>So latent, self-less;—had to live again</l>
<l>A life of carnage, and to sail abroad</l>
<l>A terror to all birds and gentle beasts</l>
<l>That heard the hurricane rushings of my wings!</l>
<l>A royal Bird indeed—but thence <del>alone</del><add><emph rend="ul">alone</emph></add>:</l>
<l>Whose inaccessible pride of place was still</l>
<l>The solemn loneness of the mightiest hills,</l>
<l>And of the highest heavens.</l></lg>

<pb n="212" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/213"/>

<lg><l part="F">"But in truth,</l>
<l>Not much, for many periods, had I need</l>
<l>To search for prey; for countless hosts of men</l>
<l>Were mustering forth o'er all the face of Earth,</l>
<l>Casting an iron gleam o'er trampled leagues</l>
<l>Of golden corn, or as they onward marched</l>
<l>Leaving behind them seas of raging fire,</l>
<l>In whose red surges cities thronged with men,</l>
<l>And happy hamlets, homes of health and peace,</l>
<l>Isled in the scopes of plenty-bearing glebes</l>
<l>That rang erewhile with rural thankfulness,</l>
<l>Were whelmed in one wide doom, and from the earth</l>
<l>All but erased. Or to their wish at last</l>
<l>Confronted upon some set field of fight,</l>
<l>Their sullen cloud-like masses, in their strength,</l>
<l>Would charge each other with a dreadful roar—</l>
<l>A roar that shrunk the furious yells of beasts</l>
<l>Into mere make-believe;—would rush to wounds,</l>
<l>And sumless slaughter, with a madness such</l>
<l>As could have issued only out of Hell!</l>
<l>Or else about fenced cities they would pitch</l>
<l>Their crowded camps, and leaguer them for years,</l>
<l>Sowing the fields about them with a slime</l>
<l>Of carnage, till their growths were plagues alone!</l>
<l>And finally beating them so flat, that lo,</l>
<l>Their very names were thenceforth heard no more.</l>
<l>—What is the ravage made by brutes on brutes,</l>
<l>To man's on Man?</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">"With liesure hence derived,</l>
<l>(For ever when I hungered, close at hand</l>
<l>Some fresh-slain man lay smoking in his gore)</l>
<l>And even scandalised by what I saw</l>
<note resp="MJS">"scandalised" has been underlined in pencil. This line is not in <ref target="H689j"><hi rend="it">Poems</hi></ref>.</note>
<l>Of wholesale murder in the ways of men,</l>

<pb n="213" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/214"/>

<l>I said—My realm is large, and I will keep</l>
<l>My state in all its regions; and though still</l>
<l>The savage instincts of <add><hi rend="pencil">the</hi></add> Eagle<add><hi rend="pencil">'s</hi></add> life</l>
<l>Were fierce within me, not the less I felt</l>
<l>That now my lot was mollified, and cast</l>
<l>Into a mould even capable of joy:</l>
<l>Safe as I was from all pursuit—from thirst,</l>
<l>From famine, and from wounds; for what wild fool</l>
<l>Would aim an arrow at me as I soared</l>
<l>Above the populations? It was plain</l>
<l>That solaces, though few and far between,</l>
<l>Were added to me; and I thence derived</l>
<l>Even in the musings of my Eagle heart,</l>
<l>A feeling that was daily more confirmed,</l>
<l>That not for ever was my soul condemned</l>
<l>To suffer in the body of a Brute!</l>
<l>For though the memories of the towering crimes</l>
<l>And matchless lusts, that filled my whole career</l>
<l>While human, worked within me evermore,</l>
<l>No longer did they shed about my life</l>
<l>That scorpian venom whose so subtle fire</l>
<l>Once burnt like blight. Nay, I remembered well</l>
<l>How often I had looked with longing eyes</l>
<l>Up at the clear Egyptian heavens, and watched</l>
<l>The wings that clove them, envying every bird</l>
<l>That soaring in the sunshine, seemed to be</l>
<l>Exempt from all the grovelling cares of men.</l>
<l>Oft I remembered how, even in my most</l>
<l>Triumphant period, I had wished to exchange</l>
<l>My being with an ibis <del>which</del> that I saw</l>
<l>Floating away, upon his speckled wings,</l>
<l>Tow'rds Memphis, at a height in heaven so safe—</l>
<l>So inaccessible to hate or hurt!</l>
<l>I thought how oft, when with my hunting train,</l>

<pb n="214" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/215"/>

<l>In that rude region spread about the Cataracts,</l>
<l>I had watched the eagles as they rose aloft</l>
<l>Into the lovely blue, and saw them turn</l>
<l>As through the colored clouds still up they went</l>
<l>Against the sunset, into feathered flags</l>
<l>Of royal purple edged with burning gold.</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">"These fields of space were now my Kingdom—why</l>
<l>Should I then not enjoy them? Nay, the faculty</l>
<l>Alone of motion in a world so rich</l>
<l>Was something noble: but to move at will</l>
<l>Upward or forward, or in circles vast,</l>
<l>Through boundless spaces with a rushing speed</l>
<l>No living thing's might rival, and to have</l>
<l>The majesty of the everlasting hills</l>
<l>Perpetually beneath me, with the green</l>
<l>Luxuriance of the myriad-peopled plains,—</l>
<l>Broad rivers, and the towery towns that sate</l>
<l>Beside their spacious mouths, with out beyond</l>
<l>The lonely strength of the resounding seas—</l>
<l>This liberty began to move my pride</l>
<l>As somewhat godlike; and, in moving, made</l>
<l>A sure impression that kept graining still</l>
<l>Into the texture of my brute estate—</l>
<l>Yea, graining in through all its animal lusts</l>
<l>And savage wonts.</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">"Hence ever more and more</l>
<l>The temper of a better spirit grew</l>
<l>Within me, as from inkling roots, and moved</l>
<l>Even like an <sic>enbryon</sic> in its moist recess:</l>
<l>A sensibility to beauteous things</l>
<l>As now I saw them in the heavens displayed,</l>
<l>And in the bright luxuriance of the earth;</l>

<pb n="215" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/216"/>

<l>Some power of just comparison—some sense</l>
<l>Of how a man would rank them, could he see</l>
<l>Those secular grandeurs from that sovereign height</l>
<l>Whence I beheld them. And with this a wish</l>
<l>To commune even with the human race,</l>
<l>And pour the loftier wonders of my life</l>
<l>Into their ears, through a rich-worded song</l>
<l>Whose golden periods in their mellow flow</l>
<l>Should witch all ears that heard them—even old men's,</l>
<l>Even jaded monarch's; not to speak of theirs,</l>
<l>Those spirit-lovely Ones—yea, Moons of Love</l>
<l>That rise at first in the Circassian hills,</l>
<l>As they should tingle all like tiny shells</l>
<l>Of roseate whiteness, to its perfect chords.</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">"One day, upon a royal visitation,</l>
<l>Low stooping 'mid the Mountains of the Moon,</l>
<l>Behold a sudden storm had gathered up</l>
<l>Out of my view, hid by a neighboring height,</l>
<l>But which, thence wheeling with terrific force,</l>
<l>Wide tossed me with its gusts—aloft, and then</l>
<l>Downward as far; then whirlingly about,</l>
<l>Even like a withered leaf. My strength of wing</l>
<l>Availed me nought, so mightily it raged!</l>
<l>Then suddenly, out in the dun distance, lo,</l>
<l>I saw as from the storm's Plutonian heart</l>
<l>A mass of white-hot light keep writhing forth</l>
<l>With horrible noises, into a vast orb!</l>
<l>When for a moment by its dread light shown,</l>
<l>The dubious figure of a withered man</l>
<l>Seemed dropping headlong through the lurid clouds;</l>
<l>While full within its radiant disc, again</l>
<l>The conquering Son of Paradise appeared</l>
<l>Up towering in his amplitude sublime;</l>

<pb n="216" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/217"/>

<l>On whose divine brow I might yet discern</l>
<l>Some sign of wrath, though of a cast less dread</l>
<l>Than erewhile. Onward with tremendous speed</l>
<l>The mighty Vision rushed, right tow'rds me, orbed</l>
<l>In that white issue of miraculous light!</l>
<l>The blasting influence of which ere long</l>
<l>Enlapped my frame. I felt a stiffling heat;</l>
<l>One cruel pang I felt, and headlong then</l>
<l>Fell earthward—dead: a plumb descending mass.</l></lg></div>

<div type="poempart">
<head type="parthead"><hi rend="dul">Part VI</hi>.</head>

<lg><l>"Within a rustic chamber, dark and low,</l>
<l>And with wild-looking men and women thronged,</l>
<l>I seemed to wake—but knew not what I was;</l>
<l>Nor how I had been <del>hith</del><add>thither</add> brought; nor why.</l>
<l>I was not large; my consciousness at once</l>
<l>Had measured that fact. Inwardly I felt</l>
<l>No briskness of existence, but a sense</l>
<l>Of languor rather, or revival slow.</l>
<l>And evermore the men and women came</l>
<l>And looked at me with wonder, and with shouts</l>
<l>Significant of confirmed astonishment!</l>
<l>Then would they whirle about the room in dance,</l>
<note resp="MJS">The "e" of "whirle" (Part 2, line 12) has been underlined in pencil.</note>
<l>Abandoned to their barbarous delight.</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">"And thus I surely strengthened into life.</l>
<l>Then looked about the chamber, half in hope</l>
<l>And half in fear, of seeing it might be</l>

<pb n="217" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/218"/>

<l>The mighty Angel that now ruled my lot.</l>
<l>My gestures were mistaken for a wish</l>
<l>To breathe the open air, and I was borne</l>
<l>Tow'rds a wide casement. Like a picture lay</l>
<l>The world without, and instantly confirmed</l>
<l>My hitherto vague impressions that a new</l>
<l>Life-change had passed upon me. On all hands</l>
<l>Nothing but mountains feathered to their tops</l>
<l>With a dense fell of pines, and valleys filled</l>
<l>With a cold darkness that was lit alone</l>
<l>By the broad flashes of the furious streams</l>
<l>That leaped in thunder out of marble gaps,</l>
<l>Was seen in prospect. Over all a low</l>
<l>Dull vapour, like a canopy of smoke,</l>
<l>Did so obscure the sun, that I had thought</l>
<l>The scene that now I saw was not of earth,</l>
<l>But for a golden flush that now and then</l>
<l>Would touch the higher ranges. What I had</l>
<l>Indeed become I knew not, but I still</l>
<l>Retained impressions of my former wonts,</l>
<l>And often made vain efforts to expand</l>
<l>The wings I had no longer, and sail off,</l>
<l>And through those sullen vapours—up, and up</l>
<l>Into the mighty silence of the blue.</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">"The day was fading, and a blare of horns</l>
<l>With many voices and much trampling noise</l>
<l>Heard from without aroused me. And ere long</l>
<l>The women that had been erewhile around me,</l>
<l>Again rushed in—each bearing some rich robe,</l>
<l>Or some gay bauble, wherewithal they soon</l>
<l>Arrayed me to their taste; and holding then</l>
<l>A mirror up before me, I percieved</l>
<l>My soul had this time passed into the form</l>

<pb n="218" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/219"/>

<l>Of a young female. The whole truth was this:</l>
<l>A matter that long afterwards I learned)</l>
<l>The being whom I now reanimated</l>
<l>Was the sole child of a Circassian Chief;</l>
<l>A Maiden of most memorable beauty,</l>
<l>Who had been long regarded by her house</l>
<l>As its chief treasure, and as such reserved</l>
<l>For him alone, no matter whence he came,</l>
<l>Whose hand could dip into the longest purse.</l>
<l>But Envy lurks in the Circassian hills,</l>
<l>As elsewhere, and a dose of opium well</l>
<l>Administered by one who had been long</l>
<l>The rival beauty (of a neighboring tribe),</l>
<l>Had served to quash a bargain quite complete</l>
<l>Save in the final payment of the gold,</l>
<l>Which had been even offered and told down,</l>
<l>And only <emph rend="ul">not</emph> accepted, through some old</l>
<l>Delaying ceremony of the tribe:</l>
<l>And in which luckless circumstance, 'twas plain</l>
<l>That both my admirable parents saw</l>
<l>The unkindest turn of all.</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">"On all hands forth</l>
<l>Had scouts been sent to summon the whole tribe</l>
<l>To attend my obsequies, and then forthwith</l>
<l>To exterminate our ancient enemies</l>
<l>Through all their tents;—such was the fierce resolve!</l>
<l>But while these things were tending, lo, the light</l>
<l>Had broken, like a new morn, from the eyes</l>
<l>Of the dead beauty; on her cheeks had dawned</l>
<l>A roseate color; from her moistening lips</l>
<l>Low murmurs too had broken: <del>wherup</del><add>whereupon</add></l>
<l>My parents, in the exultant hope of still</l>
<l>Consùmmating their bargain, had transformed</l>

<pb n="219" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/220"/>

<l>The funeral to a general tribal feast,</l>
<l>And loaded me with all <del>their</del> <add>the</add> family gauds</l>
<l><del>Orn</del> And ornaments they held. The Persian too</l>
<l>Had been invited to renew his purchase,</l>
<l>And carry me at once beyond the reach</l>
<l>Of future opium doses.</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">"With the rest</l>
<l>Back had he galloped, and was now without,</l>
<l>Eager once more to bear me to the arms</l>
<l>Of his long-bearded Lord. Within he came,</l>
<l>In wonder, but full ready to make good</l>
<l>His former bargain and pay down the price.</l>
<l>My worthy parents tenderly embraced me</l>
<l>With many tears, protesting that I was</l>
<l>The life-light of their eyes—their rose of joy—</l>
<l>Then stretchered their palms out for the proffered gold,</l>
<l>And hurried off to tell it o'er in secret—</l>
<l>The dear recovered treasure<del>s</del> they so late</l>
<l>Had mourned, as lost for ever. On that night</l>
<l>I was packed carefully on a camel's back</l>
<l>Beside a case of porcelain pipes and <del>gi</del><add>jimcracks</add>,</l>
<l>And carried Persia-ward, by stages safe,</l>
<l>From the Circassian mountains.</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">"At the Court</l>
<l>I soon became the favorite of the king;</l>
<l>Lived sumptuously, but in perpetual fear.</l>
<l>My food was served to me on plates of gold</l>
<l>Whose rims were rough with graven sprays, and set</l>
<l>With jewels simulating various fruit;</l>
<l>I slept on beds the canopies of which</l>
<l>Were royal purple looped in folds, that hung</l>
<l>Massively downward, as all sprigg'd with braids</l>

<pb n="220" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/221"/>

<l>And fringed with countless pearls: and yet no less</l>
<l>I envied the poor slaves who swept the floors.</l>
<l>My Persian lord for one whole month had been</l>
<l>Sluggishly loving—for a month and more:</l>
<l>And then I learned my place was to be filled</l>
<l>By a new favorite. And strange to say,</l>
<l>Albiet I loathed him as we loathe some cold</l>
<l>And reptile creature, when compelled to touch</l>
<l>Its so abominable being—yet</l>
<l>I could not bear that he should thus supply</l>
<l>My presence with another's. I would make</l>
<l>Some effort to regain his faded favor:</l>
<l>For I was beautiful, and therefore vain,</l>
<l>As beauty needs will be. And to this end,</l>
<l>I now arrayed myself in robes that seemed</l>
<l>Gossamer vestures of ethereal texture,</l>
<l>While scarfs of purple such as only Queen's</l>
<l>May purchase from the Indus caravans,</l>
<l>Barred them with rainbow tints; a burnished band</l>
<l>Or purest gold, whose midst throughout was raised</l>
<l>By a full row of pearls—all perfect ovals—</l>
<l>Held in the wavelets of my sunny hair:</l>
<l>A gem that seemed indeed a frozen mass</l>
<l>Of white fire, flashed upon my silk-soft brow.</l>
<l>Then, in my loveliness, even thus arrayed,</l>
<l>I <del>swe</del><add>swam</add> into his presence (though indeed</l>
<l>My hid feet rowed me) graceful as a <del>s</del><add>S</add>wan.</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">"The Harem girls applauded, while there seemed</l>
<l>Even in his own dull eyes almost a flash</l>
<l>As of extorted joy: but which became</l>
<l>At the next moment a malignant scowl,</l>
<l>Which had its dark cause in such thoughts as these:</l>
<l>(As I learned after from a Nubian girl</l>

<pb n="221" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/222"/>

<l>Who always waited on his baser needs)</l>
<l>'What! did so soft and ignorant a minx</l>
<l>Think to enchant again a man like <emph rend="ul">him</emph>,</l>
<l>Who was the sharpest fellow, past a doubt,</l>
<l>In the whole Orient? Did a minx so raw</l>
<l>Think to befool a mine of such intelligence</l>
<l>And worldly wisdom, on all hands allowed,</l>
<l>As he was—he! the paragon of kings!</l>
<l>By floating in before him, like a swan,</l>
<l>A little better feathered than at first?'</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">"Even while this mischief <del>had been</del> <add>thus was</add> brewing <del>thus,</del>—lo,</l>
<l>The Harem ladies had been waved away</l>
<l>The Newbian girl remaining only. Then</l>
<l>A conclave of those strange demoniac Dwarfs</l>
<l>Who from their secret dens and crypts would come</l>
<l>On state occasions, in the briefest space,</l>
<l>On given signals forth, were summoned in:</l>
<l>Wizard-like beings, <del>all</del> with enormous heads,</l>
<l>Splay-feet, and monstrous spider-fingered hands.</l>
<l>Nor was the council long: I on that night</l>
<l>Was to be poisoned—and with a pomegranite.</l>
<l>One of a number to be pluckt and brought</l>
<l>At supper, from the Summer Garden forth,</l>
<l>For every lady of the Harem one—</l>
<l>And one too for himself, though he disliked them.</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">"The Nubian had slipped away, and told me</l>
<l>All she had heard: yet her news moved me not,</l>
<l>So sure I felt that <add>such</add> was not my doom:</l>
<l>Or moved me but to this—the packing up</l>
<l>Of such gay properties as ladies doat on.</l>
<l>But time stays not, and we were summoned all</l>
<l>To supper. On the centre-board there stood</l>

<pb n="222" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/223"/>

<l>A silver crate piled high with crimson gourds,</l>
<l>Which soon amongst us did the king dispense,</l>
<l>To every lady one: till two at last</l>
<l>Alone remained, one of them being marked.</l>
<l>This came to me, nor could I but accept it:</l>
<l>But mindful of the part I had to play,</l>
<l>Even as I took it I fell fainting down,</l>
<l>And flurried so the ladies, they all thronged</l>
<l>About me—flurried even the king himself!</l>
<l>With infinite dexterity I then</l>
<l>Revived as suddenly, and contrived the while</l>
<l>Amid the bustle to exchange the gourds—</l>
<l>Took his, and left him mine. His soon I ate,</l>
<l>And praised as being the very soul of fruit:</l>
<l>He also, with a rollic in his eye,</l>
<l>Ate that which had been poisoned, and avowed</l>
<l>He never knew before what fruit it was;</l>
<l>Nay, that it held within its crimson rind</l>
<l>The juice of Paradise.</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">"While this went on,</l>
<l>I slipped away wholly unseen to where</l>
<l>My goods were packed, and to prepare for flight;</l>
<l>Nor had I long withdrawn, ere to my chamber</l>
<l>The Nubian girl came running,—this her news:</l>
<l>That soon the King had with a monstrous snort</l>
<l>Fall'n prostrate, while the ladies all away</l>
<l>Had scattered like a flock of gossamer clouds</l>
<l>Before a storm-blast in a summer sky!</l>
<l>And that the chambere now was thronged instead</l>
<l>To suffocation, with a fusty crowd</l>
<l>Of bare-poled hakims and grey-chinn'd physicians,</l>
<l>Who all concurred at least in this: the dark</l>
<l>Affair in hand was quite unlooked for—quite!</l>

<pb n="223" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/224"/>

<l>And as she told her news the Nubian laughed</l>
<l>With infinite delight—so loved are Kings!</l>
<l>And I laughted also, feeling that I had</l>
<l>A natural and a perfect right to do so.</l>
<note resp="MJS">"perfect right to do so." is underlined in pencil.</note>
<l>—But no time might be wasted—and we fled</l>
<l>Together, loaded <del>with</del><add>both with</add> costly spoils.</l>
<l>Still as we passed beneath the latticed Court</l>
<l>Wherein the Monarch suffered, all in vain</l>
<l>I strove to dash my womanly desire</l>
<l>To have a last look at him. So aloft</l>
<l>I mounted, on the slave's bent back,—and looked.</l>
<l>The King was sprawling on the pillowy floor</l>
<l>With quite a host of anxious quacks about him:</l>
<l>Jews and Armenians, infidels and slaves,</l>
<l>All ranks, all races; and as still he took</l>
<l>Their nostrums, with grimaces horrible,</l>
<l>He still kept threatening them, that if they failed</l>
<l>To cure him, ere that dreadful night were past,</l>
<l>The dawn should see them headless—every man!</l>
<l>Then would he wonder why he ever chose</l>
<l>Pomegranites for his supper. Then in rage</l>
<l>He cursed his blunder, and the palpable trick</l>
<l>By which a silly woman had o'erreached him!</l>
<l>Then would he sprawl and bellow like a beast!</l>
<l>And so I left him sprawling, while the sound</l>
<l>Of his brute ragings followed us beyond</l>
<l>The Garden bounds as through the dark we fled.</l>
<l>—We heard long after, that he died ere he</l>
<l>Had time to cut off <emph rend="ul">all</emph> the doctors' heads.</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">"'Twas plain and patent to my inmost self,</l>
<l>That in this last change, I had always been</l>
<l>Regenerating, more and more: for though</l>

<pb n="224" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/225"/>

<l>A spirit of mischief frolicked in my head,</l>
<l>At heart I was not bad: for they who knew</l>
<l>Me closely, and the closelier they knew me,</l>
<l>Well seeing this,—and not the less perhaps,</l>
<l>If of the woman sort, because 'twas plain</l>
<l>My conduct most was from its balance <del>cast</del><add>thrown</add></l>
<l>By whimsies, and by humors almost mad—</l>
<l>These always, and the closelier they knew me,</l>
<l>Loved me,—nay, served me as the Nubian did.</l>
<l>—And now as no one else might sell me—lo,</l>
<l>I sold myself, and made what I believed</l>
<l>A capital bargain, till I found myself</l>
<l>Installed as queen of a rude Afric King,</l>
<l>Black as a log of ebony, and who</l>
<l>As still at stated times, in motly state,</l>
<l>On bow-bent shanks and <del>hu</del><add>big</add> pot-bellied <del><unclear/></del> bulk,</l>
<l>He strode amongst us, bore I must confess</l>
<l>Much brother-likeness to a huge baboon.</l>
<l>But luckily, this monster soon preferred</l>
<l>The Nubian to myself—a consummation</l>
<l>That filled me with much thankfulness of heart.</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">'Twere long to tell what haps befell me next.</l>
<l>I was the captive of a Bedoeen Shiek,</l>
<l>And fed his camels while I served his lust;</l>
<l>Was sold in the slave-mart of Astrachan</l>
<l>And carried thence <add><hi rend="pencil">to</hi></add> India, to be crowned</l>
<l>A Rajahpoot's sultana; from which state</l>
<l>Flying at length, I fell into a worse,</l>
<l>Being pounced <del>upon</del><add>on</add> by a Tur<del>k</del><add>c</add>oman horse-stealer,</l>
<l>Who made me, with much lofty self-applause,</l>
<l>At once his mistress and his water-car<add>r</add>ier.</l>
<l>At Alexandria I became the slave</l>
<l>Of a harsh Roman matron, who was wont</l>

<pb n="225" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/226"/>

<l>To flog and famish me to make me good,</l>
<l>And when I owned myself converted, then</l>
<l>She flogged and famished me the more, to make</l>
<l>My goodness lasting. But this mush of change</l>
<l>In the contexture of my fatal life</l>
<l>But troubles and distracts me. The extremes</l>
<l>Is what I best remember: I was now</l>
<l>A Queen, and now a drudge: and finally</l>
<l>Fell stabbed in Cairo—slaughtered by a slave.</l></lg></div>

<div type="poempart">
<head type="parthead">Part VII.</head>

<lg><l>"After some short and intermediate terms</l>
<l>Of transmigration—all in feminine forms,</l>
<l>And in the course of which through many ties</l>
<l>And kindly offices incurred and done,</l>
<l>It seemed the temper of my spirit much</l>
<l>Had humanised; and in the last of which</l>
<l>'Twas mine, for once, to die a natural death:</l>
<l>Again I had some deep-down hold on being,</l>
<l>Dim as an oister's in its ocean-bed;</l>
<l>An aboriginal inception—yea,</l>
<l>A self-producing knot of living shoots</l>
<l>Which terminated all in one smooth surface,</l>
<l>From which branched forth tentacula, that searched</l>
<l>The darkling confines of my moist abode.</l>
<l>Then came a sense of free space, light and air,</l>
<l>And then of hunger, and along with this</l>
<l>Strong suctatorial powers. I could detect</l>

<pb n="226" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/227"/>

<l>Sweet food from sour, warm presences from cold,</l>
<l>And was beyond all doubt some sentient thing—</l>
<l>Some little vital centre, upon which</l>
<l>Much comfortable influence impinged.</l>
<l>But best I can recall, with what entire</l>
<l>Content I nestled betwixt two warm paps,</l>
<l>Each with its many-porous tap, both shaped</l>
<l>And colored both,—yea, to the very life,</l>
<l>Like two <add>ripe</add> mulberries of Palestine,</l>
<l>And from which, when I listed, without stint,</l>
<l>I drew a liquid that was meat and drink.</l>
<l>At length I could distinguish faces, forms,</l>
<l>And strove to imitate the sounds I heard;</l>
<l>Caught up the drift of speech, and knew at last</l>
<l>That all who came to see me and admire,</l>
<l>Called me Ben Bachai's daughter.</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">"Dark indeed,</l>
<l>But beautiful as a starry night I grew,</l>
<l>A Maid, the glory of her Father's house;</l>
<l>Her Mother's dovelet, filling all her wonts</l>
<l>With tenderness and joy. Still as I grew,</l>
<l>By strange degrees the memory of all</l>
<l>That I had been came back upon my mind,</l>
<l>To fill it with wild sorrow and dismay:</l>
<l>To know I was a cheat, nor wholly what</l>
<l>I seemed even to my parents who did both</l>
<l>So doat upon me; that I was indeed</l>
<l>But half their daughter, and the rest a fiend,</l>
<l>With a fiend's destiny,—ah! this, I say,</l>
<l>Would smite <add>me</add> even in dreams with icy pangs</l>
<l>Of wordless woe—yea, even while I slept</l>
<l>So innocently, as it seemed, and so</l>
<l>Securely happy in the arms of Love!"</l></lg>

<pb n="227" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/228"/>

<lg><l rend="indent1"><del><hi rend="erasure"></hi></del>As this was said, the Rabbi looked, and saw</l>
<l>That now again the Woman seemed to speak</l>
<l>As of herself, and not as heretofore</l>
<l>With moveless lips, and prisoned voice, that came</l>
<l>As from some dark duality within.</l>
<l>Her looks had changed too with the voice, and now</l>
<l>Again she lay—a Queen-like Creature, racked</l>
<l>With mortal sufferings, instant and extreme;</l>
<l>And who, when these grew tolerable at all,</l>
<l>Or for a time remitted, even thus</l>
<l>Went with her story on.</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">"At length upgrown</l>
<l>To womanhood,—on some mysterious pact</l>
<l>Obtaining 'twixt my Father's house and that</l>
<l>Of an Arabian Prince—time out of mind,</l>
<l>I was now wedded ere I wished; and he,</l>
<l>My husband, finally had come to claim</l>
<l>And bear me from my home—that happiest home</l>
<l>Which I should <del>no</del><add>know no</add> more: a Man most fair</l>
<l>To look upon, but void of force,—<del>indeed</del> in truth,</l>
<l>The weakling of a worn-out line, who yet</l>
<l>(What merit in a Prince!) was not depraved,</l>
<l>Not wicke<del><hi rend="del-pencil">t</hi></del><add><hi rend="pencil">d</hi></add>, not the mendicant of Lust,</l>
<l>And scoundrel slave of every selfish wish:</l>
<l>But mild, and even affectionate, even just.</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">"My dowry was immense, and flushed with this</l>
<l>The Prince had summoned from his feudal tribe</l>
<l>Five hundred horse, all spearmen, to escort</l>
<l>And guard us Desert-ward. And as we went</l>
<l>These ever and anon, at signal given,</l>
<l>W<del>h</del>ould whirl <del>about</del><add>around</add> us like a thunder cloud,</l>
<l>Wind-torn, and shooting instant shafts of fire!</l>

<pb n="228" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/229"/>

<l>And thus we roamed about the Arabian wastes,</l>
<l>Pitching our camp amid the fairest spots.</l>
<l>Nor was this wandering life unpleasant. Oft</l>
<l>Under an awning, would I lay and gaze</l>
<l>Out at the cloudless ether where it wrapt</l>
<l>The silent mountains, like a conscious power</l>
<l>Big with the soul of an eternal Past.</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">"But long this life might last not, for the Prince</l>
<l>Sickened and died—died poor; my dower as well</l>
<l>Having been squandered in our many jaunts</l>
<l>Upon the hungry horde that, day by day,</l>
<l>Was wont to prance about us: who ere long</l>
<l>Divining my extremity, grew loud</l>
<l>And urgent for rewards;—till, on a day,</l>
<l>By concert as it seemed, the tribe entire</l>
<l>Came fiercely round me, all demanding gifts,</l>
<l>Gifts that I had not—but in lieu of which</l>
<l>I was preparing to tongue-lash them well—</l>
<note>"but in lieu ... lash them well—" has been circled in pencil.</note>
<l>When, as this coil prest nearer—lo, I saw</l>
<l>Weaving his way amongst them, while they made</l>
<l>So soon as seen, with many signs of awe,</l>
<l>A lane for him to pass—the Bactrian Sage!</l>
<l>The Old Man of the Tombs! who soon came near,</l>
<l>And fixing me with his shrunk serpent eyes,</l>
<l>Waved off the abject Arabs, and then asked</l>
<l>'Why art thou poor? with needs so great upon thee</l>
<l>For wherewithal to glut yon greedy pack</l>
<l>Of Desert doggery? Again, behold,</l>
<l>I offer thee long life, and wealth, and power,</l>
<l>But on the same old terms.'</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">"Still vexed and chafed</l>
<l>I turned to him and said: Should I not know</l>

<pb n="229" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/230"/>

<l>By all the past, the nature of thy gifts</l>
<l>And what they lead to?—shows not substances,</l>
<l>Being evil, and thence non-essential all;</l>
<l>A vast accumulation of delusions</l>
<l>All terminating in eternal loss!—</l>
<l>'Well, take it as thou wilt', he said, 'my gifts</l>
<l>Are not so weighed by all'. And saying this</l>
<l>He went his way, while I retired within</l>
<l>My lonely tent to weep.</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">"Next day the Tribe</l>
<l>Again assembled, to again enquire</l>
<l>What I designed to do. The poor they said,</l>
<l>No matter what their lineage might be,</l>
<l>Should pare their needs down to their shrun<del>g</del><add>k</add> estate:</l>
<l>That, if I wished it, being thus reduced,</l>
<l>An esscort—say, a dozen spears or so—</l>
<l>Should see me safely to my Father's house.</l>
<l>This was too much! My blood arose, and I</l>
<l>Chode with them, calling them all things but men!</l>
<l>Dogs, jackals, monkeys! Go, I said, away</l>
<l>And see my face no more. Re-entering then</l>
<l>My tent, thus angered,—lo, there stood again</l>
<l>Within the twilight of its inner folds,</l>
<l>The withered Bactrian with his snaky eyes,</l>
<l>And wiry voice, that questioned as before:</l>
<l>'Why art thou poor? with needs so great upon thee,</l>
<l>And all this petty baseness brattling round?</l>
<l>Am I not here to help thee? I, thy one</l>
<l>Sole friend—not empty, but with ample means.</l>
<l>—Behold the secrets of the mundane world!</l>
<l>There, down amongst the rock roots of the mountains,</l>
<l>What seest thou there? Look, as I point: even those</l>
<l>Strange miscreations, as to thee they seem,</l>

<pb n="230" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/231"/>

<l>Are the demoniac moilers <del>of</del> that obey</l>
<l>Such arts as I possess: the gnomish brood</l>
<l>Of Demogorgan. See them how they moil</l>
<l>Amid those diamond shafts and reefs of gold</l>
<l>Embedded in the oldest drifts of Time,</l>
<l>And in the mire that was the first crude floor</l>
<l>And blind extension of the infant Earth:</l>
<l>Why art thou poor then, when such slaves as they</l>
<l>Might work for thee, and glut thy need with all</l>
<l>The matchless values which are there enwombed,</l>
<l>Serving thee always as they now serve me—</l>
<l>But on the old conditions. Nor are these</l>
<l>My servants only: turn thy looks aloft,</l>
<l>And watch the stars as they go swimming past!</l>
<l>Behold their vastness—each a world! Behold</l>
<l>Their brilliant populations, and the things</l>
<l>They trade in and converse with, such as Earth</l>
<l>May only in dim adumbrations show:</l>
<l>And these too, all shall be thy slaves' he said,</l>
<l>'As they are mine: upon the old conditions—</l>
<l>Even those thou erst didst swear to 'mid the Tombs.'</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">"But how, said I, might I make these obey me?</l>
<l>Straightway he took me by the hand, and said:</l>
<l>'Dost thou consent then to be mine for ever?'</l>
<l>I do consent, I said,—yet with a shudder</l>
<l>That shook me to the soul: and thereupon</l>
<l>He slipt a signet ring upon my finger:</l>
<l>Saying, 'by this thou mayst command them all</l>
<l>To do thy bidding, in the earth beneath</l>
<l>And in the stellar heavens, with a sway</l>
<l>Mo<del><hi rend="del-pencil">o</hi></del>re absolute than was Solomon's of old.'</l>
<l>—Suddenly then the desert winds arose</l>
<l>And blew with mighty stress amongst the tents;</l>

<pb n="231" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/232"/>

<l>Far off too in the east methought I heard</l>
<l>Low coming thunders: yea, a Storm was up!</l>
<l>For instantly aloft there ran a dread</l>
<l>Heart-killing turmoil,—and with this, behold</l>
<l>A mighty issue of miraculous light</l>
<l>Burst shaftwise forward, smiting Him in twain—</l>
<l>Yea, sheer in twain! and broken thus he fell,</l>
<l>Or so it seemed, down through the solid earth,</l>
<l>Leaving behind him on the blasted ground</l>
<l>A blue dent only, and a stench of fire!</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">"In vain I had sh<del><hi rend="del-pencil">a</hi></del>rank into a dim recess,</l>
<note resp="MJS">"u" has been written above the line in stanza 2, line 1, indicating the alternative spelling "shrunk".</note>
<l>For lo, once more, the Son of Paradise</l>
<l>Was lightning in my presence. Shame, remorse,</l>
<l>And misery unspeakable were mine,</l>
<l>As I at last dared to look up, and saw</l>
<l>Anger and sadness both upon his front.</l>
<l>At last he spake to me in tones that seemed</l>
<l>More gentle than I looked for or might hope:</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">'Couldst thou not rest content—all but redeemed,</l>
<l>All but re-born again—a Rabbi's daughter!</l>
<l>Enjoy as best thou may this ill-won power</l>
<l>Over the darker agencies of Time,</l>
<l>And bide the end—which end is punishment</l>
<l>But the more terrible the more delayed.</l>
<l>Yet know this also: thou shalt thus no more</l>
<l>Be punished in a body built of clay,</l>
<l>For Sammael must not triumph." Saying which</l>
<l>He vanished, leaving me abashed in soul,</l>
<l>And harrowed with ineffable regret:</l>
<l>And yet no power in heaven or hell, I said,</l>
<l>May now annul my deed: and therewith rose.</l></lg>

<pb n="232" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/233"/>

<lg><l rend="indent1">"Thus rich, 'twas mine to settle where I chose.</l>
<l>And long I was in finally choosing where:</l>
<l>Building vast Palaces in quiet view</l>
<l>Of ancient cities, or by famous streams,</l>
<l>I bought up beauty even as merchants buy</l>
<l>Their fabrics, in the markets of the world.</l>
<l>Men like to Gods were frequent in my halls,</l>
<l>And the most beautiful mothers earth could yield</l>
<l>Were nested in my chambers, brooding there</l>
<l>In downy privacy<del><hi rend="del-pencil">;</hi></del><add><hi rend="pencil">,</hi></add> like matron doves;</l>
<l>Whence come, as progeny, those Pages which</l>
<l>Thou seest at intervals glide in and out:</l>
<l>Beings so intensely beauteous that they look</l>
<l>Like striplings kidnapped from some skirt of heaven.</l>
<l>Yet sorrowful of countenance withal,</l>
<l>As knowing that their mortal doom is joined</l>
<l>With mine irrevocably; that with me</l>
<l>'Tis theirs to own these shows of Time; with me</l>
<l>To live,—with me to die.</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">"But all this pomp</l>
<l>Had no true taste of pleasure—no delight—</l>
<l>No satisfying end. And as 'tis said</l>
<l>A hunted roe will evermore beat round</l>
<l>Tow'rds whence he started first, I felt at length</l>
<l>Vehement longings for my native Hebron,</l>
<l>That spot in all the earth where I alone,</l>
<l>In tasting of it, had divined the worth</l>
<l>And sabbath quality of household peace.</l>
<l>Then coming hither, thus constrained, I pitched</l>
<l>My dwelling here, even this thou seest; built fair</l>
<l>And filled with splendors such as never yet</l>
<l>Under one roof-tree on this earth were stored.</l>
<l>See yon surpassing lustres! Could this Orb</l>

<pb n="233" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/234"/>

<l>Elaborate them? No. From Mars came that;</l>
<l>From Venus this. And yonder fiery mass</l>
<l>That looks as if 'twere breaking into flames</l>
<l>Of sun-bright glory—that from Mercury came.</l>
<l>Whence also came these viols, all instinct</l>
<l>With fervent music such as never <del><unclear>els</unclear></del> yet</l>
<l>From earthly instruments might thrill abroad."</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">Then siezing one of them, even as she spake</l>
<l>Over its chords she ran her ivory hand,</l>
<l>And instantly the Palace domes throughout</l>
<l>Rang resonant, as every hall and crypt</l>
<l>Were pulsing music from a thousand shells,</l>
<l>That still ran confluent with a mellow slide</l>
<l>And intercource of cadence: sweet and yet</l>
<l>Most mournful and most weird, and oft intoned</l>
<l>With a wild wilfulness of power that worked</l>
<l>For madness more than joy. "Even such" she said,</l>
<l>Were those delights with which I most conversed</l>
<l>In my so fatal loneliness of soul.</l></lg>

<lg><l rend="indent1">"Still all was show, not substance. All I held</l>
<l>But weighted more <del>the</del> my ever-haunting fears</l>
<l>And apprehensions of a wrath to come,</l>
<l>From which no change of place, no earthly power,</l>
<l>Might shield me. Ah! I see it shadowing forth</l>
<l>Out of the foregone ages—forth with Fate,</l>
<l>Even like a coming night in whose dark folds</l>
<l>My soul shall ask to hide itself in vain!</l>
<l>In vain—in vain!"</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">As thus the Woman spake,</l>
<l>Her brow grew dark, and suddenly she shrieked</l>
<l>In her great agony: "O pray for me!</l>

<pb n="234" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689i/235"/>

<l>Pray Rabbi for the daughter of thy friend!</l>
<l>The hour is coming—nay, the hour has come!</l>
<l>—There was a rustle as of wings aloft,</l>
<l>A sudden flicker in the lights below,</l>
<l>And she who until now seemed speaking, sank</l>
<l>Back on her pillow, and in silence there</l>
<l>Lay beautiful in the marble calm of death.</l>
<l>The Rabbi gazed on her, and thought the while</l>
<l>Of those far times when, as a girl, her grace</l>
<l>Had filled with pleasantness his old friend's house.</l>
<l>Then to her servants gave <del>the</del> in charge the corps<add><hi rend="pencil">e</hi></add>,</l>
<l>And turning, left the chamber; through the vast</l>
<l>And echoing halls paced hastily, and thence</l>
<l>Out through the porch, and through the garden gate,</l>
<l>Much musing as he went. At length again</l>
<l>He turned to take a final view of what</l>
<l>Was now the House of Death. Can such things be?</l>
<l>All had evanished like an exhalation!</l>
<l>Only the woods that hung like clouds about</l>
<l>The steeps of Hebron, in the whitening dawn</l>
<l>Lay dark against the sky! Only a pool</l>
<l>Gleamed flat before him, where it seemed erewhile</l>
<l>The splendid Structure had adorned the view!</l>
<l>Perplexed in mind, the Rabbi turned again</l>
<l>And hurried homeward, muttering as he went:</l>
<l>'Was it a Vision? Can such marvels be?</l>
<l>But what indeed are all things, even those</l>
<l>That seem most solid—Dust and Air at last!'</l></lg></div>

<trailer><hi rend="dul">Finis</hi>.</trailer>

</text></body></TEI>
