<TEI><body><text>
<!--+++ H689j-->

<!--*** THE WITCH OF HEBRON-->

<note resp="MJS" type="source"><hi>Poems</hi> (1883), pp. 249-304.</note>
<note resp="DS">Revised 4/1/15</note> 

<pb n="249" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/249"/>

<head type="title">THE WITCH OF HEBRON.</head>

<head type="subtitle"><hi rend="sc">a rabbinical legend</hi>.</head>

<div type="poempart">

<head type="parthead"><hi rend="sc">Part</hi> I.</head>

<lg><l><hi rend="sc">From</hi> morn until the setting of the sun</l>
<l>The rabbi Joseph on his knees had prayed,</l>
<l>And, as he rose with spirit meek and strong,</l>
<l>An Indian page his presence sought, and bowed</l>
<l>Before him, saying that a lady lay</l>
<l>Sick unto death, tormented grievously,</l>
<l>Who begged the comfort of his holy prayers.</l></lg>

<lg><l>The rabbi, ever to the call of grief</l>
<l>Open as day, arose; and girding straight</l>
<l>His robe about him, with the page went forth;</l>
<l>Who swiftly led him deep into the woods</l>
<l>That hung, heap over heap, like broken clouds</l>
<l>On Hebron's southern terraces; when lo!</l>
<l>Across a glade a stately pile he saw,</l>
<l>With gleaming front, and many-pillared porch</l>
<l>Fretted with sculptured vinage, flowers and fruit,</l>

<pb n="250" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/250"/>

<l>And carven figures wrought with wondrous art</l>
<l>As by some Phidian hand.</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">But interposed</l>
<l>For a wide space in front, and belting all</l>
<l>The splendid structure with a finer grace,</l>
<l>A glowing garden smiled; its breezes bore</l>
<l>Airs as from paradise, so rich the scent</l>
<l>That breathed from shrubs and flowers; and fair the<lb/> growths</l>
<l>Of higher verdure, gemm'd with silver blooms,</l>
<l>Which glassed themselves in fountains gleaming light</l>
<l>Each like a shield of pearl.</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">Within the halls</l>
<l>Strange splendour met the rabbi's careless eyes,</l>
<l>Halls wonderful in their magnificence,</l>
<l>With pictured walls, and columns gleaming white</l>
<l>Like Carmel's snow, or blue-veined as with life;</l>
<l>Through corridors he passed with tissues hung</l>
<l>Inwrought with threaded gold by Sidon's art,</l>
<l>Or rich as sunset clouds with Tyrian dye;</l>
<l>Past lofty chambers, where the gorgeous gleam</l>
<l>Of jewels, and the stainèd radiance</l>

<pb n="251" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/251"/>

<l>Of golden lamps, showed many a treasure rare</l>
<l>Of Indian and Armenian workmanship</l>
<l>Which might have seemed a wonder of the world:</l>
<l>And trains of servitors of every clime,</l>
<l>Greeks, Persians, Indians, Ethiopians,</l>
<l>In richest raiment thronged the spacious halls.</l></lg>

<lg><l>The page led on, the rabbi following close,</l>
<l>And reached a still and distant chamber, where</l>
<l>In more than orient pomp, and dazzling all</l>
<l>The else-unrivalled splendour of the rest,</l>
<l>A queenly woman lay; so beautiful,</l>
<l>That though upon her moon-bright visage, pain</l>
<l>And langour like eclipsing shadows gloomed,</l>
<l>The rabbi's aged heart with tremor thrilled;</l>
<l>Then o'er her face a hectic colour passed,</l>
<l>Only to leave that pallor which portends</l>
<l>The nearness of the tomb.</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">From youth to age</l>
<l>The rabbi Joseph still had sought in herbs</l>
<l>And minerals the virtues they possess,</l>
<l>And now of his medicaments he chose</l>
<l>What seemed most needful in her sore estate;</l>

<pb n="252" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/252"/>

<l>"Alas, not these," the dying woman said,</l>
<l>"A malady like mine thou canst not cure,</l>
<l>'Tis fatal as the funeral march of Time!</l>
<l>But that I might at length discharge my mind</l>
<l>Of a dread secret, that hath been to me</l>
<l>An ever-haunting and most ghostly fear,</l>
<l>Darkening my whole life like an ominous cloud</l>
<l>And which must end it ere the morning come,</l>
<l>Therefore did I entreat thy presence here."</l></lg>

<lg><l>The rabbi answered, "If indeed it stand</l>
<l>Within my power to serve thee, speak at once</l>
<l>All that thy heart would say. But if 'tis vain,</l>
<l>If this thy sin hath any mortal taint,</l>
<l>Forbear, O woman, to acquaint my soul</l>
<l>With aught that could thenceforth with horror chase</l>
<l>The memory of a man of Israel."</l></lg>

<lg><l>"I am," she said "the daughter of thy friend</l>
<l>Rabbi Ben Bachai—be his memory blest!</l>
<l>Once at thy side a laughing child I played;</l>
<l>I married with an Arab Prince, a man</l>
<l>Of lofty lineage, one of Ishmael's race;</l>
<l>Not great in gear. Behold'st thou this abode?</l>

<pb n="253" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/253"/>

<l>Did ever yet the tent-born Arab build</l>
<l>Thus for his pride or pleasure? Seest thou</l>
<l>These riches? Ah no! such were ne'er amassed</l>
<l>By the grey desert's wild and wandering son;</l>
<l>Deadly the game by which I won them all!</l>
<l>And with a burning bitterness at best</l>
<l>Have I enjoyed them! And how gladly now</l>
<l>Would I, too late, forego them all, to mend</l>
<l>My broken peace with a repentant heed</l>
<l>In abject poverty!"</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">She ceased, and lay</l>
<l>Calm in her loveliness, with dreamy looks</l>
<l>Roaming, perhaps, in thought the fateful past;</l>
<l>Then suddenly her beauteous countenance grew</l>
<l>Bedimm'd and drear, then dark with mortal pangs,</l>
<l>While fierce convulsions shook her tortured frame,</l>
<l>And from her foaming lips such words o'erran,</l>
<l>That rabbi Joseph sank upon his knees,</l>
<l>And bowed his head a space in horror down</l>
<l>While ardent, pitying prayers for her great woe</l>
<l>Rose from his soul; when, lo! the woman's face</l>
<l>Was cloudless as a summer heaven! The late</l>
<l>Dark brow was bright, the late pale cheek suffused</l>

<pb n="254" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/254"/>

<l>With roseate bloom; and, wondrous more than all,</l>
<l>Her weary eyes were changed to splendours now</l>
<l>That shot electric influence, and her lips</l>
<l>Were full and crimson, curled with stormy pride.</l>
<l>The doubting rabbi stood in wild amaze</l>
<l>To see the dying woman bold and fierce</l>
<l>In bright audacity of passion's power.</l>
<l>"These are the common changes," then she said,</l>
<l>"Of the fell ailment, that with torments strange,</l>
<l>Which search my deepest life, is tearing up</l>
<l>The dark foundations of my mortal state,</l>
<l>And sinking all its structures, hour by hour,</l>
<l>Into the dust of death. For nothing now</l>
<l>Is left me but to meet my nearing doom</l>
<l>As best I may in silent suffering."</l></lg>

<lg><l>Then as he heard her words and saw her face,</l>
<l>The rabbi in his wisdom knew some strong</l>
<l>Indwelling evil spirit troubled her,</l>
<l>And straightway for an unction sent, wherewith</l>
<l>The famous ancestor whose name he bore,</l>
<l>Herod the Great's chief hakim, had expelled</l>
<l>The dæmon haunter of the dying king.</l>
<l>With this he touched her forehead and her eyes</l>

<pb n="255" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/255"/>

<l>And all her finger-tips. Forthwith he made</l>
<l>Within a consecrated crucible</l>
<l>A fire of citron-wood and cinnamon;</l>
<l>Then splashed the flames with incense, mingling all</l>
<l>With the strong influence of fervent prayer;</l>
<l>And, as the smoke arose, he bowed her head</l>
<l>Into its coils, that so she might inhale</l>
<l>Its salutary odour—till the fiend</l>
<l>That dwelt within her should be exorcised.</l></lg>

<lg><l>Her face once more grew pale with pain; she writhed</l>
<l>In burning torment, uttering many words</l>
<l>Of most unhallowed meaning! Yet her eyes</l>
<l>Were fixed the while, and motionless her lips!</l>
<l>Whereby the rabbi certainly perceived</l>
<l>'Twas not the woman of herself that spake,</l>
<l>But the dread spirit that possessed her soul,</l>
<l>And thus it cried aloud.</l></lg></div>

<div type="poempart">

<head type="parthead"><hi rend="sc">Part</hi> II.</head>

<lg><l>"Why am I here, in this my last resort,</l>
<l>Perturbed with incense and anointings? Why</l>
<l>Compelled to listen to the sound of prayers</l>

<pb n="256" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/256"/>

<l>That smite me through as with the fire of God?</l>
<l>O pain, pain, pain! Is not this chamber full</l>
<l>Of the implacable stern punishers?</l>
<l>Full of avenging angels, holding each</l>
<l>A scourge of thunder in his potent hand,</l>
<l>Ready to lighten forth! and then, thus armed,</l>
<l>For ever chase and wound us as we fly!</l>
<l>Nor end with this—but, in each wound they make,</l>
<l>Pour venom sweltered from that tree As-gard,</l>
<l>Whose deadly shadow in its blackness falls</l>
<l>Over the lake of everlasting doom!</l></lg>

<lg><l>"Five hundred years ago, I, who thus speak,</l>
<l>Was an Egyptian of the splendid court</l>
<l>Of Ptolemy Philadelphus. To the top</l>
<l>Of mountainous power, though roughened with unrest,</l>
<l>And girt with dangers as with thunder-clouds,</l>
<l>Had I resolved by all resorts to climb;</l>
<l>By truth and falsehood, right and wrong alike;</l>
<l>And I did climb! Then firmly built in power</l>
<l>Second alone to my imperial lord's,</l>
<l>I crowned with its impunity my lust</l>
<l>Of beauty, sowing broadcast everywhere</l>
<l>Such sensual baits wide round me, as should lure</l>

<pb n="257" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/257"/>

<l>Through pleasure, or through interest entrap,</l>
<l>The fairest daughters of the land, and lo!</l>
<l>Their lustrous eyes surcharged with passionate light</l>
<l>The chambers of my harem! But at length</l>
<l>Wearied of these, though sweet, I set my heart</l>
<l>On riches, heaped to such a fabulous sum</l>
<l>As never one man's hoard in all the world</l>
<l>Might match; and to acquire them, steeped my life</l>
<l>In every public, every private wrong,</l>
<l>In lies, frauds, secret murders; till at last</l>
<l>A favoured minion I had trusted most,</l>
<l>And highest raised, unveiled before the king</l>
<l>The dark abysmal badness of my life;</l>
<l>But dearly did he rue it; nor till then</l>
<l>Guessed I how deadly grateful was revenge!</l>
<l>I stole into his chamber as he slept,</l>
<l>And with a sword, whose double edge for hours</l>
<l>I had whetted for the purpose of the deed,</l>
<l>There staked him through the midriff to his bed.</l>
<l>I fled; but first I sent, as oft before,</l>
<l>A present to the household of the man</l>
<l>Who had in secret my betrayer bribed.</l>
<l>'Twas scented wine, and rich Damascus cakes;</l>
<l>On these he feasted, and fell sudden down,</l>

<pb n="258" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/258"/>

<l>Rolling and panting in his dying pangs,</l>
<l>A poisoned desert dog!</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">"But I had fled.</l>
<l>A swift ship bore me, which my forecast long</l>
<l>Had kept prepared against such need as this.</l>
<l>Over the waves three days she proudly rode;</l>
<l>Then came a mighty storm, and trampled all</l>
<l>Her masted bravery flat, and still drove on</l>
<l>The wave-swept ruin towards a reefy shore!</l>
<l>Meanwhile amongst the terror-stricken crew</l>
<l>An ominous murmur went from mouth to mouth;</l>
<l>They grouped themselves in councils, and, ere long,</l>
<l>Grew loud and furious with surmises wild,</l>
<l>And maniac menaces, all aimed at me!</l>
<l>My fugitive head it was at which so loud</l>
<l>The thunder bellowed! The wild-shrieking winds</l>
<l>And roaring waters held in vengeful chase</l>
<l>Me only! me! whose signal crimes alone</l>
<l>Had brought on us this anger of the gods!</l>
<l>And thus reproaching me with glaring eyes,</l>
<l>They would have seized and slain me, but I sprang</l>
<l>Back from amongst them, and, outstriking, stabbed</l>
<l>With sudden blow their leader to the heart;</l>

<pb n="259" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/259"/>

<l>Then, with my poniard scaring off the rest,</l>
<l>Leaped from the deck, and swimming reached the shore,</l>
<l>From which, in savage triumph, I beheld</l>
<l>The battered ship, with all her howling crew,</l>
<l>Heel, and go down, amid the whelming waves.</l></lg>

<lg><l>"Inland my course now lay for many days,</l>
<l>O'er barren hills and glens, whose herbless scopes</l>
<l>Never grew luminous with a watery gleam,</l>
<l>Or heard the pleasant bubble of a brook,</l>
<l>For vast around the Afric desert stretched.</l>
<l>Starving and sun-scorched and afire with thirst,</l>
<l>I wandered ever on, until I came</l>
<l>To where, amid the dun and level waste,</l>
<l>In frightful loneliness, a mouldered group</l>
<l>Of ancient tombs stood ghostly. Here at last,</l>
<l>Utterly spent, in my despair I lay</l>
<l>Down on the burning sand, to gasp and die!</l>
<l>When from among the stones a withered man,</l>
<l>Old-seeming as the desert where he lived,</l>
<l>Came and stood by me, saying,'Get thee up!</l>
<l>Not much have I to give, but these at least</l>
<l>I offer to thy need, water and bread.'</l></lg>

<pb n="260" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/260"/>

<lg><l>"Then I arose and followed to his cell,—</l>
<l>A dismal cell, that seemed itself a tomb,</l>
<l>So lightless was it, and so foul with damp,</l>
<l>And at its entrance there were skulls and bones.</l>
<l>Long and deep drank I of the hermit's draught,</l>
<l>And munched full greedily the hermit's bread;</l>
<l>But with the strength which thence my frame derived,</l>
<l>Fierce rage devoured me, and I cursed my fate!</l>
<l>Whereat the withered creature laughed in scorn,</l>
<l>And mocked me with the malice of his eyes,</l>
<l>That sometimes, like a snake's, shrank small, and then</l>
<l>Enlarging blazed as with infernal fire!</l>
<l>Then, on a sudden, with an oath that seemed</l>
<l>To wake a stir in the grey musty tombs,</l>
<l>As if their silence shuddered, he averred</l>
<l>That he could lift me once more to the height</l>
<l>Of all my wishes—nay, even higher, but</l>
<l>On one condition only. Dared I swear,</l>
<l>By the dread angel of the second death,</l>
<l>I would be wholly his, both body and soul,</l>
<l>After a hundred years?</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">"'Why should I not?'</l>
<l>I answered, quivering with a stormy haste,</l>

<pb n="261" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/261"/>

<l>A rampant unreluctance! For so great</l>
<l>Was still my fury against all mankind,</l>
<l>And my desire of pomp and riches yet</l>
<l>So monstrous, that I felt I could have drunk</l>
<l>Blood, fire, or worse, to wear again the power</l>
<l>That fortune, working through my enemies' hands,</l>
<l>Had stript away from me. So, word by word,</l>
<l>I swore the oath as he repeated it;</l>
<l>Nor much it moved me, in my eagerness,</l>
<l>To feel a damp and earthy odour break</l>
<l>Out of each tomb, from which there darkling rose</l>
<l>At every word a hissing as of snakes;</l>
<l>And yet the fell of hair upon my scalp</l>
<l>Rose bristling under a cold creeping thrill:</l>
<l>But I failed not, I swore the dread oath through,</l>
<l>And then the tombs grew silent as their dead.</l>
<l>But through my veins a feeling of strong youth</l>
<l>Coursed bold along, and summered in my heart,</l>
<l>Till there before him in my pride I stood</l>
<l>In stately strength, and swift as is the wind,</l>
<l>Magnificent as a desert-nurtured steed</l>
<l>Of princeliest pedigree, with nostrils wide</l>
<l>Dilated, and with eyes effusing flame.</l>
<l>'Begone,' he said, 'and live thy hundred years</l>

<pb n="262" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/262"/>

<l>Of splendour, power, pleasure, ease.' His voice</l>
<l>Sighed off into the distance. He was gone:</l>
<l>Only a single raven, far aloft,</l>
<l>Was beating outwards with its sable wings;</l>
<l>The tombs had vanished, and the desert grey</l>
<l>Merged its whole circle with the bending sky.</l></lg></div>

<div type="poempart">

<head type="parthead"><hi rend="sc">Part</hi> III.</head>

<lg><l>"Out of these wilds to Egypt I returned:</l>
<l>Men thought that I had perished with the ship,</l>
<l>And no one knew me now, because my face</l>
<l>And form were greatly changed,—from passing fair</l>
<l>To fairer yet; from manly, to a pile</l>
<l>So nobly built, that in all eyes I seemed</l>
<l>Beauteous as Thammuz! And my heart was changed;</l>
<l>Ambition wilder than a leopard's thirst</l>
<l>For blood of roe, or flying hart, possessed</l>
<l>My spirit, like the madness of a god!</l>
<l>But this I yet even in its fiercest strain</l>
<l>Could curb and guide with sovereign strength of will.</l>
<l>From small beginnings onward still I worked,</l>
<l>Stepping as up a stair from rival head</l>
<l>To rival head,—from high to higher still,</l>

<pb n="263" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/263"/>

<l>Unto the loftiest post that might be held</l>
<l>Under the Ptolemies; and meantime paid</l>
<l>Each old unsettled score, defeating those</l>
<l>Who erst had worked against me, sweeping them</l>
<l>Out of all posts, all places; for though time</l>
<l>And change had wide dispersed them through the land,</l>
<l>The sleuth-hounds of my vengeance found them out!</l>
<l>Which things not being in a corner done,</l>
<l>What wonder was it that all Egypt now,</l>
<l>From end to end, even like a shaken hive,</l>
<l>Buzzed as disturbed with my portentous fame?</l></lg>

<lg><l>"And what to me were secret enemies?</l>
<l>Had I not also spies, who could pin down</l>
<l>A whisper in the dark and keep it there?</l>
<l>Could dash a covert frown by the same means</l>
<l>An open charge had challenged? Hence my name</l>
<l>Became a sound that struck through every heart</l>
<l>Ineffable dismay! And yet behold</l>
<l>The more I trampled on mankind, the more</l>
<l>Did fawning flatterers praise me as I swept</l>
<l>Like a malignant meteor through the land!</l>
<l>The more I hurled the mighty from their seats,</l>
<l>And triumphed o'er them prostrate in the dust,</l>

<pb n="264" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/264"/>

<l>The human hounds that licked my master hand</l>
<l>But multiplied the more! And still I strode</l>
<l>From bad to worse, corrupting as I went,</l>
<l>Making the lowly ones more abject yet;</l>
<l>Awing as with a thunder-bearing hand</l>
<l>The high and affluent; while I bound the strong</l>
<l>To basest service, even with chains of gold.</l>
<l>All hated, cursed and feared me, for in vain</l>
<l>Daggers were levelled at my brazen heart—</l>
<l>They glanced, and slew some minion at my side</l>
<l>Poison was harmless as a heifer's milk</l>
<l>When I had sipped it with my lips of scorn;</l>
<l>All that paraded pomp and smiling power</l>
<l>Could draw against me from the envious hearts</l>
<l>Of men in will as wicked as myself</l>
<l>I challenged, I encountered, and o'erthrew!</l></lg>

<lg><l>"But, after many years, exhaustion sere</l>
<l>Spread through the branches of my tree of life;</l>
<l>My forces flagged, my senses more and more</l>
<l>Were blunted, and incapable of joy;</l>
<l>The splendours of my rank availed me not;</l>
<l>A poverty as naked as a slave's</l>
<l>Peered from them mockingly. The pride of power</l>

<pb n="265" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/265"/>

<l>That glowed so strong within me in my youth</l>
<l>Was now like something dying at my heart.</l>
<l>To cheat or stimulate my jaded taste,</l>
<l>Feasts, choice or sumptuous, were devised in vain;</l>
<l>There was disfavour, there was fraud within,</l>
<l>Like that which filled the fair-appearing rind</l>
<l>Of those delusive apples that of old</l>
<l>Grew on the Dead Sea shore.</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">"And yet, though thus</l>
<l>All that gave pleasure to my younger life</l>
<l>Was withering from my path like summer grass,</l>
<l>I still had one intense sensation, which</l>
<l>Grew ever keener as my years increased—</l>
<l>A hatred of mankind; to pamper which</l>
<l>I gloated, with a burning in my soul,</l>
<l>Over their degradation; and like one</l>
<l>Merry with wine, I revelled day by day</l>
<l>In scattering baits that should corrupt them more:</l>
<l>The covetous I sharpened into thieves,</l>
<l>Urged the vindictive, hardened the malign,</l>
<l>Whetted the ruffian with self-interest,</l>
<l>And flung him then, a burning brand, abroad.</l>
<l>And the decadence of the state in which</l>

<pb n="266" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/266"/>

<l>My fortunes had recast me, served me well.</l>
<l>Excess reeled shameless in the court itself,</l>
<l>Or, staggering thence, was rivalled by the wild</l>
<l>Mad looseness of the crowd. Down to its death</l>
<l>The old Greek dynasty was sinking fast;</l>
<l>Waste and pale want, extortion, meanness, fraud—</l>
<l>These, welling outwards from the throne itself,</l>
<l>Spread through the land.</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">"But now there seized my soul</l>
<l>A new ambition—from his feeble throne</l>
<l>To hurl the king, and mount thereon myself!</l>
<l>To this end still I lured him into ill,</l>
<l>And daily wove around him cunning snares,</l>
<l>That reached and trammelled too his fawning court;</l>
<l>And all went well, the end at last was near,</l>
<l>But in my triumph one thing I forgot—</l>
<l>My time was measured. At a banquet held</l>
<l>In the king's chamber, lo! a guest appeared,</l>
<l>Chief of a Bactrian tribe, who tendered gold</l>
<l>To pay for some great wrong his desert horde</l>
<l>Had done our caravans; his age, men said,</l>
<l>Was wonderful; his craft more wondrous still;</l>
<l>For this his fame had spread through many lands,</l>

<pb n="267" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/267"/>

<l>And the dark seekers of forbidden lore</l>
<l>Knew this decrepit wretch to be their lord.</l></lg>

<lg><l>"The first glance that I met of his weird eye</l>
<l>Had sent into my soul a fearful doubt</l>
<l>That I had seen that cramp-shrunk withered form</l>
<l>And strange bright eye in some forgotten past.</l>
<l>But at the dry croak of his raven voice</l>
<l>Remembrance woke; I knew that I beheld</l>
<l>The old man of the tombs: I saw, and fell</l>
<l>Into the outer darkness of despair.</l>
<l>The day that was to close my dread account</l>
<l>Was come at last. The long triumphant feast</l>
<l>Of life had ended in a funeral treat.</l>
<l>I was to die—to suffer with the damned</l>
<l>The hideous torments of the second death!</l>
<l>The days, weeks, months of a whole hundred years</l>
<l>Seemed crushed into a thought, and burning out</l>
<l>In that brief period which was left me now.</l></lg>

<lg><l>"Stung with fierce horror, shame, and hate I fled;</l>
<l>I seized my sword, to plunge its ready point</l>
<l>Into my maddened heart, but on my arm</l>
<l>I felt a strong forbidding grasp! I turned;</l>

<pb n="268" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/268"/>

<l>The withered visage of the Bactrian met</l>
<l>My loathing eyes; I struggled to be free</l>
<l>From the shrunk wretch in vain; his spidery hands</l>
<l>Were strong as fetters of Ephesian brass,</l>
<l>And all my strength, though now with madness strung,</l>
<l>Was as a child's to his. He calmly smiled:</l>
<l>'Forbear, thou fool! am I not Sammael?</l>
<l>Whom to resist is vain, and from whom yet</l>
<l>Has never mercy flowed; for what to me</l>
<l>Are feelings which thou knowest even in men</l>
<l>Are found the most in fools. But wide around</l>
<l>A prince of lies I reign. 'Tis I that fill</l>
<l>The Persian palaces with lust and wrong,</l>
<l>Till like the darkling heads of sewers they flow</l>
<l>With a corruption that in fretting thence</l>
<l>Taints all the region round with rankest ill;</l>
<l>'Tis I that clot the Bactrian sand with blood;</l>
<l>And now I come to fling the brands of war</l>
<l>Through all this people, this most ill-mixed mob,</l>
<l>Where Afric's savage hordes meet treacherous Greeks,</l>
<l>And swarming Asia's luxury-wasted sons.</l>
<l>This land throughout shall be a deluge soon</l>
<l>Of blood and fire, till ruin stalk alone,</l>
<l>A grisly spectre, in its grass-grown marts.'</l></lg>

<pb n="269" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/269"/>

<lg><l>"The fiery eyes within his withered face</l>
<l>Glowed like live coals, as he triumphant spake,</l>
<l>And his strange voice, erewhile so thin and dry,</l>
<l>Came as if bellowed from the vaults of doom.</l>
<l>Prone fell I, powerless to move or speak;</l>
<l>And now he was about to plunge me down</l>
<l>Ten thousand times ten thousand fathoms deep</l>
<l>Through the earth's crust, and through the slimy beds</l>
<l>Of nether ocean—down! still down, below</l>
<l>The darkling roots of all this upper world</l>
<l>Into the regions of the courts of hell!</l></lg>

<lg><l>"To stamp me downward to the convict dead</l>
<l>His heel was raised, when suddenly I heard</l>
<l>Him heave a groan of superhuman pain,</l>
<l>So deep 'twas drawn! and as he groaned, I saw</l>
<l>A mighty downburst of celestial light</l>
<l>Enwrap his shrivelled form from head to foot,</l>
<l>As with a robe within whose venomous folds</l>
<l>He writhed in torment. Then above him stood</l>
<l>A shining shape, unspeakably sublime,</l>
<l>And gazed upon him! One of the high sons</l>
<l>Of Paradise, who still keep watch and ward</l>
<l>O'er Israel's progeny, where'er dispersed;</l>

<pb n="270" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/270"/>

<l>And now they fought for me with arms that filled</l>
<l>The air wide round with flashes and swift gleams</l>
<l>Of dazzling light; full soon the Evil One</l>
<l>Fell conquered. Then forth sprang he from the ground</l>
<l>And with dark curses wrapped him in a cloud</l>
<l>That moved aloft, low thundering as it went.</l></lg>

<lg><l>"And then the shining son of paradise</l>
<l>Came where I lay and spoke, his glorious face</l>
<l>Severe with wrath, and yet divinely fair—</l>
<l>'O Child of Guilt! should vengeance not be wrought</l>
<l>On thee as well? On Sammael's willing slave?'</l>
<l>I clasped his radiant knees—I wept—I groaned—</l>
<l>I beat my bosom in my wild distress.</l>
<l>At last the sacred Presence, who had held</l>
<l>The blow suspended still, spoke thus: 'Thou'rt spared;</l>
<l>From no weak pity, but because thou art</l>
<l>Descended from the line of Israel:</l>
<l>For that cause spared;—yet must thou at my hand</l>
<l>Find some meet punishment.' And as he spake,</l>
<l>He laid his hand with a life-crushing weight</l>
<l>Upon my forehead—and I fell, as dead!</l></lg></div>

<pb n="271" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/271"/>

<div type="poempart">

<head type="parthead"><hi rend="sc">Part</hi> IV.</head>

<lg><l>"Awaking as from sleep, I bounded up,</l>
<l>Stung with a feeling of enormous strength,</l>
<l>Though yet half wild with horror. Onward then</l>
<l>Ramping I went, out through the palace gates,</l>
<l>Down the long streets, and into the highways,</l>
<l>Forth to the wilds, amazed at my own speed!</l>
<l>And now afar, in long-drawn line appeared</l>
<l>A caravan upon its outward way</l>
<l>Over the desert of Pentapolis.</l>
<l>And strange the instinct seemed that urged me then</l>
<l>To rush amongst them—and devour: for I</l>
<l>Was fierce with hunger, and inflamed with thirst.</l></lg>

<lg><l>"Amidst a laggard company I leaped</l>
<l>That rested yet beside a cooling spring;</l>
<l>One of those clear springs that, like giant pearls,</l>
<l>Inlay the burning borders of the grey</l>
<l>Enormous desert. All at once they rose!</l>
<l>Some fled, some threw themselves amongst the brakes,</l>
<l>Some seized their swords and lances; this to see</l>
<l>Filled me at once with a mysterious rage</l>
<l>And savage joy! The sternness of their looks,</l>

<pb n="272" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/272"/>

<l>Their fearful cries, the gleaming of their spears</l>
<l>Seemed to insult me, and I rushed on them.</l>
<l>Then sudden spasms of pain searched deep my side,</l>
<l>Wherein a fell lance quivered. On I rushed;</l>
<l>I roared a roar that startled e'en myself,</l>
<l>So loud and hoarse and terrible its tone,</l>
<l>Then bounding, irresistible it seemed</l>
<l>As some huge fragment from a crag dislodged,</l>
<l>Against the puny wretch that sent the lance,</l>
<l>Instantly tore him, as he were a kid,</l>
<l>All into gory shreds! The others fled</l>
<l>At sight of this, nor would I chase them then,</l>
<l>All wearied by my flight. Besides, the well</l>
<l>Was gleaming in its coolness by me there.</l></lg>

<lg><l>"And as I stooped to quench my parching thirst,</l>
<l>Behold, reversed within the water clear,</l>
<l>The semblance of a monstrous lion stood!</l>
<l>I saw his shaggy mane, I saw his red</l>
<l>And glaring eyeballs rolling in amaze,</l>
<l>His rough and grinning lips, his long sharp fangs</l>
<l>All foul with gore and hung with strings of flesh!</l>
<l>I shrank away in horrible dismay.</l>
<l>But as the sun each moment fiercer grew,</l>

<pb n="273" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/273"/>

<l>I soon returned to stoop and slake my thirst.</l>
<l>Again was that tremendous presence there</l>
<l>Standing reversed, as erewhile, in the clear</l>
<l>And gleaming mirror of the smiling well!</l>
<l>The horrid truth smote like a rush of fire</l>
<l>Upon my brain! The dreadful thing I saw</l>
<l>Was my own shadow! I was a wild beast."</l></lg>

<lg><l>"They did not fable, then, who held that oft</l>
<l>The guilty dead are punished in the shapes</l>
<l>Of beasts, if brutal were their lives as men."</l></lg>

<lg><l>"Long lapped I the cool lymph, while still my tongue</l>
<l>Made drip for drip against that monstrous one,</l>
<l>Which, as in ugly mockery, from below</l>
<l>Seemed to lap up against it. But though thirst</l>
<l>Was quenched at length, what was there might appease</l>
<l>The baffled misery of my fated soul?</l>
<l>The thought that I no more was human, ran</l>
<l>Like scorpion venom through my mighty frame;</l>
<l>Fiercely I bounded, tearing up the sands,</l>
<l>That, like a drab mist, coursed me as I went</l>
<l>Out on my homeless track. I made my fangs</l>
<l>Meet in my flesh, trusting to find in pain</l>

<pb n="274" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/274"/>

<l>Some respite from the anguish of regret.</l>
<l>From morn to night, from night to morn, I fled,</l>
<l>Chased by the memory of my lost estate;</l>
<l>Then, worn and bleeding, in the burning sands</l>
<l>I lay down, as to die. In vain!—in vain!</l>
<l>The savage vigour of my lion-life</l>
<l>Might yield alone to the long tract of time.</l></lg>

<lg><l>"From hill to valley rushing after prey,</l>
<l>With whirlwind speed, was now my daily wont,</l>
<l>For all things fled before me—all things shrank</l>
<l>In mortal terror at my shaggy front.</l>
<l>Sometimes I sought those close-fenced villages,</l>
<l>Wherein the desert-dwellers hide their swart</l>
<l>And naked bodies from the scorching heats,</l>
<l>Hoping that I might perish by their shafts.</l>
<l>And often was I wounded—often bore</l>
<l>Their poisoned arrows in my burning flesh—</l>
<l>But still I lived.</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">"The tenor of my life</l>
<l>Was always this—the solitary state</l>
<l>Of a wild beast of prey, that hunted down</l>
<l>The antelope, the boar, the goat, and gorged</l>
<l>Their quivering flesh, and lapped their steaming blood;</l>

<pb n="275" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/275"/>

<l>Then slept till hunger, or the hunter's cry,</l>
<l>Roused him again to battle or to slay,</l>
<l>To flight, pursuit, blood, stratagem, and wounds.</l>
<l>And to make this rude life more hideous yet,</l>
<l>I still retained a consciousness of all</l>
<l>The nobler habits of my earlier time,</l>
<l>And had a keen sense of what most had moved</l>
<l>My nature as a man, and knew besides</l>
<l>That this my punishment was fixed by One</l>
<l>Too mighty to be questioned, and too just</l>
<l>One tittle of its measure to remit.</l></lg>

<lg><l>"How long this haggard course of life went on</l>
<l>I might not even guess, for I had lost</l>
<l>The human faculty that measures time.</l>
<l>But still from night to night I found myself</l>
<l>Roaming the desert, howling at the moon,</l>
<l>Whose cold light always, as she poured it down,</l>
<l>Awoke a drear distemper in my brain:</l>
<l>But much I shunned the sunblaze, which at once</l>
<l>Inflamed me, and revealed my dread approach.</l></lg>

<lg><l>"Homelessly roaming thus for evermore,</l>
<l>The tempests beat on my unsheltered bulk,</l>

<pb n="276" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/276"/>

<pb n="276" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/276"/>

<l>In those bleak seasons when the drenching rains</l>
<l>Drove into covert all those gentler beasts</l>
<l>That were my natural prey. I swinkt beneath</l>
<l>The furnace heats of the midsummer sun,</l>
<l>When even the palm of the oasis stood</l>
<l>All withered, like a weed: and for how long,</l>
<l>Yet knew not.</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">"Thus the sun and moon arose</l>
<l>Through an interminable tract of time,</l>
<l>And yet though sense was dim, the view of all</l>
<l>My human life was ever at my beck,</l>
<l>Nay, opened out before me of itself</l>
<l>Plain as the pictures in a wizard's glass!</l>
<l>I saw again the trains that round my car</l>
<l>Streamed countless, saw its pageants and its pomps,</l>
<l>Its faces fair and passionate, and felt</l>
<l>Life's eager pleasures, even its noble pangs!</l>
<l>Then in the anguish of my goaded heart</l>
<l>Would I roll howling in the burning sand.</l></lg>

<lg><l>"At length this life of horror seemed to near</l>
<l>Its fated bourn. The slow but sure approach</l>
<l>Of old decay was felt in every limb</l>

<pb n="277" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/277"/>

<l>And every function of my lion frame.</l>
<l>My massive strength seemed spent, my speed was gone,</l>
<l>The antelope escaped me! Wearily</l>
<l>I sought a mountain cavern, shut from day</l>
<l>By savage draperies of tangled briers,</l>
<l>And only dragged my tardy bulk abroad</l>
<l>When hunger urged. It chanced on such a day</l>
<l>I sprang amid a herd of buffaloes</l>
<l>And tore their leader down, who bellowing fell.</l>
<l>When, lo! the chief of those that drove them came</l>
<l>Against me, and I turned my rage on him:</l>
<l>But though the long lapse of so many years</l>
<l>Of ever-grinding wretchedness had dulled</l>
<l>My memory, I felt that I had seen</l>
<l>His withered visage twice before; and straight</l>
<l>A shuddering awe subdued me, and I crouched</l>
<l>Beneath him in the dust. My lust of blood,</l>
<l>My ruthless joy at sight of mortal pain,</l>
<l>Within me died, and if in human speech</l>
<l>I might have told the wild desire that filled</l>
<l>My being, I had prayed him once for all</l>
<l>To crush me out of life, and to consign</l>
<l>My misery to the pit of final death!</l>
<l>But when, all hopeless, I again looked up,</l>

<pb n="278" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/278"/>

<l>The tawny presence of the desert chief</l>
<l>Was gone, and I beheld the shining son</l>
<l>Of paradise, from whose majestic brow</l>
<l>There flashed the lightnings of a wrath divine.</l>
<l>Yea, 'twas the angel that with Sammael</l>
<l>Had fought for me in Egypt; and once more</l>
<l>He laid his crushing hand upon my front;</l>
<l>And earth and sky, and all that in them is,</l>
<l>Became to me a darkness, swimming blank</l>
<l>In the Eternal, round that point where now</l>
<l>My body lay, stretched dead upon the sand.</l></lg></div>

<div type="poempart">

<head type="parthead"><hi rend="sc">Part</hi> V.</head>

<lg><l>"Again I lived—again I felt. But now</l>
<l>The winds of heaven seemed under me, and I</l>
<l>Was sweeping, like the spirit of a storm</l>
<l>That bellowed round me, in its murky glooms,</l>
<l>All heaving with a motion wide and swift</l>
<l>That seemed yet mightier than the darkling swells</l>
<l>Of ocean, wrestling with a midnight gale!</l>
<l>The wild winds tossed me; I was drenched throughout</l>
<l>With heavy moisture, and at intervals</l>
<l>Amid the ragged gaps of moving cloud,</l>

<pb n="279" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/279"/>

<l>Methought I caught dim glimpses of the sun</l>
<l>Hanging aloft, as if in drear eclipse;</l>
<l>But as my senses cleared, I saw my limbs</l>
<l>Were clothed with plumage; and long-taloned claws</l>
<l>Were closing eagerly with fierce desire</l>
<l>And sudden hunger after blood and prey!</l>
<l>An impulse to pursue and to destroy</l>
<l>Both on the earth and in the air, ran quick</l>
<l>Out from my heart and shivered in my wings;</l>
<l>And as a thing more central yet, I felt</l>
<l>Pregnant within me, throned o'er all, a lone</l>
<l>And sullen, yet majestic, glow of pride.</l></lg>

<lg><l>"'Twas plain that I, who had aforetime been</l>
<l>Crushed out of human being into that</l>
<l>Of a wild beast, had thence again passed on</l>
<l>Into the nature of some mighty thing</l>
<l>That now swept sailing on wide van-like wings,</l>
<l>Amid the whirls of an aërial gloom,</l>
<l>That out extending in one mighty cope</l>
<l>Hung heaving, like a black tent-roof, o'er all</l>
<l>The floor of Africa.</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">"Still on I swept,</l>
<l>And still as far as my keen vision went,</l>

<pb n="280" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/280"/>

<l>That now was gifted with a power that seemed</l>
<l>To pierce all space, I saw the vapours roll</l>
<l>In dreadful continuities of black</l>
<l>And shapeless masses, by the winds convulsed;</l>
<l>But soon in the remotest distance came</l>
<l>A change: the clouds were touched with sunny light,</l>
<l>And, as I nearer drew, I saw them dash,</l>
<l>Like the wild surges of an uproused sea</l>
<l>Of molten gold, against the marble sides</l>
<l>Of lofty mountains, which, though far below</l>
<l>My flight, yet pierced up through them all, and stood</l>
<l>With splintered cones and monster-snouted crags,</l>
<l>Immovable as fate. Beneath me, lo!</l>
<l>The grandeur of the kingdom of the air</l>
<l>Was circling in its magnitude! It was</l>
<l>A dread magnificence of which before</l>
<l>I might not even dream. I saw its quick</l>
<l>And subtle interchange of forms and hues,</l>
<l>Saw its black reservoirs of densest rain,</l>
<l>Its awful forges of the thunderstorm.</l></lg>

<lg><l>"At last, as onward still I swept, above</l>
<l>A milky mass of vapour far outspread,</l>
<l>Behold, reflected in its quiet gleam,</l>

<pb n="281" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/281"/>

<l>I saw an image that swept on with me,</l>
<l>Reversed as was the lion's in the well,</l>
<l>With van-like wings, with eyeballs seething fire,</l>
<l>With taloned claws, and cruel down-bent beak,—</l>
<l>The mightiest eagle that had ever sailed</l>
<l>The seas of space since Adam named the first!</l></lg>

<lg><l>"My fated soul had passed into the form</l>
<l>Of that huge eagle which swept shadowed there.</l>
<l>Cold horror thrilled me! I was once again</l>
<l>Imprisoned in the being of a brute,</l>
<l>In the base being of a nature yet</l>
<l>Inferior by what infinite descent</l>
<l>To that poor remnant of intelligence</l>
<l>Which still kept with me,—like a put-back soul</l>
<l>Burningly conscious of its powers foregone,</l>
<l>Its inborn sov'reignty of kind, and yet</l>
<l>So latent, self-less; once again to live</l>
<l>A life of carnage, and to sail abroad</l>
<l>A terror to all birds and gentle beasts</l>
<l>That heard the stormy rushings of my wings!</l>
<l>A royal bird indeed, who lived alone</l>
<l>In the great stillness of the mighty hills,</l>
<l>Or in the highest heavens.</l></lg>

<pb n="282" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/282"/>

<lg><l part="F">"But in truth</l>
<l>Not much for many seasons had I need</l>
<l>To search for prey, for countless hosts of men,</l>
<l>Forth mustering over all the face of earth,</l>
<l>Cast the quick gleam of arms o'er trampled leagues</l>
<l>Of golden corn, and as they onward marched</l>
<l>They left behind them seas of raging fire,</l>
<l>In whose red surges cities thronged with men</l>
<l>And happy hamlets, homes of health and peace,</l>
<l>That rang erewhile with rural thankfulness,</l>
<l>Were whelmed in one wide doom; or in their strength</l>
<l>Confronted upon some set field of fight,</l>
<l>Their sullen masses charged with dreadful roar</l>
<l>That far out-yelled the fiercest yells of beasts,</l>
<l>And with brute madness rushed on wounds and death;</l>
<l>Or else about fenced cities they would pitch</l>
<l>Their crowded camps, and leaguer them for years,</l>
<l>Sowing the fields about them with a slime</l>
<l>Of carnage, till their growths were plagues alone.</l>
<l>What is the ravage made by brutes on brutes</l>
<l>To that man makes on man?</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">"With mingled pain</l>
<l>And joy I saw the wondrous ways of men,</l>

<pb n="283" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/283"/>

<l>(For ever when I hungered, close at hand,</l>
<l>Some fresh slain man lay smoking in his gore)</l>
<l>And though the instincts of the eagle's life</l>
<l>Were fierce within me, yet I felt myself</l>
<l>Cast in a lot more capable of joy;</l>
<l>Safe from pursuit, from famine, and from wounds.</l>
<l>Some solaces, though few and far between,</l>
<l>Were added to me; and I argued thence,</l>
<l>In the dark musings of my eagle heart,</l>
<l>That not for ever was my soul condemned</l>
<l>To suffer in the body of a brute;</l>
<l>For though remembrance of the towering crimes</l>
<l>And matchless lusts, that filled my whole career</l>
<l>Of human life, worked in me evermore,</l>
<l>No longer did they shed about my life</l>
<l>So venomous a blight. Nay, I could think</l>
<l>How often I had looked with longing eyes</l>
<l>Up at the clear Egyptian heavens, and watched</l>
<l>The wings that cleft them, envying every bird</l>
<l>That, soaring in the sunshine, seemed to be</l>
<l>Exempt from all the grovelling cares of men.</l>
<l>I thought how once, when with my hunting train</l>
<l>I pierced that region round the cataracts,</l>
<l>I watched an eagle as it rose aloft</l>

<pb n="284" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/284"/>

<l>Into the lovely blue, and wished to change</l>
<l>My being with it as it floated on,</l>
<l>So inaccessible to hate or hurt,</l>
<l>So peaceful, at a height in heaven so safe;</l>
<l>And then it passed away through gorgeous clouds</l>
<l>Against the sunset, through the feathered flags</l>
<l>Of royal purple edged with burning gold.</l></lg>

<lg><l>"These fields of space were my dominion now;</l>
<l>Motion alone within a world so rich</l>
<l>Was something noble: but to move at will,</l>
<l>Upward or forward, or in circles vast,</l>
<l>Through boundless spaces with a rushing speed</l>
<l>No living thing might rival, and to see</l>
<l>The glory of the everlasting hills</l>
<l>Beneath me, and the myriad-peopled plains,</l>
<l>Broad rivers, and the towery towns that sate</l>
<l>Beside their spacious mouths, with out beyond</l>
<l>The lonely strength of the resounding seas—</l>
<l>This liberty began to move my sense</l>
<l>As something godlike; and in moving made</l>
<l>A sure impression that kept graining still</l>
<l>Into the texture of my brute estate—</l>

<pb n="285" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/285"/>

<l>Yea, graining in through all its fleshy lusts</l>
<l>And savage wonts.</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">"Hence ever more and more</l>
<l>The temper of a better spirit grew</l>
<l>Within me, as from inkling roots, and moved</l>
<l>E'en like an embryon in its moist recess:</l>
<l>A sensibility to beauteous things</l>
<l>As now I saw them in the heavens displayed,</l>
<l>And in the bright luxuriance of the earth;</l>
<l>Some power of just comparison, some sense</l>
<l>Of how a man would rank them, could he see</l>
<l>Those earthly grandeurs from the sov'reign height</l>
<l>Whence I beheld them. And with this a wish</l>
<l>To commune even with the human race,</l>
<l>And pour the loftier wonders of my life</l>
<l>Into their ears, through a rich-worded song</l>
<l>Whose golden periods in mellow flow</l>
<l>Should witch all ears that heard them—ev'n old men's,</l>
<l>Ev'n jaded monarchs; not to speak of theirs,</l>
<l>Those spirit-lovely ones—yea, moons of love,</l>
<l>That rise at first in the Circassian hills—</l>
<l>And they should tingle all like tiny shells</l>
<l>Of roseate whiteness to its perfect chords.</l></lg>

<pb n="286" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/286"/>

<lg><l>"One day amid the mountains of the moon,</l>
<l>Behold a sudden storm had gatherd up</l>
<l>Out of my view, hid by a neighbouring height,</l>
<l>But which, thence wheeling with terrific force,</l>
<l>Wide tossed me with its gusts—aloft, and then</l>
<l>Downward as far; then whirlingly about,</l>
<l>Ev'n like a withered leaf. My strength of wing</l>
<l>Availed me nought, so mightily it raged;</l>
<l>Then suddenly, in the dim distance, lo!</l>
<l>I saw, as from the storm's Plutonian heart,</l>
<l>A mass of white-hot light come writhing forth,</l>
<l>And then the figure of a withered man</l>
<l>Seemed dropping headlong through the lurid clouds;</l>
<l>While full within the radiant light, again</l>
<l>The conquering son of paradise appeared,</l>
<l>Upon whose brow divine I yet might trace</l>
<l>Some sign of wrath. Onward the vision rushed,</l>
<l>Orbed in white light. I felt a stifling heat,</l>
<l>One cruel blasting pang, and headlong then</l>
<l>Fell earthward—dead; a plumb descending mass.</l></lg></div>

<pb n="287" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/287"/>

<div type="poempart">

<head type="parthead"><hi rend="sc">Part</hi> VI.</head>

<lg><l>"Within a rustic chamber, dark and low,</l>
<l>Thronged with wild-looking men and women strange,</l>
<l>I seemed to waken. Inwardly I felt</l>
<l>No briskness of existence, but a sense</l>
<l>Of languor rather, or revival slow:</l>
<l>And evermore the men and women came</l>
<l>And gazed upon me, shouting in amaze,</l>
<l>Then would they whirl about the room in dance,</l>
<l>Abandoned to their barbarous delight.</l></lg>

<lg><l>"I turned mine eyes about the low-roofed room,</l>
<l>Half fearing and half hoping I might see</l>
<l>The mighty angel that now ruled my life;</l>
<l>They thought I needed air, and I was borne</l>
<l>To a low casement. Like a picture lay</l>
<l>The world without. On all sides wide around</l>
<l>Nothing but mountains, feathered to their tops</l>
<l>With a dense growth of pines, and valleys filled</l>
<l>With a cold darkness that was lit alone</l>
<l>By the broad flashes of the furious streams</l>
<l>That leaped in thunder out of marble gaps!</l>

<pb n="288" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/288"/>

<l>Dull vapours, like a canopy of smoke,</l>
<l>Did so obscure the sun, that I had thought</l>
<l>The scene that now I saw was not of earth,</l>
<l>But for a golden flush that now and then</l>
<l>Would touch the highest ranges. What I was</l>
<l>I knew not, but I felt my former wants,</l>
<l>And oft I made vain efforts to expand</l>
<l>The wings I had no longer, and sail off,</l>
<l>And through those sullen vapours—up, and up—</l>
<l>Into the mighty silence of the blue.</l></lg>

<lg><l>"The day was fading, and a blare of horns,</l>
<l>With many voices and much trampling noise,</l>
<l>Heard from without, aroused me; and, ere long,</l>
<l>Women rushed in, each bearing some rich robe</l>
<l>Or some gay bauble, wherewithal they next</l>
<l>Arrayed me to their taste; and then they held</l>
<l>A mirror up before me, and I saw</l>
<l>My soul had this time passed into the form</l>
<l>Of a fair damsel. She, whose form I now</l>
<l>Re-animated, was—so learned I soon—</l>
<l>The only child of a Circassian chief,</l>
<l>Who had been long regarded by her house</l>
<l>As its chief treasure, for her beauty rare;</l>

<pb n="289" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/289"/>

<l>Reserved for him, no matter whence he came,</l>
<l>Whose hand could dip into the longest purse.</l>
<l>But envy lurks in the Circassian hills</l>
<l>As elsewhere, and a dose of opium,</l>
<l>Administered by one who had been long</l>
<l>The rival beauty of a neighbouring tribe,</l>
<l>Had served to quash a bargain quite complete</l>
<l>Save in the final payment of the gold,</l>
<l>Which had been even offered and told down,</l>
<l>And only <hi rend="it">not</hi> accepted, through some old</l>
<l>Delaying ceremony of the tribe;</l>
<l>And in this luckless circumstance, 'twas plain</l>
<l>That both my admirable parents saw</l>
<l>The unkindest turn of all.</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">"On all hands forth</l>
<l>Had scouts been sent to summon the whole tribe</l>
<l>To attend my obsequies, and then forthwith</l>
<l>Exterminate our ancient enemies</l>
<l>Through all their tents—such was the fierce resolve.</l>
<l>But while these things were pending, lo! the light</l>
<l>Had broken like a new morn from the eyes</l>
<l>Of the dead beauty; on her cheeks had dawned</l>
<l>A roseate colour; from her moistening lips</l>

<pb n="290" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/290"/>

<l>Low murmurs, too, had broken; whereupon</l>
<l>My parents in exulting hope transformed</l>
<l>The funeral to a general tribal feast,</l>
<l>And loaded me with all the ancient gauds</l>
<l>And ornaments they held. The Persian, too,</l>
<l>Had been invited to renew his suit,</l>
<l>And carry me at once beyond the reach</l>
<l>Of future opium doses.</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">"Soon he came</l>
<l>Galloping back to bear me to the arms</l>
<l>Of his long-bearded lord. He paid the price;</l>
<l>My worthy parents took a fond farewell</l>
<l>Of me, with tears declaring me to be</l>
<l>The life-light of their eyes, their rose of joy,—</l>
<l>Then stretched their palms out for the stranger's gold,</l>
<l>And hurried off to count it o'er again—</l>
<l>The dear recovered treasure they so late</l>
<l>Had mourned as lost for ever. On that night</l>
<l>I was packed neatly on a camel's back</l>
<l>Beside a precious case of porcelain pipes,</l>
<l>And carried Persia-ward, by stages safe,</l>
<l>From the Circassian mountains.</l></lg>

<pb n="291" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/291"/>

<lg><l part="F">"At the court</l>
<l>I soon became the favourite of the king;</l>
<l>Lived sumptuously, but in perpetual fear:</l>
<l>For all my luxury and gold and gems,</l>
<l>I envied the poor slaves who swept the floors.</l>
<l>I was the favourite of my Persian lord</l>
<l>For one whole month, perhaps a little more,</l>
<l>And then I learned my place was to be filled;</l>
<l>And though I loathed him, as we loathe some cold</l>
<l>And reptile creature, yet I could not bear</l>
<l>To see a newer rival take my place,</l>
<l>For I was beautiful, and therefore vain:</l>
<l>So, that I might regain his favour past,</l>
<l>I now arrayed myself in airy robes,</l>
<l>While scarfs of purple like an orient queen's </l>
<l>Barred them with brilliant tints, and gold and pearls</l>
<l>Confined the wavelets of my sunny hair.</l></lg>

<lg><l>"The harem all applauded, and there seemed</l>
<l>Even in his own dull eyes almost a flash</l>
<l>As of extorted joy, but this became</l>
<l>At the next moment a malignant scowl,</l>
<l>Which had its dark cause in such thoughts as these:</l>
<l>'What! did so soft and ignorant a thing</l>

<pb n="292" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/292"/>

<l>Hope to enchant again a man so wise</l>
<l>As he was—he! the paragon of kings!</l>
<l>By floating in before him like a swan,</l>
<l>A little better feathered than before?'</l>
<l>And then he waved the harem ladies forth,</l>
<l>And with him kept only a Nubian girl,</l>
<l>Whom he thought dull, and altogether his:</l>
<l>A conclave of those strange demoniac dwarfs</l>
<l>Who from their secret dens and crypts would come</l>
<l>On given signals forth, was summoned in:</l>
<l>Wizard-like beings, with enormous heads,</l>
<l>Splay-feet, and monstrous spider-fingered hands.</l>
<l>Nor was the council long; I on that night</l>
<l>Was to be poisoned with a pomegranate.</l>
<l>Then stole the Nubian girl away, and brought</l>
<l>Me word of all; yet her news moved me not,</l>
<l>So sure I felt that this was not my doom;</l>
<l>Or moved me only to prepare for flight</l>
<l>With the poor Nubian girl. Unseen I came</l>
<l>To my own chamber, where I packed my goods;</l>
<l>And whence, unseen by all, we swiftly fled.</l></lg>

<lg><l>"Twas plain and patent to my inmost self</l>
<l>That in this last change I had always been</l>

<pb n="293" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/293"/>

<l>Regenerating more and more; for though</l>
<l>I had a love of mischief in my head,</l>
<l>At heart I was not bad, and they who knew</l>
<l>Me closely, or at least the woman sort,</l>
<l>Loved me,—nay, served me, as the Nubian did.</l>
<l>And now, as no one else might sell me,—lo!</l>
<l>I sold myself, and found myself installed</l>
<l>Queen of a rude baboon-like Afric king.</l></lg>

<lg><l>"Then I was captive to a Bedouin sheik,</l>
<l>Was sold in the slave-mart of Astrachan,</l>
<l>And carried thence to India, to be crowned</l>
<l>A rajahpoot's sultana; from which state</l>
<l>Flying at length, I fell into a worse,</l>
<l>Being pounced on by a Turkoman horse-stealer.</l>
<l>At Alexandra I became the slave</l>
<l>Of a harsh Roman matron, who was wont</l>
<l>To flog and famish me to make me good,</l>
<l>And when I owned myself converted, then</l>
<l>She flogged and famished me the more, to make</l>
<l>My goodness lasting; and I finally</l>
<l>Fell stabbed in Cairo—slaughtered by a slave.</l></lg></div>

<pb n="294" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/294"/>

<div type="poempart">

<head type="parthead"><hi rend="sc">Part</hi> VII.</head>

<lg><l>"After some short and intermediate terms</l>
<l>Of transmigration, all in female forms,</l>
<l>In which, through kindly offices performed,</l>
<l>It seemed the temper of my spirit much</l>
<l>Had humanized, and in the last of which</l>
<l>'Twas mine to die for once a natural death,</l>
<l>Again I had some deep-down hold on being,</l>
<l>Dim as an oyster's in its ocean-bed;</l>
<l>Then came a sense of light and air, of space,</l>
<l>Of hunger, comfort, warmth, of sight and sound</l>
<l>I caught at length the drift of speech, and knew</l>
<l>That all who came to see me and admire</l>
<l>Called me Ben Bachai's daughter.</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">"Dark indeed,</l>
<l>But lovely as a starry night I grew,</l>
<l>A maid, the glory of her father's house,</l>
<l>Her mother's dovelet, filling all her wonts</l>
<l>With tenderness and joy. Still as I grew,</l>
<l>By strange degrees the memory of all</l>
<l>That I had been came back upon my mind</l>
<l>To fill it with wild sorrow and dismay;</l>

<pb n="295" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/295"/>

<l>To know I was a cheat, nor wholly what</l>
<l>I seemed to my fond parents—that I was</l>
<l>But half their daughter, and the rest a fiend,</l>
<l>With a fiend's destiny,—ah! this, I say,</l>
<l>Would smite me even in dreams with icy pangs</l>
<l>Of wordless woe, yea, even while I slept</l>
<l>So innocently as it seemed, and so</l>
<l>Securely happy in the arms of love!"</l></lg>

<lg><l>As this was said, the Rabbi looked, and saw</l>
<l>That now again the woman seemed to speak</l>
<l>As of herself, and not as heretofore</l>
<l>With moveless lips, and prisoned voice, that came</l>
<l>As from some dark duality within.</l>
<l>Her looks had changed, too, with the voice, and now</l>
<l>Again she lay, a queen-like creature, racked</l>
<l>With mortal sufferings, who, when these grew less,</l>
<l>Or for a time remitted, even thus</l>
<l>Took up her tale again.</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">"At length upgrown</l>
<l>To womanhood, by some mysterious pact</l>
<l>Existing 'twixt my father's house and that</l>
<l>Of an Arabian prince time out of mind,</l>
<l>I was now wedded ere I wished, and he,</l>

<pb n="296" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/296"/>

<l>My husband, finally had come to claim</l>
<l>And bear me from my home, that happiest home</l>
<l>Which I should know no more: a man most fair</l>
<l>To look upon, but void of force, in truth</l>
<l>The weakling of a worn-out line, who yet</l>
<l>(What merit in a prince!) was not depraved,</l>
<l>Not wicked, not the mendicant of lust,</l>
<l>But mild, and even affectionate and just.</l>
<l>My dowry was immense, and flushed with this</l>
<l>The prince had summoned from his vassal tribe</l>
<l>Five hundred horse, all spearmen, to escort</l>
<l>And guard us desert-ward. And as we went</l>
<l>These ever and anon, at signal given,</l>
<l>Would whirl around us like a thunder-cloud</l>
<l>Wind-torn, and shooting instant shafts of fire!</l>
<l>And thus we roamed about the Arabian wastes,</l>
<l>Pitching our camp amid the fairest spots.</l>
<l>Beneath an awning oft I lay, and gazed</l>
<l>Out at the cloudless ether, where it wrapt</l>
<l>The silent hills, like to a conscious power</l>
<l>Big with the soul of an eternal past.</l></lg>

<lg><l>"But long this life might last not, for the prince</l>
<l>Sickened and died;—died poor, his wealth and mine</l>

<pb n="297" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/297"/>

<l>Having been squandered on the hungry horde</l>
<l>That wont to prance about us; who ere long,</l>
<l>Divining my extremity, grew loud</l>
<l>And urgent for rewards, till on a day,</l>
<l>By concert as it seemed, the tribe entire</l>
<l>Came fiercely round me, all demanding gifts,</l>
<l>Gifts that I had not; as they nearer pressed,</l>
<l>Wearing his way among them, lo! I saw</l>
<l>The old man of the tombs! the Bactrian sage!</l>
<l>With signs of awe they made him room to pass;</l>
<l>He fixed me with his shrunk and serpent eyes,</l>
<l>Waved off the abject Arabs, and then asked</l>
<l>'Why art thou poor? with needs so great upon thee?</l>
<l>I offer thee long life and wealth and power.'</l></lg>

<lg><l>"I turned to him and said: 'Should I not know,</l>
<l>By all the past, the nature of thy gifts?</l>
<l>Shows and delusions, evil, sin-stained all,</l>
<l>And terminating in eternal loss.'</l>
<l>'Well, take it as thou wilt,' he said; 'my gifts</l>
<l>Are not so weighed by all.' And saying this</l>
<l>He went his way, while I retired within</l>
<l>My lonely tent to weep.</l></lg>

<pb n="298" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/298"/>

<lg><l part="F">"Next day the tribes</l>
<l>Again assembled, and with threats and cries,</l>
<l>And insults loud, they raised a passion in me.</l>
<l>My blood arose: I chid them angrily,</l>
<l>Called them all things but men, till they, alarmed,</l>
<l>Fell back in sullen silence for a while,</l>
<l>Crouching like tigers ready for a spring.</l>
<l>Humbled, perplexed, and frightened, I returned</l>
<l>Into my tent, and there within its folds</l>
<l>Stood the weird Bactrian with his snaky eyes,</l>
<l>And wiry voice that questioned as before:</l>
<l>'Why art thou poor? why dost thou suffer wrong,</l>
<l>With all this petty baseness brattling round?</l>
<l>Am I not here to help thee? I, thy one</l>
<l>Sole friend—not empty, but with ample means.</l>
<l>Behold the secrets of the inner earth!</l>
<l>There, down among the rock-roots of the hills,</l>
<l>What seest thou there? Look, as I point, even those</l>
<l>Strange miscreations, as they seem to thee,</l>
<l>Are demoniac moilers that obey</l>
<l>Such arts as I possess; the gnomish brood</l>
<l>Of Demogorgon. See them how they moil</l>
<l>Amid those diamond shafts and reefs of gold</l>
<l>Embedded in the oldest drifts of time,</l>

<pb n="299" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/299"/>

<l>And in the mire that was the first crude floor</l>
<l>And blind extension of the infant earth:</l>
<l>Why art thou poor, then, when such slaves as they</l>
<l>Might work for thee, and glut thy need with all</l>
<l>The matchless values which are there enwombed,</l>
<l>Serving thee always as they now serve me?</l>
<l>Nor these alone: turn thou thy looks aloft,</l>
<l>And watch the stars as they go swimming past.</l>
<l>Behold their vastness, each a world,' he said;</l>
<l>'The secrets of all these, too, thou shalt know,</l>
<l>The spirits of all these shall be thy slaves,</l>
<l>If thou wilt swear as erst amid the tombs.'</l></lg>

<lg><l>"The woe of desolation wrapped me round,</l>
<l>The joy to know all mysteries tempted me,</l>
<l>And with a shudder that shook me to the soul</l>
<l>I swore, as erst I swore amid the tombs.</l></lg>

<lg><l>"As on my hand he placed a signet-ring,</l>
<l>Suddenly loud the desert winds arose,</l>
<l>And blew with mighty stress among the tents;</l>
<l>And instantly aloft the thunder ran,</l>
<l>A mighty issue of miraculous light</l>
<l>Burst shaft-like forward, smiting him in twain,</l>

<pb n="300" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/300"/>

<l>Or so it seemed, down through the solid earth.</l>
<l>In vain I shrunk into a dim recess;</l>
<l>Before me stood the son of paradise.</l>
<l>Then leapt the soul to life within my heart—</l>
<l>Leapt into life with fear, and pain, and woe—</l>
<l>Anger and sadness both were on his brow.</l></lg>

<lg><l>"'Could'st thou no trial bear—all but redeemed;</l>
<l>Could'st thou not rest content? a rabbi's child!</l>
<l>Enjoy as best thou may this ill-won power</l>
<l>Over the darker agencies of time,</l>
<l>And bide the end, which end is punishment</l>
<l>But the more terrible, the more delayed;</l>
<l>Yet know this also, thou shalt thus no more</l>
<l>Be punished in a body built of clay.'</l>
<l>He vanished, leaving me to sharp remorse,</l>
<l>And harrowed with the thought of his grieved look.</l>
<l>'And yet no power in heaven or hell,' I said,</l>
<l>'May now annul my deed.'</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">"And not one day</l>
<l>Of joy has brought to me my 'ill-won power.'</l>
<l>I built vast palaces in quiet view</l>
<l>Of ancient cities, or by famous streams;</l>

<pb n="301" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/301"/>

<l>I filled my halls with men and women fair,</l>
<l>And with these pages of a beauty rare</l>
<l>Like striplings kidnapped from some skirt of heaven;</l>
<l>Yet sorrowful of countenance withal,</l>
<l>As knowing that their mortal doom is joined</l>
<l>With mine irrevocably, that with me</l>
<l>'Tis theirs to own these shows of time, with me</l>
<l>To live—with me to die. And as, 'tis said,</l>
<l>A hunted roe will evermore beat round</l>
<l>Towards whence he started first, I felt at length</l>
<l>An ardent longing for my native place;</l>
<l>That spot in all the earth where only I,</l>
<l>In tasting of it, had divined the worth</l>
<l>And Sabbath quality of household peace.</l>
<l>Then coming hither, thus constrained, I pitched</l>
<l>My dwelling here, even this thou seest; built fair,</l>
<l>And filled with splendours such as never yet</l>
<l>Under one roof-tree on this earth were stored.</l>
<l>See yon surpassing lustres! Could this orb</l>
<l>Show such? From Mars came that; from Venus this;</l>
<l>And yonder mass of sun-bright glory, that</l>
<l>From Mercury came, whence came these viols, too,</l>
<l>Instinct with fervent music such as ne'er</l>
<l>From earthly instruments might thrill abroad."</l></lg>

<pb n="302" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/302"/>

<lg><l>Then seizing one of them, even as she spake,</l>
<l>Over its chords she moved her ivory hand,</l>
<l>And instantly the palace domes throughout</l>
<l>Rang resonant, as every hall and crypt</l>
<l>Were pulsing music from a thousand shells</l>
<l>That still ran confluent with a mellow slide</l>
<l>And intercourse of cadence: sweet, and yet</l>
<l>Most mournful and most weird, and oft intoned</l>
<l>With a wild wilfulness of power that worked</l>
<l>For madness more than joy. "Even such," she said</l>
<l>"Are the delights with which I most converse</l>
<l>In the dark loneness of my fated soul,</l>
<l>For all is show, not substance. All I hold</l>
<l>But darkens more the certainty I have</l>
<l>Of wrath to come, from which no change of place,</l>
<l>No earthly power, no power of heaven nor hell,</l>
<l>May shield me now. I see it shadowing forth</l>
<l>Even like a coming night, in whose dark folds</l>
<l>My soul would ask to hide itself in vain.</l>
<l>And now I go to meet the angel's face;</l>
<l>I will not claim my hundred years of pride,</l>
<l>I trample underneath my feet the gift</l>
<l>For which I sold my soul; I will not touch</l>
<l>The ring of Sammael, nor use his power</l>

<pb n="303" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/303"/>

<l>To stay the torments that devour my life;</l>
<l>Misery, shame, remorse, and dread are mine;</l>
<l>Yet shall the angel see repentant eyes,</l>
<l>And know at last I could one trial bear;</l>
<l>Too late, too late."</l></lg>

<lg><l part="F">As thus the woman spake,</l>
<l>Her brow grew dark, and suddenly she shrieked</l>
<l>In her great agony. "Oh pray for me!</l>
<l>Pray, rabbi! for the daughter of thy friend!</l>
<l>The hour is coming, nay, the hour is come!"</l></lg>

<lg><l>There was a rustle as of wings aloft,</l>
<l>A sudden flicker in the lights below,</l>
<l>And she, who until now seemed speaking, sank</l>
<l>Back on her pillow and in silence lay</l>
<l>Beautiful in the marble calm of death.</l>
<l>The rabbi gazed on her, and thought the while</l>
<l>Of those far times, when, as a child, her grace</l>
<l>Had filled with pleasantness her father's house.</l>
<l>Then to her servants gave in charge the corpse,</l>
<l>And forth he paced, much musing as he went.</l>
<l>At length he turned to gaze once more upon</l>

<pb n="304" facs="/corpix/english/harpur/h689/h689j/304"/>

<l>The silent house of death. Can such things be?</l>
<l>All had evanished like a morning mist!</l>
<l>Only the woods that hung like clouds about</l>
<l>The steeps of Hebron, in the whitening dawn</l>
<l>Lay dark against the sky! Only a pool</l>
<l>Gleamed flat before him, where it seemed erewhile</l>
<l>The splendid palace had adorned the view!</l>
<l>Perplexed in mind, the rabbi turned again</l>
<l>And hurried homeward, muttering as he went:</l>
<l>"Was it a vision? Can such marvels be?</l>
<l>But what in truth are all things, even those</l>
<l>That seem most solid—dust and air at last!"</l></lg></div>

</text></body></TEI>
